<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The antapology of the melancholy stander-by in answer to the dean of St. Paul's late book, falsly stiled, An apology for writing against the Socinians, &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Wettenhall, Edward, 1636-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 227 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65532</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1487</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8064</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11981401</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11981401</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51847</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65532)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51847)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 523:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The antapology of the melancholy stander-by in answer to the dean of St. Paul's late book, falsly stiled, An apology for writing against the Socinians, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Wettenhall, Edward, 1636-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 68 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [3].</note>
                  <note>Page 6 is cropped and p. 38 print is faded in filmed copy. Pages beginning-39 photographed from Bodleian Library copy and inserted at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sherlock, William, 1641?-1707. --  Apology for writing against the Socinians.</term>
               <term>Socinianism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51847:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51847:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ANTAPOLOGY OF THE Melancholy Stander-by: In Anſwer To the DEAN of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s late Book, falſly ſtiled, <hi>An Apology for Writing against the Socinians,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Diſputandi Pruritus est Scabies Eccleſiae.</l>
               <l>Errare poſſum, Haereticus eſſe nolo.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year MDCXCIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:51847:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51847:2"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THE following Anſwer was writ, for the main Body of it, ſome time ago at the Author's Home, in great Diſadvantage, as will appear by divers Paſſages in it. Since he wrote it, he has had Occaſion to come abroad; and though in his way he has met with divers Books which at home he wanted, yet ſome very needful ones he could not come by, or in travelling had not leiſure to ſearch. If therefore in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Inſtances Authorities be wanting, and in others not particularly or exactly enough cited, he hopes the Reader will pardon what is more his preſent Infelicity than Fault. Had not the Uſage he has found with the pretended Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſt been unſufferably bad, he had born it in Silence. And he hopes he has here vindicated himſelf without Gall, though with much Imperfection.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:51847:3"/>
            <head>CONTENTS of the ſeveral Sections.</head>
            <list>
               <item>§. 1. <hi>THE Dean of St.</hi> Paul'<hi>s calumnious Way of</hi> apologizing, <hi>no Argument of his Skill in School-Divinity.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>The true State of the</hi> Matter of Fact <hi>between Dr.</hi> Sherlock <hi>and the</hi> melancholy Stander-by.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>A further Explication of the ſame, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with ſome Account of the</hi> Doctrine of the Trinity, <hi>and where the</hi> melancholy Stander-by <hi>would have Divines ſtop, both as to</hi> Faith <hi>and as to</hi> Peace. <hi>Dr.</hi> Sherlock <hi>ſtopped not here.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>A Deſcent to Particulars injuriouſly charged on me by the Dean of St.</hi> Paul'<hi>s: and an Account of his</hi> Arts in perverting my Senſe.</item>
               <item>5. <hi>What I meant by the</hi> Latitude <hi>wherein I would have Faith left; and what by</hi> Simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city.</item>
               <item>6. <hi>A Defence of the Reflection I made on the</hi> Maſter of the Sentences <hi>and the School-Doctors, as to their</hi> Diſputes <hi>and</hi> Deciſions <hi>in the Doctrine of the</hi> Trinity.</item>
               <item>7. <hi>My Apology as to the</hi> Idleneſs <hi>and</hi> Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfulneſs <hi>in the</hi> School-Doctors, <hi>charged upon me by Mr. Dean.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>8. <hi>A Vindication of what I avouched touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the</hi> Judgment of the firſt Reformers <hi>as to the School-Divinity and</hi> School-terms in our Prayers. <hi>The Judgment of later Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines as to this ſecond Point.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>9. <hi>An Anſwer to Mr. Dean's Objection touching my Plea for ſticking to</hi> Scripture-Language.</item>
               <item>10. <hi>It ſeems not poſſible by any Words ſo to fix the Senſe of all controverted Places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but that</hi> Hereticks <hi>may have</hi> Evaſions. <hi>Yet this is no Prejudice to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Scripture-Terms and Language.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>11. <hi>A</hi> Defence <hi>of the</hi> Latitude <hi>I plead for: and by the by, of the</hi> Negative Belief.</item>
               <item>12. <hi>An Anſwer to Mr. Dean's Objection of one Faith.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>13. <hi>A Reaſſertion of my Reaſons for forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing new Diſcourſes on this Subject; by ſome Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the</hi> Advantage <hi>Dr.</hi> Sherlock'<hi>s Book of the Trinity has given the</hi> Socinians and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts.</item>
               <item>14. <hi>A Reaſſertion of my other Reaſon by the late Writings, that the</hi> Improvements <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be made in Explication of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, have only</hi> imbroiled and expoſed it. <hi>Of</hi> Geometrical Attempts <hi>this way.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>15. <hi>My Defence for ſettling the uſual Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Trinity upon the</hi> Decrees <hi>of the</hi> Nicene <hi>and</hi> Conſtantinopolitan <hi>Councils. Of ſome Niceties in the</hi> Athanaſian Creed.</item>
               <item>16. <hi>An Anſwer to the Imputation of</hi> Hob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beiſm; <hi>and Mr. Dean proved to contradict himſelf.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>17. <hi>An Anſwer to a Particular or two forcibly brought in by the Apologiſt, and as would ſeem merely to inodiate me.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>18. <hi>My Aſſertion that ſome preſent Writings in this Controverſy have given</hi> Advantages to Atheiſts, <hi>vindicated.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>19. <hi>A Vindication of my ſelf from</hi> Theiſm. <hi>A Profeſſion of</hi> my Belief <hi>of the</hi> Trinity <hi>and</hi> Incarnation; <hi>and of the</hi> whole revealed Chriſtian Religion. <hi>My Senſe of</hi> Scorners.</item>
               <item>20. <hi>A Reaſſertion of the</hi> Danger of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting Fundamentals. <hi>The Dean changes them inſtead of defending them; which the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor hopes other preſent Writers will not.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>21. <hi>A Vindication of my laſt Argument touching the preſent</hi> Unſeaſonableneſs <hi>of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick diſputing this Controverſy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>22. <hi>An Anſwer to the Dean's Objection, that if we diſpute not, the World will think us all Socinians: and to an Inſinuation of his for rendring me obnoxious to the Government.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>23. <hi>An Account of what I meant by</hi> fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Time and Place <hi>for taking the Socinian Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies into Conſideration: and a Vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of what I propoſed in the mean time.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>24. <hi>An Anſwer to ſome Queſtions which Mr. Dean puts to me, and particularly as to</hi> admitting Socinians <hi>to ſome kind of</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. <hi>Some Points by him unduly ſtated and imputed to the Socinians.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>25. <hi>A Reaſſertion of my Senſe touching the</hi> Acts of Parliament <hi>in Favour of</hi> Diſſenters: <hi>and an Anſwer to ſome Reproaches.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>26. <hi>A Reaſſertion of what I aſſerted done as to</hi> Reformation <hi>in King</hi> Edward <hi>the VIth's Time, without a</hi> Convocation.</item>
               <item>27. <hi>An Anſwer to his good Will</hi> for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming me out of the Church. <hi>His falſe Charge on me touching Dr.</hi> Wallis <hi>noted, and his Diſceſſion from the Doctrine of the Church r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſerted. His</hi> Hypotheſis <hi>juſtifies</hi> Neſtorianiſm.</item>
               <item>28. <hi>An Anſwer to his</hi> concluſory Aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; <hi>and an Animadverſion upon his Promiſe of deſending his Vindication of the Trinity.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51847:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The ANTAPOLOGY of the</hi> Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly Stander-by. <hi>In Anſwer to the Dean of St.</hi> Paul'<hi>s late Book, falſly ſtiled,</hi> An Apology for writing againſt the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians.</head>
            <p>SOME Men have ſuch a peculiar Talent at Inſolence and ill<note place="margin">§. 1.</note> Language, that it is difficult for a modeſt Perſon, or one who would obſerve the common Rules of good Manners, to give them a meet Anſwer. In the Rank of ſuch Writers I am ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry I muſt place the late Apologiſt. I could have wiſhed, upon many Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, that in the Reflections he has been pleaſed to make on my Paper, he had, for his own ſake as well as mine, uſed more Temper. Reproach and Scorn is an eaſy way of confuting: And 'tis not without Difficulty that humane Nature forbears rendring an angry or diſdainful Reply to haughty and ill-natur'd Anſwers. In ſuch caſe, <hi>Calcare faſtum majori faſtu,</hi> ſeems to too many a Point of Juſtice; but I ſhall not eſteem it ſo, deſiring to pardon ſuch Practice in others, rather than in my ſelf. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing therefore my Mind, and quitting, as near as I am able, all Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Self-love, over-looking the Contempt, and many of the Indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and falſe Imputations, yea and ſome (at leaſt ſeemingly) malicious Inſinuations to thoſe in Authority, which he has thought fit to print a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, I ſhall return nothing but <hi>the Words of Truth and Soberneſs,</hi> without Cavil, or even Contradiction, any further than Juſtice requires: Only becauſe an accuſed Perſon cannot ordinarily make his Defence, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he be admitted as well to diſcover and complain of the Wrong done him, as to deny and diſprove; and being that the faireſt Laws of Diſpute allow, as occaſion offers, to retort upon the Adverſary his own Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; theſe things I muſt demand to be lawful for me: which Liberty being granted me, I ſhall endeavour, without warm Water, to wipe off the Dirt that Mr. Dean has caſt upon me.</p>
            <p>Whereas therefore he is pleaſed to charge me with want of School-Divinity, (touching which I ſhall ſay more anon) I who have no great
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51847:4"/> Confidence or Opinion of my own Learning in any kind, but am an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirer of all kinds of uſeful Learning, where-ever I find it, would have been glad to have had occaſion for Admiration at his Skill in the more uſeful Part of the Divinity of the Schools, I mean in their Morals; which had his Reverence better read, or better remembred, he would not have defended his fine new Notions with Calumny. The Angelical Doctor, and the ſeveral Commentators on his Text, would have taught him bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter [<hi>Non licitum eſſe calumnioſe ſe defendere] 2dâ 2dae qu. 69. a</hi> 2. The Dean's way of dealing with me, enforces me ſo particularly to cite the Place, leſt hereafter again he ſhould take occaſion to tell the World, as ſo often he does in other Caſes, with equal Truth and Modeſty, that I have not read the Author.</p>
            <p>With a Plea of this Nature (I mean calumnious) it is that he begins what he calls his Apology for writing againſt the Socinians, excuſing himſelf for <hi>his long Silence</hi> (more truly the Impoſſibility of the thing) in not vindicating his late Vindication. His Excuſe is a Pretence of <hi>a long and patient Expectation what the learned Writers of ſome Controverſies at preſent would bring forth;</hi> and the learned Writers he will have to be the Character given by me of the <hi>Socinians.</hi> How far he is ſincere in this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <hi>Patience,</hi> I will not venture ſo much as to gueſs; but his own Conſcience tells him, and God, who is not mocked, knows. As to his pretending that by the late <hi>learned Writers of Controverſies</hi> I mean the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians;</hi> not to expoſe him for this as an Excuſe doubly wanting Art, (firſt in the Choice of it, then in the putting it off with no better a Gloſs) it lies groſly open, and whoſoever runs and reads may ſee the Prevaricati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: I take it as a wilful Miſtake, and in a word, a down-right Calumny. I prove it a Miſtake by ſolemnly proteſting I meant no ſuch thing: and ſurely to this my Proteſtation, Belief cannot be denied; for could a Man have ſo little Senſe as to deſire the Socinians not to write againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? And I prove it a wilful Miſtake by his own Text; for after he has ſaid twice, (<hi>pag. 1. lin.</hi> 2. &amp; <hi>p. 2. l.</hi> 4.) that I meant the Socinians by thoſe Terms, he as in the ſame Breath (<hi>p. 2. l.</hi> 10.) complains, <hi>himſelf and Dr.</hi> Wallis <hi>to be more immediately concerned in this Suit for For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance.</hi> This laſt he ſpoke true, and knew it to be ſo: Therefore the other is a wilful Miſtake, or what I will not name. And again, he cites and repeats, <hi>p.</hi> 24. a different Character I gave the Socinians, whom I repreſented not as learned; and as far as I know any of them, I have found them rather to affect the Reputation of Religious Simplicity than Learning. Now though I acknowledg Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> and Dr. <hi>Wallis</hi> (I ſhould for all Reaſons, except that of Preferments, have ſaid Dr. <hi>Wallis</hi> and Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>) to be learned Writers: Yet God forbid I ſhould inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51847:4"/> to the World touching them, (what one of them has done touching me) that they are Socinians. Further, if he had had any Thoughts that hereby I meant the Socinians, why does he tax me (<hi>p.</hi> 18.) for not tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Socinians what Injuries they do by their writing in this Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy. If this Term be interpreted equally to belong to both Sides, I have told one as much as the other of the Miſchief they do. This then, becauſe it is ſaid falſly (and contrary to his own Senſe) againſt me: And further (as far as I can perceive) with a Deſign to render me odious, or to confute my Paper by drawing its Author under Reproach, as an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toller and Applauder of Socinians; I challenge as a Calumny, and ſay it is ſuch a Defence as ſhews no Skill in School-Divinity, nor in the fair Laws of Diſputation.</p>
            <p>By this Beginning it may eaſily be gueſſed what Candour and Sincerity I am treated with in the Progreſs, Body, and even Concluſion of his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy. Waving therefore many Inſtances of like Diſingenuity, I ſhall, as a fit Preparatory to all Particulars, preſent here the main State of the Cauſe betwixt us.</p>
            <p>The Author of the <hi>Suit for Forbearance</hi> had deſired that the <hi>Diſputes</hi>
               <note place="margin">§. 2.</note> touching the Controverſies of the <hi>Holy Trinity,</hi> might be at preſent <hi>let alone till fit Time and Place.</hi> What he meant by fit Time and Place, he will ſhew anon: And to perſwade to this he had ſaid, <hi>This particular Controverſy is of all others at preſent moſt unreaſonable, moſt dangerous, and moſt unſeaſonable.</hi> And as he took the Name of the <hi>melancholy Stander-by,</hi> merely to inſinuate a peaceable Temper, ſo he endeavoured to write as a Peace-maker; and to that purpoſe would appear under the fitteſt Qualification of ſuch, namely, as a Perſon violent on neither ſide: notwithſtanding he conceives, in what he wrote, there is much more Tenderneſs ſhewn, and more ſaid in favour of the eſtabliſh'd Church, of which he all along in his Diſcourſe profeſſes himſelf (what he really and cordially is) a Member, than the moſt uncharitable Logick can force from any thing he has ſaid, or deſired, in reference to the Socinians.</p>
            <p>And where is the Miſchief of all this? Is it <hi>Treaſon in Divinity,</hi> or is it Hereſy, to move for Peace, at leaſt for a Truce, till both Parties are calmed, and may calmly treat? This was moſt plainly all that that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor deſigned or moved for: And he is ſo far from repenting his Motion, notwithſtanding the Treatment he has received, that he now renews it, and thinks in Conſcience he ought ſo to do; he beſeeches, as upon his Knees, that Proteſtants agreeing in the common Rule of a holy Life, (the ſure way to Heaven) and keeping to the Holy Scripture, and the common Creed, uſually called the Apoſtles, as the Summary of Faith contained in Scripture, would give over making Hereticks of one another: That thoſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51847:5"/> who have private Opinions of their own, different from what is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accounted and called Orthodox, would keep their Singularities to themſelves; (<hi>Haſt thou Faith? have it to thy ſelf:</hi>) that if any have ſo little Temper as to contend for private Opinions, others at preſent would either for the ſake of Peace and Holineſs, wink at the Errors and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Spirits of ſuch Men, or at leaſt not exaggerate, at this Juncture of Time, any Points in Difference amongſt us. He declares himſelf, not to be without Hopes that Poſterity may, in no long Time, find ſome Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedients for uniting Proteſtants; though it be true many things muſt firſt be done preliminary hereto. If he be miſtaken in theſe his Sentiments, prove him ſo, and then call him imprudent, weak, ſhallow in his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Counſels, and Opinion of things, unfit to ſay any thing by way of publick Advice, and what elſe of that Nature you pleaſe. This, in ſuch caſe, would be a juſt and modeſt Reprehenſion of him, and what I am ſure the Man will meekly take. But to make him black and odious by all Arts, and to talk of reforming him out of the Church for his peaceable Deſires and Well-meaning, is imperious beyond Meaſure, and what another would call Tyrannical, (nor will he name what Spirit it beſpeaks) eſpecially when the great Argument, or Foundation of all, againſt what he has ſaid, is no better than a <hi>Petitio Principii,</hi> or taking for granted the prime Matter in queſtion, namely, that <hi>the Doctrine of the Trinity as Dr.</hi> Sherlock <hi>has ſtated, and does defend it, is a Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental of the Chriſtian Faith.</hi> This the Dean in his Apology has not offered one Word to prove; but quitting his Adverſaries, and ſhutting both Eyes and Ears againſt all that has been ſaid againſt his Novelties on this Subject, violently falls upon expoſing the peaceable Man, which was indeed much the eaſier Project; but whether either Chriſtian or Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the World will judg.</p>
            <p>The <hi>melancholy Stander-by</hi> had aſſerted in his <hi>7th</hi> Page, <hi>the Doctrine of the Trinity, as duly ſtated, to be one of the Fundamentals of Chriſtian Religion.</hi> And it is moſt plain, by what he propounds as the <hi>Medium</hi> of Peace, that the ſtating it <hi>according to Scripture, and in Scripture-Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage,</hi> he eſteems the moſt due ſtating it: the Dean likes not this, ſays it is a Propoſal of old Hereticks, and not only would have the Philoſophical Terms, now a long time uſual in this Point, received for Peace-ſake, but as Fundamental in Faith: Nay, and not content herewith, he gives new Definitions of, or affixes new Notions to theſe Terms, and would have all paſs upon us ſtill under the Colour of Fundamentals. The <hi>melancholy Stander-by</hi> (to ſpeak the whole Truth) neither could nor can admit ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe, namely, either that Philoſophical Terms, never uſed by Scripture, and beſides of various Uſe or uncertain Signification, ſhould
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51847:5"/> be made Fundamentals of Faith; or that the Doctor's new Explication of them ſhould paſs at all; and his Reaſons may perhaps appear anon. But in what he writ he expreſs'd not this his Diſſent, ſo as to conteſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe Points: Only as he would not enter into the Controverſy himſelf, ſo he deſired (chiefly by reaſon of the Miſchief he thought he ſaw ariſing from thence) it might be at preſent forborn by all; and he is ſtill as willing as ever to decline engaging on either Point, only in his own Defence, againſt what the Dean has endeavoured to load him with; he muſt now ſay, that if any ſhould join Iſſue with the Dean upon the firſt Article of the Nicene Creed, <hi>I BELIEVE IN ONE GOD,</hi> &amp;c. which is a Fundamental, and the true Catholick and Apoſtolick Faith: It will ſoon appear that Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> has in his Book contradicted, and to his Power overthrown that Faith, as much as ever <hi>Johannes Philoponus,</hi> or <hi>Joachim</hi> the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>So the Text of the</hi> Decretal <hi>ſtiles him.</hi>
               </note> Florentine Abbot, [or as others, the Abbot of <hi>Floria</hi> or <hi>Flency</hi>] the two greateſt and moſt antient Leaders of the Tritheiſts ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily aſſigned, ever did: for according to the beſt Accounts of them, neither of theſe expreſly maintained more Gods than one, nay they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly diſclaimed ſuch Aſſertion; only they ſo taught the Nature and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of three Perſons, as that their Doctrine inferred three Gods: from which Charge the Invention of <hi>mutual Conſciouſneſs</hi> will never clear <hi>Dr.</hi> Sherlock'<hi>s Definition of a Perſon in the Godhead;</hi> for ſuch Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, whatever he ſays to the contrary, can infer only an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord,</hi> not of <hi>Subſtance and Nature;</hi> whereas it is an Unity of Subſtance and Nature that the Council and Fathers have held: but theſe things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire more Words than the preſent Deſign admits.</p>
            <p>To make the Sum of my Sentiments (or what I would be at) plainer.<note place="margin">§. 3.</note> The holy Scripture ſtates the Trinity under the Notion of <hi>Three bearing witneſs in Heaven,</hi> (for I have much more to ſay for that exagitated Text than to allow it wanting in any Copies on any other Reaſon but their Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection) and affirms <hi>theſe three one;</hi> but how they are one it deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines not: And <hi>Faith</hi> being a <hi>Belief of the Witneſs of God,</hi> and <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm a Seal</hi> or Badg <hi>of Faith;</hi> when we are baptized, we are baptized <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>into the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt,</hi> as own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and aſſenting to, or profeſſing and vowing to acquieſce in their Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs touching all the whole Will of God, and Method of Salvation pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in the Goſpel. This is <hi>Scripture,</hi> and here the <hi>melancholy Stander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi> would <hi>ſtop as to Faith</hi> in this Point of the Trinity. To the Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion there is yet no occaſion to ſpeak.</p>
            <p>The Fathers in the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> did not (as far as ever I could per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by any genuine Monuments of theirs) vote the Term <hi>three Perſons,</hi> the <hi>Incarnation of the Son of God,</hi> or his Divinity, (though made Man)
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51847:6"/> was the Controverſy before them, rather than the Trinity; and the great Product of that Council was the word (<hi>Homoouſion</hi>) in Aſſertion of the Son's being of the ſame Subſtance with the Father: But the Greek Fathers of that Age did ſoon uſe the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (which in this Caſe is moſt aptly rendred Subſiſtence) and contend for three <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Subſiſtences. Now as to the common Definition of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (<hi>in divinis</hi>) that is, to my beſt Memory, pretended to be taken out of <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> by <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcen,</hi> a Father of much latter Age: I ſaid to my beſt Memory; for my Condition is ſuch at preſent, and has been ſuch upward of four Years, that I am without the Uſe of the beſt part of my Books, and now near 150 Engliſh Miles diſtant from a Library: Yet I thank God I am Maſter of <hi>Juſtin</hi> and <hi>Damaſcen</hi> more ways than one, (be it ſpoken without Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front to Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> in caſe of my having read other Books) I had read them near two and thirty Years ago. But to return to the Definition ſpoken of, as now I take it out of my old (perhaps too imperfect) Notes, runs thus: <q>In the Holy Trinity an Hypoſtaſis is an unbegun (or if the<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Damaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en. Dialectic. cap. ult.</note> Word may be pardoned, a beginningleſs) manner of the eternal Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence of each [that is of Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt.]</q> So that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this Author, it ſuperadds nothing to the Divine Eſſence, which is one and common to all the three, ſave a bare manner of Exiſtence or Subſiſtence. Only by the way I muſt note, as to the Authority of that Piece in the Works of <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> whence this Definition comes, namely, the <hi>Expoſitio rectae fidei;</hi> it is ſufficiently proved by <hi>Scultetus, Rivet</hi> and others, to be none of <hi>Juſtin</hi>'s genuine Works.</p>
            <p>The Latin Fathers which came ſoon upon the Heels of the Council, and of the Greek Fathers above ſpoken of, ſuſpected this Word <hi>Hypoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis,</hi> (and St. <hi>Jerome</hi> particularly) contended there was Poiſon under the<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Epiſtol. ad Damaſ. Tom. 2.</note> Honey, and boggled at it. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> acknowledges he <hi>underſtood not the Difference</hi> the Greeks deſigned between <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (that is in our preſent Language, between Eſſence and Subſiſtence) <hi>But becauſe,</hi> ſays he, <hi>according to our Cuſtom of Speech, Eſſence and Subſtance are all one,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Trinitat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. 5. in fine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>apitis 8, &amp; cap. 9.</note> 
               <hi>therefore we dare not ſay one Eſſence three Subſtances, but one Eſſence or Subſtance, and three Perſons.</hi> So that when they laid aſide <hi>Hypoſtaſis,</hi> they introduced a Term equivalent, and perhaps more ambiguous, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Perſona;</hi> and then ſaid there were three Perſons in one Eſſence: Yet at the ſame time St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> acknowledgeth the Uſe of this Term impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and that it was Neceſſity drove them to it; they uſed this Word for<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>agna prorſus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>opia huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> laborat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>quium. Dictum eſt tamen tres perſonae, non ut illud diceretur, ſed ne taceretur. Non enim rei <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bilis eminentia hoc vocabulo explicare valet. Cap. 9.</note> want of a better: <hi>The Father,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt are truly three: But when it is demanded, three what? humane
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51847:6"/> Speech is defective; notwithſtanding we have ſaid three Perſons, not that ſtrictly we mean or intend to ſay this, but leſt we ſhould be ſilent, and ſay nothing; for the Tranſcendency of the ineffable Matter cannot be expreſs'd by this Word.</hi> And again more fully in his ſeventh Book, proving the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, to be one, becauſe the Father is Wiſdom, the Son Wiſdom, and the Holy Ghoſt Wiſdom; and in God to be wiſe, is the ſame as to be, and to be the ſame, as to be God: <hi>Therefore,</hi> ſays he, <hi>for expreſſing what is inexpreſſible, that we may ſpeak in ſome meaſure, what we cannot ſpeak out, the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Itaque loquendi causâ de ineffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilibus, ut fari aliquo modo poſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, quod effari nullo modo poſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, dictum eſt à noſtris Graecis, una Eſſentia, tres Subſtantiae: a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinis autem, una Eſſentia, tres Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonae. Et ut intelligatur in aenig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate quod dicitur placuit, ita dici, ut aliquid diceretur. Ut quaerere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur quid tria ſunt, quid tres confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimus nos ad inveniendum aliquid ſpeciale vel generale nomen, quo complectamus haec tria; neque oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currit animo, quia excedit ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminentia divinitatis uſitati eloquii facultatem. Cap. 3, &amp; 4.</note> 
               <hi>Grecian Chriſtians have ſaid one Eſſence, three Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances</hi> [that is, Subſiſtences:] <hi>and the Latins, one Eſſence, three Perſons: And that what we ſay may be underſtood</hi> [at leaſt] <hi>in a Riddle; we thought it good thus it ſhould be ſaid, that ſomething might be ſaid. When it is required what theſe three are, we apply our ſelves to find out ſome ſpecial or general Name where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may comprize all the three: nor does there any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur to our Thoughts, becauſe the Tranſcendency of the Divinity exceeds the Faculty of uſual Speech.</hi> He goes on to the Effect following: <q>If we take theſe three, <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> we can find ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what common, which they all have, and ſay they are three Men: but touching Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, we cannot ſay they are three Fathers, or three Sons [nor indeed three Gods,] what therefore are the three?</q> Three Perſons. By all which it is plain they uſed this word <hi>Perſons,</hi> not becauſe it was proper, but becauſe the Speculation was run ſo fine that they knew not what elſe, or what leſs improper to ſay. And let this ſuffice in my preſent Penury of Books, as to the Fathers, who of old either firſt introduced, or by their Uſe firſt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized (<hi>in divinis</hi>) this Term, <hi>three Perſons,</hi> or <hi>a Trinity of Perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the Senſe of the School-Doctors, touching the word <hi>Perſona</hi> in this Controverſy, I muſt ſpeak chiefly out of my Memory, having beſides the Maſter of the Sentences, and ſome imperfect pieces of others, only St. <hi>Thomas</hi>'s Sum at hand, in which Work he is ſomewhat brief on this Term: Yet even therein when he concludes it convenient that the Name <hi>Perſon</hi> be uſed touching God, he does it with this Limitation, that <hi>it be</hi>
               <note place="margin">Conveniens eſt ut hoc nomen perſona de Deo dicitur; non tamen eodem modo quo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur de Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turis.</note> 
               <hi>not uſed</hi> (or which is the ſame, underſtood) <hi>after the ſame manner as it is of the Creatures.</hi> But I do avow it, and will be bound to produce Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies enough, as ſoon as I can come at Books, that it is both his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and the common Doctrine of his Followers, that the word <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> when uſed touching God and the Creatures, is not taken in the ſame
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51847:7"/> 
               <hi>equal or univocal Senſe, but only by way of Proportion: and as to the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi>
               <note place="margin">Perſona de Deo &amp; Creaturis non dici univo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce ſed analogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce.</note> 
               <hi>of ſignifying and Impoſition of the Name, it firſt and more properly agrees to the Creatures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to Proteſtant Divines alſo, for the Reaſons above touched I muſt be ſparing in their Numbers; but I am ſure the Syſtematiſts ordinarily aſſign either four or five Differences in the Uſe of the Word, when attributed to God and to the Creature: And I find by me in my Notes, this Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, which I long ſince tranſcribed out of <hi>Zanchy,</hi> a judicious and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Calviniſt: <hi>In the Creatures one Perſon is not only</hi>
               <note place="margin">Una Perſona [creata ex contex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu precedente ſupplenda] ab altera non tam diſtincta quam etiam diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncta eſt; at proinde diverſae ſunt inter ſe ſubſtantiae, licet unius natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae. In Deo una Perſona ab altera diſtincta quidem eſt, ſed disjuncta eſſe non poreſt, &amp;c. De tribus E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lohim, Parte <hi>2da.</hi> lib. 1. c. 3.</note> 
               <hi>diſtinct from the other, but disjoined and ſeparate; ſo that the Subſtances are divers, though the Nature one: But in God one Perſon is indeed diſtinct from the other, but cannot be disjoined, and therefore the Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are not only of the ſame Nature, (for ſo are hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Perſons) but of the ſame Eſſence. Nay, they ſo ſubſiſt in the ſame Eſſence, that they are indeed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but that Eſſence.</hi> Somewhat very near this the Doctor, to do him Juſtice, more than once or twice expreſly ſays in his Book, I mean, in his <hi>Vindication of the Holy Trinity (viz.)</hi> p. 47, 67, 104, &amp;c. <hi>that they are diſtinct, not ſeparate:</hi> but then he in effect unſays all again much oftner: and that both by his Definition of a <hi>Perſon, in divinis,</hi> and in thoſe other Paſſages of his, produced by me in my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, (<hi>p.</hi> 14.) and by many other Paſſages, which I might tranſcribe from him. For my own part, I am not able to excuſe him from contradicting himſelf over and over, moſt plainly, in the Space of a dozen Lines, in one of the Pages now cited, (<hi>viz.</hi> 67. of his <hi>Vindication;</hi>) for firſt he acknowledges, <q>Theſe three Divine Perſons are not ſeparate Minds, as created Spirits are, but only diſtinct: each Perſon has a Self-conſciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his own, and knows and feels it ſelf (if I may ſo ſpeak) as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from the other Divine Perſons. The Father has a Self-conſciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his own, whereby he knows and feels himſelf to be the Father, and not the Son nor Holy Ghoſt: And the Son in like manner feels him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be the Son, and not the Father, nor the Holy Ghoſt: And the Holy Ghoſt feels himſelf to be the Holy Ghoſt, and not the Father nor the Son;</q> as <hi>James</hi> feels himſelf to be <hi>James,</hi> and not <hi>Peter</hi> nor <hi>John.</hi> I ſay then, if the Father hath a Self-conſciouſneſs of his own, whereby he knows and feels himſelf to be the Father, and not the Son, nor the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>as</hi> James <hi>feels himſelf to be</hi> James <hi>and not</hi> Peter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then both is he ſeparate from the Son and Holy Ghoſt, and his Self-conſciouſneſs alſo ſeparate from the Self-conſciouſneſs of each the other. And again, if the Father, Son and Spirit, feel himſelf to be himſelf, and not the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51847:7"/> other, as <hi>James</hi> feels himſelf to be <hi>James,</hi> and not <hi>Peter</hi> nor <hi>John;</hi> then muſt each feel himſelf ſeparate from the other: For 'tis manifeſt to me, that in knowing and feeling my ſelf not to be <hi>Peter</hi> nor <hi>James,</hi> I know and feel my ſelf ſeparate, ſevered, or ſeveral from them. Nay it is by knowing and feeling my ſelf ſeparate, that I know and feel my ſelf diſtinct. If therefore the Father knows and feels himſelf diſtinct from the Son, and from the Holy Ghoſt, as we Men know our ſelves diſtinct from one another, he then muſt know and feel himſelf ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate alſo unavoidably, or elſe he does not know and feel himſelf diſtinct as we do. He muſt therefore upon this Hypotheſis be ſeparate as well as diſtinct from the other: Beſides, three infinite Minds (as he there, and <hi>p.</hi> 50. and ſo onwards, moſt frequently and familiarly ſtiles the three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons) and one infinite Mind, that is, three ſames, and not three ſames, are to me an unavoidable Contradiction: But it had been at leaſt no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction to have ſaid, one infinite Mind, or a Subſtance, may have three manners of Subſiſting, or three ſeveral Relations, which was the old way of ſpeaking; and which if it had been kept to, the <hi>melancholy Stander-by</hi> had forborn his Suit. That ancient Notion of a Divine Perſon is more conſiſtent, and much leſs obnoxious; though how far ſatisfactory it may be to all Men, he diſputes not: however he does account it to be the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Orthodox Doctrine, now many hundred Years received. And here he would have our Divines to ſtop, as a common Boundary, for Peace: and his Reaſon is, becauſe here our Articles which were (as is ſaid in the very Title of them) agreed upon for the avoiding of Diverſities of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and for the eſtabliſhing Conſent touching Religion, do ſtop; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing only, or ſtating to us the Doctrine of three Perſons in the Terms, wherein from old Times it has been delivered down; and therefore in all Likelihood deſigning only the old Senſe. This is but more clearly and explicitely what the <hi>Suit for Forbearance</hi> deſired of Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> and other preſent Writers in this Controverſy. Wherefore upon the whole, how juſt in this Caſe the Imputation of a <hi>diſguiſed Heretick,</hi> of a Man <hi>ſpite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful againſt the Cauſe and Perſons</hi> who maintain it; <hi>a Wolf in Sheeps clothing,</hi> and like Characters faſtned upon the Author of it, are, God will judg if the World do not. Had I either diſputed againſt the old Notion, or aſſigned any new one, or ventured at new and dangerous Explications, as ſome have done, Mr. Dean had had ſome Colour for thus treating me: But ſith I have not, I muſt tax this Language alſo as downright Calumny.</p>
            <p>But to come off from this querulous Parentheſis; Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> would not, or did not, ſtop here, as is apparent by what I have tranſcribed actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally out of his Book; however he tells the World, <hi>I did not read it.</hi> In
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51847:8"/> which Imputation I will frankly acknowledg every tittle of Truth there is, namely, I had not, when I writ, read his Book all over; for it was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of my Lodging (without my Knowledg or Conſent) before I had done with it; and perhaps the Doctor has no Reaſon to complain of that Miſchance: But I had looked over all, and carefully read a great part, taken Notes out of it, as will appear by my <hi>Adverſaria</hi> of that Month, yea indeed tranſcribed much more than I alledged: And I alledged not, as the Dean (to the end he might ſhuffle off a diſtinct Anſwer to me, and the Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of his Novelties) is pleaſed to ſtile them, broken Paſſages out of<note place="margin">Pag. 30.</note> his Book, but intire Definitions and Propoſitions, which contained the Subſtance of this Hypotheſis, as he ſtiles it. And I do affirm, the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, in what I ſo cited, (<hi>p.</hi> 14, &amp; 15. of my Paper) has gone moſt plainly beyond and contrary to the Doctrine both of the Fathers, Schools, and Proteſtant Divines. And in his Apology he ſeems to have gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond himſelf: For he at leaſt four times calls our Lord Jeſus, a God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnate, <hi>p.</hi> 4, 26, 27, 31. Now if the Son be a God incarnate, then the Father is a God not incarnate: And the ſame ought to be ſaid, according to this way of ſpeaking, of the Holy Ghoſt: Nay it is actually ſaid by him in theſe Words, [<hi>This Confeſſion proves the Holy Ghoſt a God,</hi> Vind. <hi>p. 190. lin. ult.</hi>] I ſay then, if there be a God, and a God, and a God, unavoidably there muſt be three Gods. And this is the very Abſurdity the Socinians would reduce their Adverſaries to: Therefore the Doctor ſo defends the Myſtery of the Trinity, or ſo confutes Hereſy, as to run in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the very ſame Abſurdity to which his Adverſaries would reduce him, which I hope we may ſay, without Offence, is moſt unreaſonable, moſt dangerous, and at preſent moſt unſeaſonable, the thing charged by the <hi>Melancholy Stander-by.</hi> This the Doctor might have evaded, had he been content to have taken up with the old Acceptation or Definition of a Perſon <hi>in divinis;</hi> or to have ſpoken with Scripture, Jeſus Chriſt is <hi>God manifeſt in the Fleſh;</hi> or if that muſt not ſuffice, as is uſual, <hi>God incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate:</hi> But the adding an individuating Particle [<hi>a</hi>] to the Name of that common Eſſence [<hi>God</hi>], and then predicating that Name ſo determined, touching the three Perſons, as it reduces the Subjects touching which it is predicated, into the Rank of common Individuals; ſo it leaves the Eſſence, when taken without that individuating Particle, in the Rank of a common <hi>Species:</hi> And ſo contrary to the conſtant Doctrine even of the Schools, God ſhall be predicated of the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, as a <hi>Species of Individuals;</hi> as <hi>Man</hi> is of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> whom all acknowledg to have been three Men: and as much muſt the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt be three Gods: Which if it be not moſt grievous Hereſy,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51847:8"/> and particularly the Hereſy of <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Which my Author ſays is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Doctrine of</hi> Greg. Naz. <hi>the great Divine.</hi> Niceph. Calliſt. Hiſt. lib. 18. cap. 48.</note> 
               <hi>Philoponus,</hi> I muſt confeſs I know not what is. I do not ſay the Dean believes three Gods, God forbid I ſhould; but I do avow, he has ſaid what neceſſarily infers three Gods: I hope therefore, according to his Promiſe, (<hi>p. 11.) he will thankfully correct this Abſurdity, and not bluſh to recant an Error.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. 4. After this my general Vindication, I am now to deſcend to the Particulars I am charged with.</p>
            <p>And firſt he charges me (in Effect in his Title-page) but more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly in <hi>Pag.</hi> 2. and in other Places, <hi>that I deſired no Body would write againſt Socinians.</hi> Whatſoever my Intent was, of which I think he wants the Gift of <hi>diſcerning Spirits</hi> to capacitate him for being a Judg; I am ſure he can never prove this Charge from my Paper; in which the only Controverſy mentioned was that of the Trinity, and poſſibly ſome of its Subdiviſions. Now it is notorious, (1) That the Socinians are not the only Perſons Heterodox in theſe Points. (2) That theſe are not the only Points in which they are Heterodox: There are alſo divers others, in which I believe in my Conſcience, they grievouſly err. The Doctor then might have written againſt the Socinians, and not meddle with the Doctrine of the Trinity. Therefore when I deſired the Controverſy of the Trinity might for the preſent be ſorborn, I did not deſire that no Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhould write againſt the Socinians.</p>
            <p>The next Touch at me, which I will remark, is, if <hi>I am a Divine of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apol. <hi>pag. 2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the Church of</hi> England, <hi>why ſhould I profeſs</hi> (he means ſtile) my ſelf <hi>a Stander-by?</hi> I anſwer, perhaps I was not ſo conceited of my Skill at the Weapon as others are: But admit I had been, muſt every one that thinks he has found out ſome new Paſs or Guard, draw preſently upon the next Man he meets begirt with a Sword? Should all of the Doctor's Degree, or mine, have written on that Subject, where had been the End of Books? I was therefore, on this Account, as well as in the Senſe before mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, a <hi>Stander-by;</hi> and on how many Scores <hi>melancholy,</hi> it is too long and too ſad to recount: I heartily pray neither Mr. Dean, nor any other Chriſtian, may have like Reaſon.</p>
            <p>But he is <hi>always very jealous of Men who are ſo tender of the wrong Side.</hi> It is evident indeed to any who reads my Paper, I have expreſs'd there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a Tenderneſs, (1) For the <hi>Church of England</hi> and <hi>the Nicene Faith.</hi> (2) For the <hi>Credit of the Reformation.</hi> (3) For <hi>Peace and Holineſs.</hi> Is any, or are all theſe the wrong Side? As to his <hi>Obſervation,</hi> which he tells us he has made, and which he ſubjoins, touching Mens <hi>Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> being <hi>due to their Inclinations,</hi> he may keep theſe his profound poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51847:9"/> Notes for better Purpoſe. I own my Inclination to the three Points mentioned, and wiſh the ſame both in him and in all Members of our Church.</p>
            <p>As to his <hi>perverting my peaceable Aſſertions,</hi> and making them <hi>what he pleaſes,</hi> by odious <hi>That is's,</hi> in the two next Paragraphs, and a multitude of other Places: Theſe are ſuch open diſingenuous Arts, that I will only note them; and having told my Reader, that this is his common way of dealing with me, to the end he may caſt Reproach and a publick Hate upon me, I will concern my ſelf to anſwer only to the more material Points, or to the Groſs of the <hi>Res ſubſtrata,</hi> which he imputes to me.</p>
            <p>I confeſs my ſelf an Enemy to ſuch open Diſputes between Proteſtants,<note place="margin">§. 5.</note> as only publiſh to the common Enemies the Diviſions of the Proteſtants. Nor do I find the Reformers to have been (whatever Mr. Dean ſays) for ſuch Diſputings: nor that the voluntary Diſputings of unauthorized Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have ever ſuppreſſed, but rather revived old Hereſies. How I would have thoſe who ſhould write in this Controverſy authorized, I will anon ſet down: In the mean time I come to that <hi>Latitude and Simplicity</hi> wherein I ſuppoſe <hi>Chriſtian Faith was delivered,</hi> and <hi>wherein I would have</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 3, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>it left;</hi> which Mr. Dean will <hi>not underſtand:</hi> And firſt he would gladly know what I mean by the Latitude of Faith.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe he ſeems to be at a great deal of Pains here to miſtake me, (another Man would have ſaid to blunder) I will tell him, that <hi>Latitude</hi> here is a <hi>metaphorical Term;</hi> and I will not be ſo exact as to ſuppoſe it tranſlated to our purpoſe either from Aſtronomy or Geography, but taking it meerly for one of the triple Dimenſions of Bodies, apply it by way of Similitude to that Extent of Signification, which Terms of any Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may naturally both in themſelves, and in their Dependance on Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedents and Subſequents, admit.</p>
            <p>All Men who have read and conſidered, do know that the ſame Words may carry with them different Notions; and that the Compaſs of thoſe different Notions, though it be bounded by the common Import of the Words, yet does often times include divers Specialties in it: And this I affirm as to the <hi>Propoſitions of Faith,</hi> both in <hi>Holy Scripture,</hi> and even in the <hi>Apoſtles Creed</hi> it ſelf. As to the latter, I inſtance in that Clauſe, <hi>He deſcended into Hell;</hi> our Divines have told us, it admits three or four<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Though it be a Chriſtian's Duty to believe every Article of this Creed, I conceive the agreeing upon ſome one Senſe, wherein to interpret every Article of it, is not ſo abſolutely neceſſary: but that ſome one of them may be taken in a LATIT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DE, and either not determined to any one Interpretation, or reſolved to be capable of more.</hi> Practic. Cat. lib. 5. §. 2.</note> Senſes: Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> himſelf allows two; and whoſoever underſtands and believes it in either of thoſe Senſes, though he ſhould haply doubt or diſtruſt the other of them, is not guilty either of Hereſy or Unbelief:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51847:9"/> No, nor (ſuppoſing that by Contention he divide not the Church or him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from it) is he to be taxed with Schiſm. Now to <hi>leave Faith in the Latitude in which it was delivered,</hi> is to <hi>impoſe no Determinations of ſuch Words or Expreſſions as neceſſary to Salvation,</hi> but to allow each Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to believe the Matter propounded in one of thoſe Senſes, whatever it be, which the Words naturally bear, and which in his Conſcience he judges the trueſt. And <hi>this Allowance</hi> I particularly demand <hi>as to the Point in hand,</hi> as ſet down, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5. 7. And <hi>ſuch Allowance</hi> in this, as well as in other diſputed Points, would, I ſay, <hi>ſoon reduce Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies</hi> amongſt Proteſtants to a <hi>very ſmall Compaſs,</hi> at leaſt <hi>the Heats</hi> in managing them would <hi>ceaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then as to what I mean by <hi>Simplicity,</hi> he ſays, <hi>I leave it to gueſs.</hi> Is this then a Word of Difficulty; or is this Phraſe, the <hi>Simplicity of Faith,</hi> unuſual and uncertain? But when no Exception elſe could be found, <hi>Nodus in ſcirpo</hi> muſt be pretended. Take then, good Mr. Dean, the <hi>Simplicity of Faith</hi> in what Senſe your good Nature can; yea, ſhould you take it even for <hi>Fooliſhneſs it ſelf,</hi> (which none can think I intended) the firſt Chapter of the firſt to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> would in a ſort juſtify the Expreſſion. But by <hi>Simplicity</hi> I meant here, as all who are not wilfully blind will underſtand me, <hi>Plainneſs, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmixedneſs, Purity.</hi> I would not have ſo much of Philoſophy vamp'd into Faith: And I am not of the Mind of that Cardinal, that <hi>we ſhould have been to ſeek for ſundry Articles of our Faith, had it not been for</hi> Ariſtotle; and (though I love him much better) I will add, for <hi>Plato</hi> either.</p>
            <p>But here I muſt anſwer (once for all) as to my <hi>Diſpleaſure with the</hi>
               <note place="margin">§. 6. <hi>Pag. 4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>School-Doctors. Pray what Hurt have they done,</hi> ſays Mr. Dean? I could give a certain Reaſon, for which I might ſay perhaps, they have done him little. But I will rather give him two other Anſwers; one I hope he will not except againſt, becauſe it is his own: <hi>They ſometimes miſtake the Fathers Senſe, whom they pretend to follow, or clog it with ſome pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Niceties of their own; by which Means this Myſtery has been confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi> Vind. <hi>p.</hi> 138. And again, <hi>p. 139. Though I do not think it impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to give a tolerable Account of the School-terms and Diſtinctions, yet that is a Work of greater Difficulty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> This we muſt take for a fair Specimen of Mr. Dean's great Skill and Reading in the School-Doctors. But my own Anſwer is, the Writings of the School-men, or rather that Vein of Study and Diſpute which they have brought into the Church of God, turning the whole Body of Chriſtianity into nice and too curious (many times idle) Queſtions, and reſolving theſe in the difficulteſt Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophical Terms, and ſo running all to thin Metaphyſical Diſtinctions, has made Religion moſtly a Buſineſs of Speculation and Wit. The En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51847:10"/> of Subtilty has very much eaten out the Heart and Vitals of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity; raiſed fruitleſs Contentions, bitter Envyings, endleſs Schiſms and Parties in the Church; deſtroyed in a great meaſure the Love of God and all good Affection, and debauch'd Faith it ſelf, for the main, into Opinion or Scepticiſm. This is my Anſwer further; I do aver the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Bleſſed Trinity is diſhonoured and expoſed by their Queſtions and Diſputes of it: And particularly, as to the <hi>Maſter of the Sentences,</hi> with whom the Dean will not allow <hi>me to be intimately acquainted,</hi> I<note place="margin">Pag. 17.</note> ſay, that had I uſed ſeverer Language touching him than that, what Stuff has he in his firſt Book made of this Doctrine by too much Subtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and too nice Enquiries, the Matter would juſtly have born it. And for a Proof hereof, If I ſhould run through all, I muſt tranſcribe in a manner his whole firſt Book: Let it therefore ſuffice of <hi>ſuch Stuff,</hi> as I juſtly called it, to give only a Taſte. Methinks theſe that follow are not ſeemly Queſtions to be put, inquired into, or diſputed, touching the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite incomprehenſible Majeſty, Creator and Lord of all. I will not therefore turn them into Engliſh; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trum Pater voluntate genuerit filium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diſtinct. VI.</note> 
               <hi>an neceſſitate? &amp; an volens vel nolens ſit Deus?</hi> And it is reſolved that the Word of God is the Son of God, by Nature, and not by his Will: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ſhould ſeem without his Will, and ſo the Father, God and a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unwillingly. The Unſoundneſs of this Reſolution ſee in <hi>Danae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>'s Cenſure</hi> on it. The next Queſtion is no more reverent; <hi>An Pater potue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diſt. VII.</note> 
               <hi>vel voluerit gignere filium? Et an hoc ſit aliqua potentia quae ſit in filio?</hi> And if the Father always had ſuch Power and ſuch Will, he had a Power and a Will to do ſomething which the Son had not; and conſequently the Son muſt not be of equal Power with the Father, nor have like Will. The Sum of the Reſolution is, <hi>Filius potuit gignere, ſed non oportuit.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; <hi>An filius ſit ſapiens à ſeipſo, vel per ſeipſum?</hi> And he reſolves it; <hi>Non eſt ſapiens a ſe, ſed de Patre &amp; à Patre:</hi> Diſt. 32. E. Again; That may ſeem a little better touching the Proceſſion of the Holy Ghoſt; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trum Spiritus ſanctus priùs vel pleniùs procedat à Patre quam à Filio?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diſt. XII.</note> And, <hi>An plenius vel magis proceſſerit à Patre quam à Filio?</hi> Now though he reſolved it in the Negative, yet (<hi>ne te perturbaret</hi>) leſt this ſhould offend any, he tells us, that the Holy Ghoſt proceeds principally from the Father; but he is found alſo to proceed from the Son: <hi>Sed hoc qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>que illi Pater dedit, non jam exiſtenti &amp; nondam habenti?</hi> Had I been Author of ſuch a Saying as this laſt, what ſhould I have heard? But who pleaſes may read more on the ſame Subject. I will conclude all this as the Maſter does a certain Section in one of the cited Diſtinctions: <hi>Sub ſil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntio potiùs eſſet praetereundum, niſi me ſuper hoc aliquid loqui cogeret inſtantia quaeren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium;</hi> which I will be content to engliſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <q>I would not have diſcovered
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51847:10"/> the Maſter's Shame, could I have, in the Judgment of ſome, eſcaped otherwiſe, without the Brand of an ignorant, impudent and falſe Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer.</q> But though I will add no more of theſe grating Places, yet I will deſire of Mr. Dean, becauſe he profeſſes <hi>to be able to give a tolerable Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of theſe Mens Terms and Diſtinctions,</hi> to ſhew if he pleaſes his Skill in any uſeful Explication of the following Paſſages: <hi>Eadem eſt Potentia</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diſt. VII. G.</note> 
               <hi>Patris quâ poteſt eſſe Pater, &amp; Filii quâ poteſt eſſe Filius.</hi> Yet he doubts not to affirm, <hi>Filii originem eſſe ab initio; at non ipſum eſſe ab initio, ſed ab initiabili.</hi> And touching the Trinity and the Holy Ghoſt; <hi>In Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diſt. XXXII. Ae.</note> 
               <hi>eſt Dilectio quae eſt Trinitas, &amp; tamen Spiritus ſanctus eſt Dilectio quae non eſt Trinita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, nec ideo duae ſunt Dilectiones.</hi> Take theſe Aſſertions ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſingly and apart by themſelves, as I deſigned them; or imagine that being all from one Hand, they ought to be conſiſtent with one another, and what pretty Employment will it be to make uſeful Divinity, I had almoſt ſaid even Senſe of them? I might add hundreds more either on this or other Subjects out of the ſame Author, but I fear it ſhould be ſaid they are hard Shells without a Kernel; and truly ſo I long thought them; and a great deal more of other Mens Writings on this Controverſy. Nor can I forbear obſerving by the way, that the learned, pious, holy and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> could not, or did not find room ſo much as for <hi>one Section;</hi> nay, that I remember, not <hi>one Queſtion and Anſwer</hi> for this <hi>whole Controverſy</hi> in his <hi>Practical Catechiſm,</hi> which yet excellently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructs us in many other Controverſies wherein Holineſs and Chriſtian De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion is concerned: But in all likelihood he judged what the Church-Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm has taught thereof, out of the Creed, to be ſufficient to any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Practice which can be ſuperſtructed hereon.</p>
            <p>Yet I muſt not thus conclude what I have to ſay for my Juſtification in my Reflection on the Maſter of the Sentences, the learned Dean being ſo well verſed in the School-men, has certainly heard of a certain <hi>Cenſure</hi> or <hi>Caution</hi> to ſome Texts of the Maſters in theſe Words, <hi>Magiſter non tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur:</hi> And what is that in plain Engliſh, but that on theſe Subjects the Maſter has writ ſo, as that his very Scholars or Partizans are aſhamed of him, and not able with all their Subtilties to defend him? One of the firſt Articles, as I take it, to which this Note is put, is, <hi>Charitas quâ di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligimus Deum &amp; proximum, eſt Spiritus ſanctus:</hi> Or, <hi>Charitas quae eſt amor Dei &amp; proximi, non eſt aliquia Creatura:</hi> that is, <q>Charity whereby we love God and our Neighbour, is no created being, but the Holy Ghoſt.</q> This would afford admirable Conſequents: But to let them paſs untouch'd; being that the Aſſertion it ſelf ſo intimately concerns the Holy Ghoſt, as to pronounce, in ſome meaſure, touching his very Quid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, as I may ſo ſpeak; and being that the Holy Ghoſt is the third Perſon
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51847:11"/> in the Trinity, this muſt neceſſarily be acknowledged to be a very conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Point in the Controverſy of the Trinity. And then neither have all the Papiſts been very Orthodox in the Diſputes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout<note place="margin">As to the Orthodoxy of all the Papiſts, in Point of the Trinity, I would ask Mr. Dean if he never heard any thing of a Deſign ſome had of getting in, or add<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Bleſſed Virgin to the Trinity, and what a Trinity they would in ſuch Caſe have made of it? Or how Orthodox that Party was in their Conceptions, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Deity or of that Trinity? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> the Trinity, as Mr. Dean ſays, <hi>Apol.</hi> p. 23. for the Maſter himſelf advanced herein a groſs heretical Propoſition; nor was the <hi>melancholy Stander-by</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquainted with the Maſter, when he only with a light Touch cenſured what the Maſter had troubled the World with on this Controverſy. For my own part, I would be unwilling to be put upon it to defend what yet the Maſter aſſerts, and after his way endeavours to prove, in another Place, touching the Holy Ghoſt, that (ſaith he) <hi>the Holy Ghoſt is an Act of Love,</hi> (ſo I render <hi>Dilectionem</hi>) or <hi>the Love of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Spiritum ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum Dilectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem eſſe ſive amorem Patris &amp; Filii, quo ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licet Pater dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git Filium, &amp; Filius Patrem. Diſt. 10. F.</note> 
               <hi>the Father, and of the Son, namely, wherewith the Father loveth the Son, and the Son the Father:</hi> Notwithſtanding that that Diſtinction has no ſuch Stricture, that I have obſerved, ſet upon it by the Scholaſtick Cenſors; and notwithſtanding too that Mr. Dean has more amply explicated and eſpouſed it, <hi>Vind.</hi> p. 130, &amp;c. <hi>The Father,</hi> ſaith the Dean, <hi>is original Mind and Wiſdom: The Son the Word and Wiſdom of the Father, that is, the reflex Knowledg of himſelf, which is the perfect Image of his own Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and the Holy Ghoſt, that Divine Love which the Father and Son have for each other.</hi> Theſe he calls <hi>three ſubſtantial Acts in God, ſo diſtinct as that they can never be the ſame.</hi> But whoſe will conſider what <hi>Idea</hi> our Minds frame of <hi>Self-reflection</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> (the Latin Term is <hi>Dilectio</hi>) will rather ſtile theſe <hi>immanent Actions,</hi> how permanent ſoever they may be ſuppoſed. Now that an Action, though immanent, can be a <hi>living, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent Subſtance,</hi> an <hi>infinite eternal Mind,</hi> is what I would be loth to be bound to the Proof of.</p>
            <p>But ſays the Dean, <hi>why did you not accuſe the Fathers and Councils!</hi> for the Maſter took moſt of what he has out of them.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe that I had ſo much Reverence for the Fathers and Councils, as to be willing their Names ſhould not be blemiſh'd, am I to be chaſtiſed for that? He and all the World know, I could not read the Maſter's Book, but I muſt read therein the Names, and oftentimes the Places of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whence he took moſt of what he ſays: I could not therefore be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant that many of theſe things are to be found in the Fathers: But I was deſirous, I ſay, that their venerable Names ſhould ſhine as bright as may be; and that the rather, for that this Rummager has after a ſort weed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Writings, and very often taken only the worſt things out of them. The Father, out of whom he has injudiciouſly amaſs'd together the moſt he has of the Trinity, complains, thoſe his Books of the Trinity
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51847:11"/> were almoſt raviſh'd out of his Hands, before he could amend or finiſh<note place="margin">Aug. Retract. lib. 2. cap. 15.</note> them as he would have done; and that he intended not to have publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, but to have ſpoken what he thought of this Argument in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Work. When therefore I find St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> produced, proving the Son <hi>the Beginning,</hi> a Principle, or Original, (<hi>Principium</hi> the Word is) <hi>and that not only in reſpect of the Creatures, but even of the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> from ſuch a Teſtimony of Scripture as this is, <hi>They ſaid unto him, Who art thou? and he anſwered, Even the ſame that I ſaid unto you from the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> which the vulgar Latin, and St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> as well as ſome other Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, corruptly read, <hi>The Beginning, who alſo ſpeak to you:</hi> I let St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> paſs, who in effect did as good as ask Pardon for his Miſtake, or miſapplying this Text; and I tax him, who taking no Notice of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's excuſing his imperfect Work, alledgeth even the moſt culpable Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages in it for legitimate Proofs.</p>
            <q>—<hi>Libellus, Male cum recitas, incipit eſſe tuus.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>He by this Means makes the Fathers Over-ſights his, and is juſtly to be blamed for them. But as to his Faithfulneſs in dealing with the Fathers, hear what a great Man ſays; <q>His Books of the Sentences, ſays <hi>Mornaeus,</hi> he has made up out of Pieces of the Fathers, here and there culled out and put together in a certain Order; which Fathers he, by <hi>changing, omitting, adding</hi> Words at pleaſure, has forced to ſerve his Plot, and bowed to the corrupt Divinity of his Age.</q> And however Orthodox any, who affect Diſpute and endleſs Speculation, may judg him in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the <hi>Trinity</hi> and <hi>Incarnation, Bellarmine</hi> himſelf, after Recital of his Works, adds this Account on him out of <hi>Matthew Paris,</hi> 
               <q>That he was accuſed of Hereſy in the Matter of the <hi>Incarnation,</hi> and condemn'd at <hi>Paris</hi> nineteen Years after his Death.</q> Then as to the Point of the Trinity, the Caſe wherein I taxed him, <hi>L. Danaeus</hi> (a <hi>Geneva</hi> Divine, and no Socinian) avows and proves, that <hi>in every Part of his Diſputation</hi>
               <note place="margin">In quâlibet hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus Diſputatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis parte, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligentia dolo malo aequipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur. <hi>Cenſura ad Diſt. 35. lib. 1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>hereon, his Fraud and Negligence are equal.</hi> And whoſoever will ſpend a few Hours in peruſing the ſaid <hi>Danaeus</hi>'s <hi>Prolegomena</hi> to his Commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on the firſt Book of the <hi>Sentences,</hi> (the <hi>Maſter's</hi> Piece by me chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged) and eſpecially <hi>Prolegom.</hi> V. will find, both there, and more fully in the Book, the Maſter diſtinctly convicted to be, (1) <hi>A falſe Witneſs; (2) A pernicious Writer;</hi> And, (3) <hi>A ridiculous one.</hi> He will find alſo an explicit <hi>Collection</hi> of his Frauds and Falſifications; to which the Author ſubjoins, he <hi>has not pick'd out Paſſages to cavil at, but rather challenges any to produce what is faultleſs.</hi> I might ſay much more, but let this ſuffice as to my Defence in whatſoever Reflections I made on the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51847:12"/> Maſter of the Sentences in this Point. I hope it appears I gave not that Touch upon him, which I did without Reaſon and knowledg of his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhments.</p>
            <p>But for all this, <hi>the more general Cauſe of my being ſo angry with the</hi>
               <note place="margin">§. 7. <hi>Pag. 5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>School-Doctors, is, becauſe I have not Induſtry enough to read or underſtand them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I thank Mr. Dean for this Ornament, and will take hence only an Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of a little publick Penance before God and the World, confeſſing with hearty Sorrow and Shame, that I have not been ſo induſtrious as I ought to have been: I cannot before an all-ſeeing Eye acquit my ſelf of ſome kind of Idleneſs, but beſeech my good God to pardon what cannot be recalled, and to quicken me for the future to double Diligence. Yet I may adventure to plead, that amongſt them who have known the Varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of my Labours ſince I came out into the World, and I believe alſo amongſt all thoſe now alive, who either had the Tuition of me, or were Aſſociates of my Studies in my Education, there is none will ſay I was in any meaſure ever noted (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) for a ſcandalous Ideler. Then as to my reading and underſtanding the School-men in particular, I will only add, that many Years ago, as ſoon as Maſter of Arts, I ſet my ſelf to read and ſtudy thoſe of beſt Note amongſt them, and ſpent no inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Time and Pains therein, as much at leaſt as a Life otherwiſe labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious would permit; that about ten or eleven Years ago, having ſome Leiſure and Opportunity, I reſumed thoſe Studies with particular Purpoſe to refreſh my Memory, and rectify (if I could) my Judgment, both in and by them; that I think, when I read them, I generally do under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them, (I ſaid generally, for I am of Opinion, that ſometimes they underſtood not themſelves, that is, they diſputed themſelves into uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, obſcure and confuſed Notions) but I confeſs <hi>I never read theſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors with ſuch Reliſh,</hi> Savour and Delight, with ſuch Warmth, good Affection and Holy Advantage, as I did and daily do read the ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. O the infinite Diſproportion of them! Even in moral Notions, in which notwithſtanding divers of the School-Doctors excel themſelves, comparatively to their other Writings. How much more Force is there ſometimes in one Word or Glance of the Holy Ghoſt, than in the acuteſt Definitions of the Doctors? How far ſharper and more piercing are the Divine Oracles, even <hi>dividing aſunder the Soul and Spirit, and diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Thoughts and Intents of the Heart?</hi> Further, I acknowledg <hi>my Memory has not ſuch a retentive Faculty of the nice Diſtinctions and Diviſions which theſe Wits run;</hi> nor, after all, do I ſee the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of them</hi> as to promoting <hi>Peace, Holineſs,</hi> or in divers Caſes <hi>ſound Judgment</hi> in the Church of God. How many School-Notions were (not yet two Ages
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51847:12"/> ago) made Points of Faith, as far as the uſurping Power of what ſtiled it ſelf an Oecumenical Council could make them? And has Chriſtianity received ſo much Improvement by thoſe Sanctions, as that we ſhould be fond of the Fountains whence they derived thoſe <hi>Waters of</hi> Meribah, or at this Day pretend that theſe ſpinoſe and crabbed Doctors have <hi>only guard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Chriſtianity with a Hedg of Thorns?</hi> &amp;c. I pity thoſe who for a ſhiſt betake themſelves to ſuch Aſſertions, and I liſt not to purſue this thence: only for a final Trial of my Inſight into thoſe Authors, I appeal to every judicious Reader, whether I did not deliver in my Paper, <hi>p.</hi> 13. the Doctrine of the Trinity and Unity more conformably to the Doctrine of the Schools, than Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> did in his <hi>Vindication,</hi> notwithſtanding his pretended greater Converſation in them. I tranſcribed it not indeed either out of the School-men or Canoniſts, <hi>de ſummâ Trinit.</hi> (from whom Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> ſeems to have almoſt tranſlated in this Point) nor yet from St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> from whom they all have taken it; though I was ignorant of none of thoſe: but from a Maſter of the Temple, becauſe I took that [to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Temple] to be more an Argument <hi>ad Hominem.</hi> Now if I faithfully reported the Doctrine of the Schools, 'tis very probable I was not ſo unacquainted with them, as Mr. Dean's Candour would repreſent me.</p>
            <p>My next Accuſation is, that I have ſaid, <hi>The firſt Reformers complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi>
               <note place="margin">§. 8. <hi>Pag. 5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>of this,</hi> [namely, the corrupt Divinity of the Schools] <hi>and deſired a purer and more ſcriptural</hi> (he inſtead thereof puts <hi>ſpiritual) ſort of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity.</hi> I did indeed ſay this, but not without due Authority. My Words were very nearly (as nearly as I could remember) the Engliſh of a Paſſage of the great <hi>Melancthon,</hi> which, having not then my Note-books at hand, I could not perfectly<note place="margin">Tantum Labyrinthorum &amp; falſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum opinionum eſt in Thomâ, Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to &amp; ſimilibus, qui dediti Ariſtote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis Doctrinae, transformare Eccleſiae Doctrinam in Philoſophiam coepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, ut ſemper ſaniores Theologi deſideraverint aliud genus Doctrinae plenius &amp; purius. <hi>And a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore;</hi> Haec aetas non tantum coenum, ſed &amp; inſuper venena, id eſt opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones probantes manifeſta idola in fontes evangelicos invexit. <hi>Philip. Melancthon. in Praefat. ad Luther. Tom. 2.</hi>
               </note> report, but will now in the Margin tranſcribe the Text, by which it may appear, I was favourable in my Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and ſpoke not the full of what my Author would have warranted. And if this which is ſaid in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin ſatisfy not, that the <hi>Doctrine of the School-men is full of Labyrinths and Falſities, of Dirt and Poiſon, ſo as to have infected the very Fountains of the Goſpel-Doctrine,</hi> which yet is more than I ſaid, let Perſons of Leiſure and Advantages conſult the ſecond Tome of <hi>Melancthon</hi>'s own Works, where they may find ſome little Tracts deſigned to make good this Charge; particularly, <hi>Oratio Thomae Didymi</hi> (a perſonated Name no doubt) <hi>pro M. Luther:</hi> And <hi>Philippi Melancthonis pro Luth. Apologia, adverſus furioſorum Pariſienſium Decretum,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I could have ſaid much to the ſame Effect out of <hi>Luther</hi> himſelf in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51847:13"/> Places, but I feared it might have been ſaid, he was too fiery. Nor are like Paſſages at all infrequent in <hi>Calvin:</hi> but perhaps by ſome Men as much might have been ſaid of him as of me, that he had not read or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood whom he cenſured: <hi>Melancthon</hi>'s Authority I thought I might more ſafely ſpeak upon, he being a Perſon whoſe Learning and Moderation might recommend his Judgment as more ſincere and competent. Now theſe three of the firſt Reformers I ſhall abide by at preſent, as having cenſured the Divinity of the Schools much more ſeverely, than I did after them.</p>
            <p>But theſe were <hi>not our Engliſh Reformers;</hi> and <hi>I cenſured even them for retaining Scholaſtick Cramping Terms in their publick Prayers.</hi> By Mr. Dean's Favour I cenſured them not, only I modeſtly <hi>wiſhed they had uſed the ſame Temper as did the foreign Reformers,</hi> in baniſhing hard or Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtick Terms out of our Prayers.</p>
            <p>By <hi>theſe Terms</hi> he ſays <hi>I mean the Beginning of the Litany.</hi> And how came he to know my Thoughts? I will aſſure him <hi>I meant not that alone.</hi> I will not touch upon divers Collects: But what does he think of that <hi>Preface</hi> in the Communion Service, ordered to be uſed before the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, on Trinity Sunday? Has not that School-Divinity enough in it, all addreſs'd to God by way of direct Adoration? However, becauſe he has pitch'd upon the other, I am content to ſtick by it, and ſhall only give him, touching it, the Senſe of two of the firſt Reformers; I confeſs not ours in <hi>England,</hi> (for I expreſs my Sorrow that they obſerved not ſuch Caution) but two the moſt eminent who led the way to them. <hi>Luther</hi> leſt that Petition, <hi>O Holy, Bleſſed and Glorious Trinity,</hi> &amp;c. out of the Liturgy; as not only his Enemies, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and others, accuſe him to have done, but the <hi>German</hi> Office to this Day evidenceth: And <hi>Gerard, Brochmand,</hi> and other learned Lutherans, not only confeſs, but defend him for it, ſaying, the German Word which they uſe for the Trinity, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies Triplicity rather than Trinity. But if that had been all, why could not Trinity have been adopted into High Dutch as well as into Engliſh? There was another Reaſon for it, which I am loth to ſpeak. <hi>Calvin</hi> not only omits it, but thus cenſures it: <hi>It is good,</hi> ſays he, <hi>to forbear ſuch Forms of ſpeaking which are either too rough or remote from the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the Holy Scripture. The Prayer ſo</hi>
               <note place="margin">Utile eſt ſuperſedere à formulis loquendi nimiùm aſperis vel à Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae uſu remotis. Precatio vulgo trita, ſancta Trinitas unus Deus miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere noſtri, mihi non placet, ac om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nino Barbariem ſapit. Epiſt. quâ fidem admonitionis confirmat ad Polonos; Tom. ult. p. 687.</note> 
               <hi>common with the People, O Holy Trinity, one God, have Mercy upon us, does not pleaſe me, and altogether ſavours of Barbarity.</hi> Had the Socinians been the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Perſons who except againſt it, more might be ſaid for the retaining it: But as to its Original, it was cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly never in the publick Prayers till <hi>introduced by
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51847:13"/> Pope</hi> Gregory <hi>the Great,</hi> the Compiler of the Litany for the main part, or the Body of it, though not perfectly in the Form it now ſtands in; and<note place="margin">Ethnici in ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mâ rerum ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantiâ quem potiſſimum De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ûm aut Dearu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> orarent, neſcie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant omnes i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitur precaban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp;c. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaub.</note> what other Innovations came in with it, is ſufficiently known. No leſs a Man than <hi>Caſaubon</hi> will tell us, whom the Church imitated, or what Precedents ſhe had in ſuch accumulate repeated Invocations; <hi>Exercitat. p. 327. Edit. Londin. A. D.</hi> 1614. Or, <hi>Ad An. D.</hi> XXXII. <hi>N.</hi> 14. And not only in a manner all our <hi>Nonconformiſt Countrymen,</hi> elder or la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but Foreigners of great Learning, have ſtrong Exceptions againſt this Part of the Litany. If any will anſwer thoſe which amongſt others the learned <hi>Johannes Forbeſius,</hi> in his <hi>Inſtructiones Hiſtorico-Theologicae (Part. 1. Qu. 31. a.</hi> 1.) brings, I will acknowledg to owe great Satisfaction to ſuch a Perſon. For how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever<note place="margin">Hâc formulâ periculosè diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guntur cogitationes, &amp; conceptio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes precantis veluti ad diverſa ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecta, quas recolligere conatur col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectione objectorum in unum. Nullo nititur praecepto, vel exemplo ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crae Scripturae vel catholicae anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitatis: imo ab eiſdem &amp; à do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinâ ſaniorum Scholaſticorum, &amp; ab ipsâ ratione Theologicâ Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pat. &amp;c. Forbeſ.</note> I acknowledg ſome Men may uſe the preſcribed Form without Sin, yet I cannot but judg it much ſafer not to go ſo near dividing the Deity, and ſo far to diſtract Devotion. Much more than this could I ſay, which I cannot anſwer ſo well as I would, on this Subject: but this may ſuffice to ſhew, the Glance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I gave was not without Cauſe. And the reducing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of our Prayers to more Scriptural Forms, would much recommend our Reformation to foreign Divines, as well as to thoſe of our own Country, whom we ought, if poſſible, to bring in and unite to us.</p>
            <p>But this is only a <hi>plauſible Project much talked of of late, and ſuch,</hi>
               <note place="margin">§. 9. <hi>Pag. 6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>which Hereticks in former Days were the firſt Propoſers of. The Arians objected this againſt the Homoouſions, that it was an unſcriptural Word:</hi> By Mr. Dean's Favour he herein contradicts St. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> himſelf, who accuſes the Arians, that they <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>firſt began to fight againſt God from unwritten Terms,</hi> or Arguments; and particularly objects againſt them uſing the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>begotten,</hi> pleading that it was an <hi>unſcriptural Word,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. Athanaſ. in Epiſt. de Synod. Nic. contra Haereſin. Arian. decretis. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> lb. p. 282.</note> 
               <hi>and therefore ſuſpitious, having alſo various Significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; but that the ſimple, written and trueſt Terms, which had but one Signification, were thoſe in Scripture, the Father and the Son; that</hi> unbegotten <hi>was uſed by the Heathens, who knew not the Father, nor the Son; but that of the Father was known to be from our Lord's own Mouth.</hi> And doth he not at the ſame time apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logize from the Neceſſity that lay upon the Council, for the Uſe of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, though not in Scripture, and toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confeſs, that <hi>the moſt accurate Expreſſions or Notions of the Truth are
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51847:14"/> rather to be taken from the Scriptures than other Books?</hi> It were to be wiſhed this Father had been more conſtant to this his ingenuous Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment. Again, did not St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> alſo in the like Caſe, diſputing againſt the Arians, ſay as much of <hi>Ingenitus</hi> in Latin, that it was no Scripture-term, and therefore refuſe it? I am under great Infelicity that I am without ſo many of my Books, and ſo being oftentimes to truſt Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory or old Notes, cannot make my Anſwers ſo cloſe and pertinent as otherwiſe I might: But I am ſure St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> (and I think in his Book of our Lord's Incarnation) anſwering the Arians Argument for proving the Father and the Son not to be of the ſame Nature and Subſtance, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that one was <hi>ingenitus,</hi> unbegotten, the other <hi>genitus,</hi> begotten, (now, ſaid they, the ſame Nature and Subſtance cannot be begotten and unbegotten) returns roundly, <hi>In ſanctâ Scripturâ nuſquam invenio, non legi;</hi> or to that purpoſe; Unbegotten is no where in Scripture. I am not, I am ſure, far from his very Words. Now was this a good Anſwer in the Fathers; and ſhall the ſame be ill, meerly becauſe at another time, in another Caſe, it came from an Heretick? The Hereticks propoſing it, you ſay, renders it ſuſpect: St. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> and St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> uſing it, ſay I, and relying upon it too, gives it Authority. The Hereticks uſed it not firſt, but only retorted it on the Fathers: Wherefore at leaſt admit the Authority of the one to take off the Diſadvantage it may ſuſtain from the other; and let <hi>the Project,</hi> as you call it, ſtand or fall according to its own naked Merit: Only by the way give me leave to add, that if what is juſt and reaſonable muſt be rejected becauſe it has been ſometimes uſed by Hereticks, we muſt oftentimes give over pleading from Scripture, and quit a World of Texts therein.</p>
            <p>I muſt acknowledg I am not able to ſee why Men ſhould be ſo averſe from the Language of the Holy Ghoſt, either in their Prayers or Creeds. The Sum of the Reaſon alledged is, that it is the <hi>Senſe of Scripture which</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 7.</note> 
               <hi>is the true Faith, and not merely the Words:</hi> And <hi>muſt we,</hi> ſaith Mr. Dean very admirably, <hi>believe the Words or Senſe of the Scripture?</hi> I may deſire him, if he can, to believe this or that Senſe, as revealed by God, (for he cannot know this or that Senſe or Propoſition as revealed by God) without the Words in which it was revealed. I demand, Do thoſe Words expreſs, contain and convey to us this Senſe of ſuch or ſuch Point of Faith, or do they not? If they do not, then the Senſe inſiſted on is not the Senſe of the Scripture, and conſequently not Faith. If they do, why ſhould we not keep thoſe Words by which God hath thought fit to expreſs this Senſe? Why ſhould we ſeparate what he has joined? Are we wiſer than he? or can we expreſs the Mind of God better than himſelf?</p>
            <p>But <hi>when Hereticks have uſed their utmoſt Art to make the Words of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51847:14"/> Scripture ſignify what they pleaſe, is it not neceſſary to fix their true Senſe, and to expreſs that in ſuch other Words as Hereticks cannot pervert?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yes, in the Name of God, let us uſe our <hi>utmoſt Art to vindicate</hi> (if poſſible) all and every <hi>Scripture from Heretical Gloſſes</hi> or Diſtortions, and with all the Light and Evidence we can, diſcover and aſſert its genuine Senſe. The natural Explication of Scripture is our immediate Scope in moſt, or in all the Arts and Sciences, which as Divines we take in. But what do all our Explications effect, ſave a Proof or Diſcovery that this or that is the Senſe contained under ſuch Words of Scripture?</p>
            <p>When therefore we have plainly proved that theſe Words of Scripture contain this Senſe, why ſhould we change the Words? If they were not plain, the Explication, ſuppoſing it to have done any thing to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, has made them plain: When they are plain, then why may they not be kept?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>They may be undetermined,</hi> ſaid Mr. Dean, and <hi>'tis neceſſary to fix their</hi>
               <note place="margin">§. 10.</note> 
               <hi>true Senſe.</hi> But this is the Difficulty: They may rationally, at leaſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably, admit more Senſes than one; and when you ſay you have fixed your own true Senſe, another ſhall deny the Senſe you have fixed to be the true Senſe; at leaſt aſſign another equally probable Senſe: And a third Perſon, it may be a third. For Inſtance, the Apoſtle tells us, 1 <hi>Cor. 2. 10, 12. God hath revealed</hi> [the Joys and Glories <hi>which he has prepared for thoſe that love him] unto us by his Spirit; for the Spirit ſearcheth all things, yea the deep things of God: For what Man knoweth the things of Man ſave the Spirit of Man which is in him? even ſo the things of God knoweth no Man but the Spirit of God. Now we have received not the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the World, but the Spirit which is of God; that we might know the things which are freely given us of God.</hi> This Text the learned Dr. <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock,</hi> as well as others, (even <hi>Athanaſius</hi> himſelf) interpret not without Probability of the eſſential Spirit of God; and the Doctor, both in his <hi>Vindication</hi> and <hi>Apology,</hi> endeavours thence to prove the Perſonality of the Holy Ghoſt, and his mutual Conſciouſneſs with the Father and the Son. Now I ſacredly proteſt I remember not my ſelf ever to have read any Socinian Author on this Text: But I find ſome others, by the word <hi>Spirit,</hi> here underſtand the ſpiritual Illumination and inward Perſwaſion of Mind wrought in the Apoſtles and other faithful People: And this we ſeem enforced from <hi>ver.</hi> 12. to admit; where we read the Apoſtles to have received the Spirit, which cannot be well underſtood of the Perſon, but of the Gifts of the Holy Ghoſt. This agrees too with the Cloſe of <hi>ver. 10. The Spirit ſearcheth all things,</hi> that is [<hi>ſcrutari nos facit</hi>]. This Illumination in their Search, leads all ſuch who are endowed therewith, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the knowledg and belief of all things neceſſary to their Salvation, even the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51847:15"/> deepeſt Myſteries of the Kingdom of Heaven. Further, this ſpiritual Gift may be ſaid <hi>to know,</hi> i. e. we by this Illumination know and reliſh the things of God, as feelingly as <hi>the Spirit of Man knows the things of a Man;</hi> becauſe this Gift is ſo true a Communication from God, and as it were ſomewhat of the <hi>Divine Nature (2 Pet.</hi> 1. 4.) imparted to us. But that the Spirit of God here ſpoken of as knowing the things of God, ſhould be a Perſon diſtinct from God, any more than the Spirit of a Man, knowing the things of a Man, is a Perſon diſtinct from the Man, ſeems unreaſonable. And it is conſiderable, that amongſt others, even <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Beza</hi> allow, by the Spirit here may be underſtood ſuch Gift of Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination as ſpoken of. But <hi>Grotius</hi> referring us to what he had ſaid on <hi>Mark</hi> 2. 8, &amp;c. with great Learning and Probability interprets the Spirit here, of the <hi>Divine Nature of Chriſt;</hi> and tells us it was by Chriſt, as coming from the Boſom of his Father, and knowing all his Secrets, that theſe things were revealed to the Apoſtles; and that the Senſe here is the ſame as in <hi>John</hi> 1. 18. and <hi>ch.</hi> 6. 46, &amp;c. and he produces many Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, both from Scripture and Fathers, touching the Divine Nature of our Lord being ſtiled the Spirit. Now who ſhall determine which is the true and genuine Senſe? and if any of the two latter ſhould be genuine, then has not the Dean evinced hence what he conceived, and particularly not the mutual Conſciouſneſs of the Holy Ghoſt with the Father and the Son, for that the Perſon of the Holy Ghoſt is not here ſpoken of? It were eaſy, but that it would be tedious, to give like Inſtances in many other Texts of Holy Scripture. What ſhall we do then? It were an admirable Expedient indeed, could we determine infallibly this or that to be the true Senſe of each controverted Text, and then expreſs that Senſe in ſuch Words as Hereticks cannot pervert. But where ſhall we find that Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, or thoſe Words? Some have maintained (whatever their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is now I know not, nor muſt concern my ſelf, if they uſe to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict themſelves: Some I ſay have maintained) that there is no infallible Judg on Earth, nor any need of one, being we have, as far as is neceſſary to Salvation, an infallible Rule, the Scriptures of Truth: Suppoſe then, as to the forementioned Place, we ſhould take ſome ſuch ample, wide or large Senſe as this; <q>The Joys and Glories of Heaven, the good things which God has prepared for them that love him, we could never have known without Divine Revelation, nor ſhould ever have had a Senſe, Reliſh and Perſwaſion of, without a Work of Illumination and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction upon our Minds, or more generally without other Aids and Aſſiſtances of Grace.</q> This well enough ſutes with the Text, and thus much is ſufficient to conclude hence for Salvation, or to any Intent of holy Life: and this all Proteſtants will acquieſce in, at leaſt none will contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51847:15"/> Why may not we ſtop then here in this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral<note place="margin">This reſtraining of the Word of God from that LATIT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DE and <hi>Generali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings of Men from that Liberty wherein Chriſt and the Apoſtles left them, is and has been the only Foundation of all the Schiſms in the Church, and that which makes them im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal. Mr. <hi>Chilling worth,</hi> Ch. <hi>IV.</hi> n. 16.</note> Senſe, without affixing any of thoſe particular Senſes to the Text? that is, Is it not beſt to <hi>leave it in its full Latitude,</hi> without reſtraining the word <hi>Spirit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Further, I would be clearly for expreſſing ſome fixed true Senſe of all controverted Texts in ſuch Words as Hereticks cannot pervert, but for two or three Reaſons, one already mentioned, namely, that I cannot always be ſure which Senſe is moſt truly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fix'd: and being I am not or cannot be ſo, a ſecond Reaſon will be, that by expreſſing ſuch Senſe in ſuch Words, and fixing it to Scripture, ſo that now ſuch Senſe ſhould become the Senſe of Scripture, (<hi>it being,</hi> as we know, <hi>the Senſe of Scripture which is the true Faith, not meerly the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Words</hi>) I ſhould fear by this means, Mens changing Faith, or which is much the ſame, changing Scripture. And a third Reaſon, which is as urgent as all the reſt, is, I do not know, nor does it appear, that any Man knows, no nor that any Church or Council ever have known, where to find ſuch Words which Hereticks cannot pervert.</p>
            <p>I could aſſign many Words from time to time pitch'd upon, to <hi>prick the Fingers of Hereticks, and guard the Faith:</hi> but I will content my ſelf<note place="margin">Pag. 5.</note> with two, neither of which Mr. Dean can pretend to be unacquainted with; they are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <hi>Perſonae:</hi> Theſe we know have been long thought fit Terms to fix the Senſe of Scriptures: But are they Words which Hereticks cannot pervert? or, are they not more equivocal, and ſo more pervertable, than moſt of the uſual Terms in Scripture? The firſt indeed is ſeveral times uſed ſingularly in the Greek of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, and rendred conſtantly by the old Interpreter <hi>Subſtantia;</hi> but by many Moderns, and particularly by our Tranſlators, two or three ways: Three times that now occur to me, by <hi>Confidence; 2 Cor.</hi> 9. 4. and <hi>ch. 11. 17. Heb.</hi> 3. 14. (yet in the firſt of theſe Places <hi>Beza</hi> tells us, it might have been rendred, <hi>in hoc fundamento gloriationis,</hi> which is near the firſt and natural Import of the Word: And <hi>Caſtellio</hi> renders it, <hi>in hâc materiâ:</hi> Eraſmus, <hi>in hoc argumento;</hi> which we may fitly engliſh, in this Subject of Boaſting:) Once (<hi>viz. Heb.</hi> 11. 1.) by <hi>Subſtance,</hi> which is its Philoſophical Acceptation: And once by <hi>Perſon,</hi> which I may call the Eccleſiaſtical or Scholaſtical Acceptation of the Word, affixed to this Place by <hi>Theophilact,</hi> as it is ſaid by Authority of <hi>Gregory Niſſen;</hi> but I have neither by me to conſult. After all, notwithſtanding, we no where read <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in Scripture, though frequently in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Suppoſe then we take this Term, <hi>Three Hypoſtaſes,</hi> to fix the Senſe of that Text, <hi>There are three that bear Witneſs in Heaven,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51847:16"/> Are there now no more Homonymies of it that yet we have ſeen? Yes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith <hi>Budaeus,</hi> is almoſt the ſame as Exiſtence; and Evil has <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: for both which he gives good Authority. Again, <hi>Nicephorus Calliſtus</hi> tells us, <hi>The Word is ſcarce in uſe amongſt the</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Hiſt. lib. 10. cap. 15. in Sentent. lib. 1. Diſt. 23.</note> 
               <hi>Antients in any certain Signification, but the Moderns have frequently uſed it for</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: nay <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>per totam ſecularium ſcholam,</hi> are the ſame, ſays <hi>Eſtius.</hi> Now all the World knows that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, although uſed ordinarily by <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> for his Predicament of Subſtance, yet more properly ſignifies Eſſence or Nature. Three Hypoſtaſes then may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted three Eſſences, or Natures; and under this Term may <hi>Tritheiſm</hi> it ſelf, in its worſe Senſe, lurk. Nor are there wanting thoſe who tell us, this very Term led <hi>Philoponus</hi> into his Hereſy. Further, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> will have it, that <hi>Hypoſtaſis</hi> properly ſignifies <hi>Subſtantiam primam,</hi> which<note place="margin">In Controv. de Chriſto.</note> is not neceſſarily <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or a Perſon, but may be any meaner Animate, or even an Inanimate, individual. I could add yet two or three<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Niceph. ubi ſupr.</note> more Significations of this Word out of the above-mentioned <hi>Nicephorus Calliſtus,</hi> who vouches good Authority for the meaneſt of them; which I will not here ſet down, leſt the Dean ſhould ſay, <hi>I teach People to ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cule the Trinity in their Prayers,</hi> when I only report the Words of appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Authors, to caution others againſt unadviſed and obnoxious Terms. But it is plain, from what I have ſaid, this Term is further from fixing the Senſe of Scripture, than the Terms of Scripture.</p>
            <p>Next as to the word <hi>Perſona,</hi> though that Word be now (upon the Authority above-mentioned) by <hi>Beza</hi> brought in, and juſtly too, into our modern Tranſlations; yet it was true in <hi>Aquinas</hi>'s time, and ſince that too, that it was neither <hi>in Old nor New Teſtament uſed touching God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Nomen perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na in Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris veteris vel novi Teſtamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti non inveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur dictum de Deo. 1. <hi>q. 29. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 3.</hi>
               </note> And when uſed plurally, (as the former) it muſt be acknowledged an Eccleſiaſtical or Scholaſtical Word, ſound out, as the other, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ixing (if poſſible) the Senſe of Scripture, to uſe the Dean's Phraſe; and does it do it? The Dean no doubt knows what <hi>Laurentius Valla,</hi> a Critick, but no Socinian, ſays of its Congruity in this Point. And it is too trite a Subject to reckon up all its Homonymies. I will only remind, that it is taken in one Senſe <hi>in humanis,</hi> for a ſingle Subſtance, ſeparate and by it ſelf; in another <hi>in divinis,</hi> for ſuch a Subſtance diſtinct, but not ſeparate.</p>
            <p>Now upon the whole, have either of theſe Words fix'd the Senſe of the Scripture, ſo that Hereticks cannot pervert it, and have a private Senſe of their own touching it? May not a Man, (1) Own three Hypoſtaſes, or three Perſons, that is, profeſs Faith in or under the two moſt Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Terms that have been found out, and none but God and himſelf know what he means? Nay, may he not hold to the Words, and yet hold Hereſy, yea Blaſphemy, and that in divers particular Senſes which I
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51847:16"/> have named, and which I have declined to name, for that the Subject is ſo tender? Again, (2) May not a Man uſe the Words quite contrary to the Forms, in which the Fathers generally uſe them, and yet ſpeak Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Truth? Did not, if <hi>Theodoret</hi> ſay Truth, the Council of <hi>Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Theodor. Hiſt. lib. 2. cap. 8.</note> ſay, <hi>This Catholick Tradition and Confeſſion have we received and taught; this do we hold, that there is but one Hypoſtaſis,</hi> meaning there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by one Subſtance of the Deity? Nay, laſtly, muſt it not be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, that at leaſt one of theſe Words, (<hi>viz. Hypoſtaſis</hi>) has given occaſion to the Tritheites Hereſy; as any Man may ſee who pleaſes to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult what <hi>Photius,</hi> what <hi>Leontius</hi> the <hi>Byzantine Advocate,</hi> and what <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cephorus Calliſtus</hi> report of <hi>Thiloponus,</hi> too long here to be inſerted?</p>
            <p>Were it not better then to keep to Scripture-Words, in which all agree, than to take up new ones of humane Invention, and contend and damn one another about them; when yet it is apparent we may uſe theſe, (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever artificial refined Terms) and be as far from agreeing in Senſe as ever we were, nay much further than if we had kept to Scripture-Language? <hi>Hereticks may here conceal themſelves under a</hi> larger <hi>Latitude of Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 8.</note> 
               <hi>and ſpread their Hereſies with a traditionary Senſe and Comment of their own,</hi> more exactly and poiſonouſly than the Purity and Simplicity of the Holy Text would have permitted. But if any be ſtill fond of the Litigious, Eccleſiaſtical, or Scholaſtical Terms in their Confeſſions and Articles, let them ſtand for me. In the Orthodox Senſe, and for Peace ſake, they may be ſubſcribed to: only in our Prayers at leaſt, wherein a moſt intire Aſſent and Conſent, <hi>without doubting</hi> or doubling, is to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> let us have Scripture, and ſpeak to God as he has revealed himſelf to us.</p>
            <p>What then? muſt we reform the Doctrine of the Trinity out of our Prayers, as, in his good-natured Fit, Mr. Dean expreſſes it? No; but put it in there only as God has put it in our Bibles: And my Hopes and Deſires of ſeeing this done, I take to be no <hi>foul Imputation,</hi> nor at all<note place="margin">Pag. 5.</note> likely to caſt an ill Reflection <hi>on any Deſign of excellent Perſons</hi> whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
            <p>But I muſt return with my Apologiſt to the Latitude of Faith, which<note place="margin">§. 11.</note> he again (to uſe his own Term) <hi>tragically complains</hi> of me for pleading for, and demands <hi>whether there be any more than one true Chriſtian Faith?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 8.</note> 
               <hi>and whether Chriſt and his Apoſtles intended to teach any more? Or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they did not intend that all Chriſtians ſhould be obliged to believe this one Faith?</hi> Here are Queſtions enow, and Fallacy enough in them. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer briefly and plainly; <hi>Faith,</hi> as <hi>Truth,</hi> can be but <hi>one.</hi> And every Truth which Chriſt and his Apoſtles taught, ought, if it can be without Scruple underſtood, without Scruple to be believed. All Chriſtians are
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:51847:17"/> obliged to believe to the utmoſt of their Underſtandings each Truth by Chriſt and his Apoſtles taught. But whether a determinate, explicite Belief of all the Truths which Chriſt and his Apoſtles taught, be abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary to the Salvation of every private Chriſtian, or even of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Chriſtian Doctor, I take to be a Queſtion worthy of the Dean's Conſideration. For mine own part I dare not affirm it, but judg a <hi>Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude muſt be allowed;</hi> and in ſuch Determinations as exceed moſt Mens Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, ſome ſuch Temper as my Notion of a <hi>Negative Belief</hi> muſt be admitted. Which Term, by his good Favour, has no more Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety or Contradiction in it, than that more uſual one amongſt Divines of a <hi>Negative Righteouſneſs,</hi> whence I tranſ-ſumed it; thinking it for a Reaſon, which he may gueſs at, more palatable to ſome People than an <hi>implicite Faith:</hi> and I having ſo fully and perſpicuouſly defin'd it, it was poor and pedantic in him to carp at the Term. In a word, we are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject nothing as falſe, nor eſteem any thing as mean, ſuperfluous or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable, which our Lord, or his Apoſtles have taught. We are to give Diligence to underſtand, and as we can underſtand, explicitely to believe all: but there are many Points in Divinity, (that is, in the whole Body of what our Lord and his Apoſtles have taught) whereof perhaps we may not have ſo clear and determinate a Senſe, as that we can ſay, this or that is it, which our Lord and his Apoſtles intended to oblige us to believe. And here we muſt either totally ſuſpend our Faith, till we can better ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy our ſelves, (in the mean while not contradicting) or elſe we muſt believe, though not without ſome Tenderneſs, what to us appears the more probable of the ſeveral Points in Scruple. Now the Belief of the more probable Side cannot be ſtiled Faith, but in a certain <hi>Latitude</hi> of the Name. 'Tis ſure our Lord and his Apoſtles full well knew they both ſpoke and writ to People of very different Capacities and Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, and no doubt accordingly accommodated their Doctrine. What was neceſſary to the Salvation of all, is by them delivered very plain; and I will add, 'tis ſhort. <hi>Certa ſemper ſunt in paucis,</hi> ſays <hi>Tertullian:</hi> And all learned Proteſtant Divines have been ever very tender in defining the Number of Fundamentals, or what things are neceſſary by all to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved to their Salvation. Here the <hi>Minumum quod ſic,</hi> as we commonly ſpeak, is a difficult Point to determine; and Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> in his Book of Fundamentals, has amply ſhewn there muſt be, as to the Number of them, a Latitude allowed, according to different States or Circumſtances of Men. But his Authority is infinitely greater, who ſaid, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever much is given, of him ſhall be much required:</hi> Conſequently of him who knew not, or (giving honeſt Diligence to know) underſtood not what is revealed, a leſs meaſure of Faith ſhall be expected. So that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51847:17"/> even here, I ſtand to it, is a Latitude. Suppoſe a Man to have been bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, to underſtand competently the Apoſtles Creed, and the common Rules of Chriſtian Duty, to profeſs the Belief hereof, to ſhew his Love to God and Chriſt by good Works, and a Life ſavouring of Heaven, to live in the Communion of ſuch a Church or Society of Chriſtians as will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſuch a Perſon for a Member of Chriſt, though perhaps he may not be admittted (for want of great Knowledg and a Faith of deeper My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries) into the Communion of the regular eſtabliſh'd Church (which yet he is far from contemning or cenſuring:) Suppoſe, I ſay, a Perſon to be of ſuch Character and Circumſtances, ſhall we dare to ſay this Man's Faith is not ſufficient to his Salvation, becauſe we our ſelves perhaps have more Faith, and are juſtly perſwaded more is neceſſary to our own Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? In all Likelihood he endangers himſelf to be excluded from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, who takes upon him to exclude ſuch.</p>
            <p>I am far from denying that Men ought to grow up to Perfection <hi>in all Faith and Knowledg;</hi> that is, to endeavour to comprehend and believe, as near as they are able, all the Myſteries of the Kingdom of Heaven<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed Truths built upon that <hi>one Foundation,</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, and him crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But we know how vaſtly the <hi>Superſtructure</hi> is increaſed: the Compaſs of Scripture, even of the New Teſtament, is large; the Difficulty of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding it, at this Diſtance, great; the Lights which we have by Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Doctors, various, and by their Variety many times dazling and confounding one another; nay even whole Churches in Doctrinals very contrary to one another; and at leaſt one, and that the greateſt of them all, for the maintaining her Grandeur, has deſignedly, <hi>with all the Arts</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Epheſ. 4. 14.</note> 
               <hi>and Methods of Deceit,</hi> new modell'd the whole Frame of Chriſtian Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and not ſtuck in a ſort to corrupt even Scripture it ſelf, by impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing on the World her corrupt Tranſlation, and in many Points corrupter Senſe of it, for infallible Truth, and the only ſure way to Heaven: in which Impoſitions of hers all Proteſtants agree many Points to be falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and deſtructive. Now theſe being, and having been the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the preſent Age, and indeed of many late Ages; is it not the conſtant Doctrine of all Reformed Churches, that every Perſon ſhould with Prayer, Humility, and Study of the Truth, propoſing unto himſelf the Holy Scripture for his Rule, judg for himſelf? And muſt not every Man believe what is the Reſult of his Judgment, or what in Conſcience, according to Scripture, he judgeth Truth? Now perhaps ſundry Points which particular Doctors, yea which Churches have differently determin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and which ſome of them pretend to be of Faith, an honeſt inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Man cannot perceive the Holy Ghoſt to have determined at all; nor does he find them in the Apoſtles Creed (the old Standard or Leiger-Roll
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:51847:18"/> of Fundamentals:) Nay further, examining them according to the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy or <hi>Proportion of Faith,</hi> (that is, comparing them with undoubted Fundamentals) he cannot reſolve which Opinion bears moſt Proportion, or is moſt certain. In this Caſe what ſhall the Man do? For my own part I can ſee nothing more proper and ſafe, than to take the Matter in <hi>that Latitude wherein the Scripture delivered it.</hi> Had not learned Men differently interpreted and imbroiled the Text, perhaps I ſhould never have perceived any more than one Senſe of it, even that in which I now take it: But having ſeen their Gloſſes, I am ſenſible the Text will admit ſeveral Interpretations; and which of them was deſigned by the Holy Ghoſt, I know not: I disbelieve none of them; nor will I, as far as able, in my Practice act contrary to what either or any of them enforces. I ſubmit intirely to the Authority of God in all. Here's my <hi>negative Belief.</hi> I will not divide the Chriſtian Church, nor take Part with them that do di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide it, but <hi>hold the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace;</hi> maintain Chriſtian Charity with all Chriſtian People, and eſteem all them to be Chriſtians who are content to walk (or who, without the Contradiction of a diſorderly Life, profeſs to walk) by that Rule which I own, namely, Holy Scripture. This is the <hi>Latitude</hi> I plead for, and from which I think I never ſhall be driven.</p>
            <p>But there being but <hi>one Faith, there can be no more Latitude in Faith</hi>
               <note place="margin">§. 12.</note> 
               <hi>than there is in an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nit.</hi> This is a Subtilty indeed, and no doubt a ſtabbing Argument againſt the People of the long Name, as ſome are pleaſed to ſtile many conformable moderate Perſons. But are there not <hi>as many ſorts of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nits</hi> as there are of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nities?</hi> And did Mr. Dean never hear in Philoſophy of an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Compoſition,</hi> which is ſo far from ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding Parts, that it ſuppoſes them? Or in Arithmetick, did he never hear of <hi>Integrals<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and what minute Parts thereof Artiſts can make? No Latitude in an Unit: Yes, and in the one Faith too, eſpecially as by the one Faith we underſtand what Churches and Doctors have now made it. Have we not whole Syſtems of Opinions now adays made up into Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions of Faith? Certainly all controverted Points in Chriſtian Doctrine can no more be maturely determined, and the ſtated Truth diſtinctly be believed by all Men, than all Chriſtian Perfection be by all equally attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. There are thoſe to whom <hi>it is given</hi> in an ampler and more peculiar meaſure, to know the Myſtery of the Kingdom. Though all may have the ſame Scripture or Body of revealed Religion, all have not the ſame natural Sagacity and Judgment, the ſame Education and Advantages of Improvement, the ſame Leiſure and Opportunity for Search and Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Mind. Some, and that far the greateſt Numbers of Chriſtians, can only underſtand the common Chriſtianity, repent of their Sins, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:51847:18"/> in Well-doing depend upon God's Mercy in Chriſt Jeſus for Life everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Others <hi>leaving</hi> (that is, not ſtopping at thoſe) <hi>the Principles of the Doctrine of Chriſt,</hi> (the alone true Foundation) <hi>go on unto Perfection.</hi> So that there is a meaſure of Faith as well as of other Chriſtian Perfections: And God is doubly the Author of a Latitude in Faith; (1) In revealing his Truth in ſuch Terms as admit of a Latitude of Conception. (2) In giving to Men, as he ſees fit, ſuch meaſures of Knowledg and Perſwaſion as leaves them in an higher or lower Degree of Faith, and even of Holineſs: And accordingly <hi>in our Father's Houſe there are many Manſions.</hi> Nor can any Man with Reaſon gainſay theſe things.</p>
            <p>Now though this be far from <hi>thinking it indifferent what Men believe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 9.</note> 
               <hi>or whether they believe any thing or not;</hi> yea, faralſo <hi>from believing what we pleaſe;</hi> yet I confeſs it is believing, as by Grace we are able. I muſt conceive as I can, and judg as I can, and believe as I can too: And nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I, nor any Man alive, who believes any thing, can believe all that dictating Men will impoſe upon them. The Authority of the Church, it is true, is of great Weight, and will go very far to the determining any ſober Man's Judgment, in a caſe where Evidences on both ſides are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly equal, that is alike probable, or alike uncertain. But the Faith we owe to the Church, and that we owe to God, are very different. All the Churches or Councils in the World can never make that an Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of Faith which God has not made ſo. He who alone can beſtow Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, has alone Power to enact the Conditions of it, and make Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Faith. But in Controverſies the Church may declare her Senſe, and we are bound ſo far peaceably to ſubmit and accept it, as not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict or teach contrary, under Penalty of her Cenſures. And this I would be content to conceive the whole of what our Church requires, as to thoſe things which are meerly her Determinations: For in truth it is to no purpoſe for her to require ſuch Approbation and Conſent, which whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paid or no, ſhe can never come to have Knowledg; of which ſort is Belief and inward Approbation. To exact this, may breed Hypocriſy; it cannot be a Seed of Charity and true Chriſtian Concord. And thus as to that Latitude, Simplicity and negative Belief which have ſo much of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended the Apologiſt; though I am well ſatisfied, that had I imbraced his Definitions and Hypotheſes, he would have allowed me as great a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude in deceding from the Churches Doctrine, as he has taken himſelf.</p>
            <p>And now paſſing by many Favours (ſo I call divers ſcornful Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons<note place="margin">§. 13.</note> by the way) which Mr. Dean is pleaſed to beſtow upon me, I come next to profeſs, that notwithſtanding any thing which he hath ſaid to the contrary, I am clearly of the Mind ſtill, that it is Oppoſition chiefly which keeps many Heterodox Opinions and Pamphlets alive.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:51847:19"/>
            <p>But <hi>it is better ſuch Pamphlets ſhould be in an hundred Hands with an</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Anſwer, than in ſive without one.</hi> Not to tell him, he takes Care by the rate he receives for every Sheet he publiſhes, that ſuch Pieces of his as the <hi>Vindication of the Trinity,</hi> ſhall not be in the Hands of one Perſon in an hundred, (I am ſure, at leaſt on a certain time, I could not ſpare Money to buy it). I will only ſay, 'tis hard to determine which more ſubverts the Orthodox Doctrine, the Adverſaries Impugnations, or his Vindication. I have heard that the wicked <hi>Vanninus</hi> ſo writ in Proof of the Being of a God, as to increaſe the Suſpition of Atheiſts that there was none. And I do avow that Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> has ſo vindicated the Trinity, that he has, to his Power, made the Unity aſſerted by the Fathers utterly impoſſible, and run into the very Abſurdity whereto the Adverſaries would reduce us: For if his Definitions and Hypotheſes be true, there muſt unavoidably be three Gods, as has been ſhewn; and there may be as well three thouſand, or as many as <hi>Varro</hi> ſays the Romans ever had.</p>
            <p>No, <hi>theſe three are one,</hi> ſays Mr. Dean; one <hi>by mutual Conſciouſneſs.</hi> I anſwer, beſides that this amounts to no more than to an Unity of Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, which (as has been ſaid) is not the Unity that the Church and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ever held, and which we have ſeen the Council of <hi>Sardis</hi> avowed to be the Catholick Faith ever taught, received and delivered down, (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) one Subſtance, or an Unity of Subſtance; beſides this, I ſay, three thouſand Minds or Spirits may be as well conceived mutually conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as three; and ſo we may defend Polytheiſm, or maintain all the Gods of the Heathen to have been but one.</p>
            <p>Indeed I never read any Chriſtian Writer to go ſo near in expreſs Terms aſſerting a Plurality of Gods, ad the Dean of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> has done: a God, and a God, and a God, as has been ſhewn. And if this kind of ſpeaking be not direct or full enough, what is wanting in expreſs Terms, is abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly made up in his Hypotheſis, which unavoidably infers three Gods; and thoſe no more or otherwiſe one, than even an infinite Number (could there be ſuch a Number) of Minds might be one: which two Points, though I was content to ſtile only the Abſurdities to which our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries would reduce us, yet I know what Names other People would have given them, could they have been found in any Writings of mine.</p>
            <p>Further, it is to be conſidered, Dr. <hi>Sherlock's Vindication of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Holy and ever Bleſſed Trinity,</hi> (an auguſt and glorious Title, vaſtly raiſing the Expectation of all who read or hear it) came out with the Solemnity of a Publick, I had almoſt ſaid <hi>Canonical Licence</hi> in its Front, affixed thereto by an Eccleſiaſtical Reverend Perſon, authorized by Law for ſuch Purpoſe: So did his Apology alſo. This at firſt Sight re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents the Doctrine contained in them, not as the Sentiments of a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:51847:19"/> Doctor, but as Doctrine approved by our Church; for there are at leaſt three Doctors of the Church to avouch for it. And ſome will ſay, If it be thus authorized by the Chaplains, are not certain other much greater Perſons concerned for it? What Advantage now may the Enemy take every way thence? Plainly; foraſmuch as other Doctors and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of the Church cannot but diſapprove and diſclaim this Explication or Notion of the three Perſons, or of the Trinity, and only of ſuch an Unity as there aſſerted, it will and muſt be ſaid, we are neither agreed amongſt our ſelves as to Trinity nor Unity: Shall therefore the <hi>melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly Stander by</hi> be thought an Enemy to the Church for deſiring ſuch Writings as theſe may be forborn?</p>
            <p>Again, Mr. Dean tells us, that <hi>Dr.</hi> Wallis <hi>when he called the three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 9.</note> 
               <hi>three Somewhats, thereby only meant, that the true Notion of a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon he did not know:</hi> And hereto, by the way, Mr. Dean, according to his wonted Ingenuity or Care, ſubjoins, I commended this. No, Sir, that which I commended was what I wiſh had been to be found in you; Dr. <hi>Wallis</hi>'s Orthodoxy in the Acceptation of the word Perſons <hi>in divinis,</hi> (ſet down by me in the Doctor's own Words) <hi>for ſomething analogous to Perſons, and not ſignifying juſt the ſame.</hi> But to commend Dr. <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> or any one who worſhips three Perſons, for ſaying he does not know what a Perſon is, is ſo far from me, that I ſay Mr. Dean in imputing the Saying to Dr. <hi>Wallis,</hi> and the commending it to me, has wronged us both egregiouſly: the Doctor, in expoſing him (and Multitudes in him) as liable to this unavoidable Conſequence, that they worſhip they know not what: and me, in telling the World I commend them that do ſo. I delight not to ſearch further into, much leſs to exaggerate the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Books on this Subject have given our Adverſaries of all kinds. By theſe Touches it is plain more may be aſſigned: But as to thoſe two above-named Particulars, which I only ſtiled Abſurdities, the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or original Grounds of all the reſt; having now ſhewn them expreſly enough, I muſt mind Mr. Dean of his Promiſe, that he will <hi>correct them;</hi> and it may be a fit Subject for ſome of thoſe <hi>few ſhort Treatiſes,</hi> which he has told us he <hi>will publiſh on this Argument as he has leiſure:</hi> whether <hi>he correct them thankfully</hi> or no I value not much, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided<note place="margin">Pag. 11.</note> he ſincerely or expreſly <hi>recant</hi> them, which in caſe of <hi>Errors</hi> he has ſaid <hi>he will not bluſh</hi> to do.</p>
            <p>However I will not bluſh to preſs again what he endeavours to expoſe,<note place="margin">§. 14.</note> my Deſires to all to let this Controverſy reſt, as it was above thirteen hundred Years ago determined by two general Councils: And my Reaſon ſtands unſhaken, as far as I can ſee, by the Dean or any elſe: The Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements which have ſince been attempted upon it, have more em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broil'd
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:51847:20"/> it than explain'd it, and bring us down many times into groſſer and more phantaſtical Conceptions of the Deity than become us. As to what the Schools and Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> have done, I have already ſpoke my Senſe. I could have ſhewn that Dr. <hi>Walls</hi> was only the Engliſh Author for <hi>three Somewhats,</hi> and have cited a certain Father for <hi>tria quaedam;</hi> but I had rather Mr. Dean ſhould tell the World how ignorant I am of the Fathers, than that their Eſteem ſhould be leſſened by any thing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by me that may ſeem to reflect on them. Only becauſe the World, as if weary of metaphyſical Improvements in this and like Subjects, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins now to be fond of, or expect even in Chriſtian Myſteries ſome Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders from Phyſicks or Mathematicks, I ſhall give an Account of ſomething more copious in this kind, than what, as far as I know, our learned Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor here at home has as yet publiſhed. There is a Book intituled, <hi>Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> de la Republique des Lettres,</hi> imprinted at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> 1685. wherein I find an Account of an <hi>Eſſay</hi> called a Memorial [<hi>Memoire</hi>] communicated by <hi>M.</hi> and writ to ſhew the Habitude or Reſemblance [<hi>Rapport</hi>] of the three Dimenſions of a Body to the three Perſons of the Deity; in which, after a ſhort Preface of the different Natures of a think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and extenſe Subſtance, there is drawn a <hi>Parallel</hi> between <hi>La Trinite</hi> in one Column, and <hi>Laquantite</hi> in another, amounting to no fewer than <hi>twenty three Particulars.</hi> And after ſomewhat ſaid of the Uſe of theſe Parallels, wherein he utterly denies the falſe Idea's, as he terms them, of the School-men, he adds <hi>ſeven more parallel Inſtances<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> between the <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections Hereticks</hi> make againſt the <hi>Trinity,</hi> and ſuch as may be made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>triple Dimenſions of Bodies.</hi> Then follow <hi>ten Axioms</hi> out of the <hi>Religio rationalis Andreae Viſſovatii,</hi> (an Author of whom I can find no Account amongſt thoſe Books which I have to conſult) placed alſo Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumn-wiſe, the Trinity on one Side, and extenſe Subſtance on the other. He ends with a Promiſe (if this Eſſay take) of a <hi>Parallel</hi> between <hi>the Incarnation and the ſenſible World:</hi> on all which I will only ſay, <hi>Real</hi> and <hi>Phyſical Quantity</hi> exiſts only in <hi>Bodies; Mathematical Quantity</hi> merely in the <hi>Mind,</hi> or Thoughts of the Artiſt. Now how highly Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity is likely to be advanced by ſuch Speculations as theſe, what <hi>real</hi> and what <hi>rare ſpiritual Conceptions</hi> and <hi>Demonſtrations,</hi> at this rate, we ſhall in ſome time come to have touching God, I leave all conſidering Men to judg; and in the mean while again deſire all to ſtop at the afore-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned ſafe Boundaries of Faith and Peace.</p>
            <p>I muſt now proceed with Mr. Dean rebuking me, as ſurely <hi>intending</hi>
               <note place="margin">§. 15.</note> 
               <hi>this for no more than a Jeſt,</hi> that I would have the Doctrine of the <hi>Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty left upon its old bottom of Authority.</hi> And here he demands, <hi>would I my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 12.</note> 
               <hi>believe ſuch abſurd Doctrines as ſome repreſent the Trinity in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity to<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:51847:20"/> be, meerly upon Church-Authority? for his Part he declares he would not.</hi> And for my part, I who adhere to Scripture, and plead for ſuch ſtrict Adheſion, am preſs'd with none of theſe Abſurdities or abſurd Doctrines; but if he will not accept ſuch Terms or Forms of ſpeaking as <hi>Homoouſion,</hi> or <hi>Conſubſtantial, Conglorified,</hi> and the like, from Councils and Fathers, he muſt (which would be a great Fault in me) even let them alone. I do not know whence elſe he can or muſt receive them, nor who elſe coin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, and deſire him to inform me. Perhaps he will ſay what the great Father in this Controverſy did before him; theſe ſyllabical Words are not indeed in Scripture, but (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) their Senſe is. I anſwer; So I believe the Father-thought; and ſo I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve thought the Generality of the Nicene Fathers, (for by Mr. Dean's Favour, they pretended rather to determine this Point out of Scripture, than to <hi>deliver any traditionary Senſe thereof;</hi> and agreeable to this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence was the placing the Holy Records in the midſt of the Council;) yea (admitting what we judg good Conſequents out of Scripture to be of the ſame Truth with Scripture) ſo think I: but ſo do not others think, nor will I pretend my ſelf able, nor do I ſee any (notwithſtanding their mighty Boaſts) able to convince them. Demonſtrate to the World this to be the Senſe of Scripture, and the Controverſy is at an end: Till that be done, if we will be fair, we muſt own this to be the State of our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence. We have for the <hi>Orthodox</hi> Side, Scripture interpreted by the <hi>Tradition of the Church:</hi> this at length reſolves it ſelf mainly into <hi>Church-Authority.</hi> For the traditionary Senſe which determines Scripture to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify this, not that, is of ſuch Authority: and therefore is the Dogme thence concluded ſuch alſo. Wherefore I ſee no Reaſon to recal that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Acknowledgment of mine, (conceived indeed in Terms a little larger) <hi>After all Authority muſt define this Controverſy:</hi> Yet haply it might not be amiſs to deſire my Words may be ſtrictly attended: I ſaid indefinitely, <hi>Authority;</hi> for I know not whether it can be ſaid, <hi>ſingle Eccleſiaſtical Authority</hi> did ever <hi>effectually define it,</hi> (that is, appeaſe the Controverſy) nor will it, I fear, ever be able. There was ſome other <hi>concurrent Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> of which I forbear to ſpeak, interpoſed to temperate the Factious in a certain Council, as well as to recommend its Decrees: and ſo muſt there be amongſt us for the ending this Controverſy. Let but the <hi>Forms of Worſhip,</hi> which ſome Mens Conſciences cannot bear, be made eaſy, that we may unite in the Service of God; and 'tis no matter how <hi>ſevere the Laws</hi> be againſt any who ſhall <hi>write or ſpeak more</hi> in the Controverſy.</p>
            <p>I cannot tell but Mr. Dean may have private Reaſons which induce him rather to abide by the Arguments or Sentiments of ſome Fathers, than the Authority of the Councils by me inſiſted on. I have not pretended to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:51847:21"/> much Skill in Fathers and Councils; and no where imperiouſly to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy my Pretences within the Space of two or three Pages, rattle out over and over the ſame ſix or ſeven Fathers in a Breath, without producing a Word out of any of them, which ſome Men may interpret a Pretence to Skill in them, but no good Mark whence to diſcover it. However, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Judgment and Authority of Councils is ſo little in his Eſteem, and the <hi>learned and ſubtile Diſputations</hi> of a certain Perſon <hi>in the Nicene</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Council</hi> of ſo great Force with him, I will take leave, notwithſtanding my being ſo little vers'd in theſe Authors, to tell him, that though I have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ue and profound a Veneration for the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> as moſt Men living, yet I judg there is nothing has more expoſed that Council than thoſe tedious and jejune Diſputes reported by ſome to have paſſed therein. I have, I ſay, a true and profound Veneration for that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, and eſteem it only ſecond to that of the Apoſtles in <hi>Acts</hi> 15. Who can think otherwiſe of it that conſiders the <hi>Number</hi> of the Fathers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, or otherwiſe that reflects on the <hi>Quality</hi> of many (I do not ſay all) of them: the Number three hundreed and eighteen: their Quality, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of them ſuch who had even at that time bid fair for Martyrdom; Confeſſors of the firſt Rank, that bore in their Body <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. Hiſt. l. 1. c. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Marks of Chriſt;</hi> they are <hi>Theodoret</hi>'s Words of them in alluſion to the Apoſtles; that had ſome of them their Hands cut off, had been ſeared and tormented with Fire, and otherwiſe ſuffered for the Faith of Jeſus; and of ſome, I remember, he ſays, that they had the very <hi>Apoſtolick Gifts of Miracles;</hi> he mentions one who had <hi>raiſed the Dead.</hi> The Decrees of ſuch Perſons, I confeſs, next to thoſe of the Apoſtles, do obtain very much upon me. But as to theſe Decrees in Points of Faith, what ſhall we do for them? I know of none but their Creed which aſſerts indeed the Divinity of the Son, and his Conſubſtantiality with the Father; but of the Holy Ghoſt it makes only a bare mention, without aſſerting any thing, only profeſſing ſimply the Belief of the Holy Ghoſt. This Creed has been moſt religiouſly preſerved, and the Greek. Text thereof reputed ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred; inſomuch that in the Latin Edition of St. <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Alexandria</hi> his Dialogues touching the Trinity, we have the Greek Text ſet down intire by it ſelf: Admitting therefore this Creed inviolably, yet as to the Diſputes in this Council, by Mr. Dean's Favour, we are much to ſeek. <hi>Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> reports one Diſpute he had with <hi>Arius,</hi> but (if I miſtook not my ſelf when I read it) that was in the way to the Council, and not in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil it ſelf; for <hi>Athanaſius</hi> being at that time only a Deacon, though chief of the Alexandrian Quire of Deacons, I am not ſatisfied that he was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſo wonderfully to diſpute in the Council, as Mr. Dean pretends. I could give many Reaſons for my Opinion herein, but for Brevities ſake
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:51847:21"/> forbear them. Then as to the Diſputes reported by <hi>Gelaſius Cyzicenus, Photius,</hi> whoſe Credit I need not aſſert, cenſures him as a <hi>pitiful and</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Phot. Bib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lioth. Cod. 15.</note> 
               <hi>mean Writer, ſuperficial; and his Book no more Argumentative than Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical:</hi> So I render that obſcure Paſſage of my Author, cited in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin. And though <hi>Alfonſus Piſanus</hi> the Jeſuit, has lick'd him up, and put him off with all the Credit he can, yet hear what a late Doctor and Fellow of the <hi>Sorbon</hi> ſays of him [<hi>Genuina act a minimè continet:</hi>] <q>His Book contains not the genuine Acts of the Council: nay the Acts<note place="margin">Edmund. Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher. Hiſt. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. gen. l. 1. c. 2. Equidem cum maximo animi moeroredicere cogor, nullos extare libros, in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> quibus tot tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>táque fictitia ſcripta, quàm, in tomis Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliorum le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantur. §. 6.</note> thereof never came intirely to us.</q> And if not the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, much leſs the <hi>Debates,</hi> whereof the Acts were the Reſult. <hi>Gelaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> indeed talks of having tranſcribed and collected what he writes out of old Parchments of <hi>Dalmatius</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Cyzicum,</hi> which he found intire in his Father's Houſe; but either this was a Device to put off his Work with better Colour and Authority, or elſe that <hi>Dalmatius,</hi> if Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of that Hiſtory, was as ſhallow as himſelf. A better, and in theſe Matters a more judicious Hiſtorian (though I confeſs as to the Lives of Saints a little Monkiſh and Legendary) gives us this Account as to the Point in Hand: <q>
                  <hi>Hoſius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Corduba</hi> ſeems to be the firſt who brought in [to be treated of in Councils (I ſuppoſe) he means] the mention of thoſe Words, <hi>Subſtance</hi> and <hi>Subſiſtence,</hi> or <hi>Perſon,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.) For being ſent by <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Emperor to <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria</hi> for appeaſing the Diſturbances which <hi>Ariu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> had raiſed there, and <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> endeavouring alſo to pull up by the Roots the Opinion of <hi>Sabellius</hi> of <hi>Libya,</hi> he moved the Queſtion touching Subſtance and Subſiſtence, by which <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> much of a certain contentious kind of trifling (the word imports very near what we call <hi>Banter</hi>) was kindled: And the Nicene Council, which was held at length, eſteemed that Queſtion unworthy of Debate or Mention. But after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> when ſome again began to contend and trifle (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Matter, the Synod of <hi>Alexandria</hi> ſeems to me wiſely to have reſolved what I before reported. Now the Decree of the Synod of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> which he before reported, was this; Foraſmuch as the Queſtion of Subſtance and Subſiſtence (or Perſon) has much diſturbed the Churches, and frequent Contentions and Diſputations have hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore paſſed touching theſe Words, the Synod of <hi>Alexandria</hi> having diſcuſſed the Signification and proper Import of them, has decreed, that there is no need of theſe Terms touching God: for the word <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) is no where found in Holy Writ. But St. <hi>Paul,</hi> for the better expreſſing his Doctrine, abuſed the word <hi>Subſiſtence</hi> or <hi>Perſon,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) Notwithſtanding this Synod has decreed, that theſe Words ſhould be uſed after another way, when any have occaſion to confute
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:51847:22"/> the Hereſy of <hi>Sabellius,</hi> leſt through Want (or Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biouſneſs) of Words we ſhould think that in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> of God we call one thing by three Names: but that every of the Names which we uſe in the Trinity being trebly diſtinguiſh'd, ſhould be theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logically expreſs'd by a proper Subſiſtence.</q> Thus my Author, who alſo preſently after the Paſſage where I firſt broke off, reports a remarkable Piece of Advice out of <hi>Evagrius,</hi> which I ought not to omit: <q>
                  <hi>Evagrius Aſcetes,</hi> ſaith he, in his Book of Monaſticks, diſſwades us to diſcourſe boldly and on our Heads touching the Deity, and would by no means have Men to go about to define God, he being moſt ſimple. For, adds he, every Propoſition or Enunciation contains either ſome general Nature which is predicated, or ſome ſpecial one; or elſe ſome Difference, properly or Accident, or ſomewhat compounded and made up of theſe: But if we can perceive none of theſe in the Holy Trinity, let us adore that with Silence which we cannot utter or declare.</q> 
               <hi>Nicephor. Calliſt. l. 10. c.</hi> 15. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> himſelf, whoſe Authority ought to go vaſtly further, is ſometimes in the ſame ſtrain, who, though in his numerous Books of the Trinity he ſiſts<note place="margin">Veriùs enim cogitatur Deus quàm dicitur, &amp; veriùs eſt quam cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>De Trin. lib. 7.</hi>
               </note> all as fine as he can, yet at length confeſſes, to the ſame Effect with my Author laſt cited, the Subject to be beyond Expreſſion: For, ſaith he, our Thoughts of God are commonly more true than our Expreſſions; But God more truly is than we can think.</p>
            <p>But to return again to Hiſtory and Mr. Dean: The <hi>Coeſſentiality</hi> or <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiality</hi> of the Son with the Father was the Point determined againſt <hi>Arius</hi> in the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> which was indeed previous or preliminary to one Part of the Doctrine of the Trinity: but the Controverſy of the Trinity of Perſons was not raiſed but by the Followers of <hi>Arius,</hi> not by himſelf, (as <hi>Baronius</hi> both witneſſes and proves) and therefore could not be decided in the Council of <hi>Nice.</hi> If therefore we were to ſtand only to the Decrees of the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> in the Matter of the Trinity, our Faith herein would be comparatively very ſhort: For by that Council nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was there affirmed a Trinity of Perſons, nor Unity of the three. It is not therein ſo much as determined what the Holy Ghoſt is. Mr. Dean therefore did me wrong if he intended thoſe Words, <hi>The Council of</hi> Nice,<note place="margin">Pag. 13.</note> 
               <hi>on whoſe Authority we muſt reſt,</hi> (namely in Point of the Trinity) ſhould be underſtood to be my Words. He may be permitted to confound the learned and ſubtil Diſputations of <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in behalf of the Divinity of Chriſt, (which Point indeed was determined in the Council of <hi>Nice</hi>) and the Controverſy of the Trinity in Unity, (to which there was ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> Advance made in the Council of <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi>) he, I ſay, may
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:51847:22"/> be admitted to confound theſe two together, and to reſt for both upon the ſingle Authority of the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> becauſe in that Council he will find <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and ſo may hope to hook in the Confeſſion commonly called the Creed of St. <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> (I uſe the Terms of our own Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy:) but I expreſly avouched the <hi>Authority of the Nicene and firſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinopolitan Councils in Conjunction,</hi> as having betwixt them ſetled the Doctrine of the Trinity; yet not in the hard Words which after-Ages uſed. For in theſe two Councils, though there be in effect three Perſons de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, yet is not the term <hi>three Perſons</hi> uſed; but both the Matter and the Language wherein the Deciſion is made, looks much liker that of the Scripture than what we find in a certain later Creed, when Men pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to draw Conſectaries from theſe Councils Definitions, and put ſuch their Conſectaries into hard, artificial and intricate Terms; and then impoſed all for Faith, with ſo much Nicety, that it is at leaſt as eaſy to miſtake as to underſtand the Truth: and ſometimes really the Miſtake is much the more obvious.</p>
            <p>I cannot forbear an Inſtance or two out of the Creed juſt now men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, uſually aſcribed to <hi>Athanaſius;</hi> but if <hi>Voſſius</hi> be in the right, compiled much after his Age by one <hi>Anaſtaſius,</hi> as he conjectures, if my Memory fail not, for I have not my Book by me: that Creed then thus proceeds; <hi>THE FATHER IS ETERNAL, THE SON ETERNAL, AND THE HOLY GHOST ETERNAL; AND YET THEY ARE NOT THREE ETERNALS, B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T ONE ETERNAL. AS ALSO THERE ARE NOT THREE INCOMPREHENSIBLES, NOR THREE <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NCREATED, B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T ONE <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NCREATED, AND ONE INCOMPREHENSIBLE.</hi> Suppoſe now a Man ſhould thus argue hence; If there are three, yet not three uncreated, but one uncreated, then two of the three muſt be created: For the three muſt be either crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or uncreated, that is, eternally exiſtent. But it is further alſo added, that there are not three Eternals, but one Eternal: therefore ſuppoſing the Father to be uncreated and eternal, (as of the three moſt properly and eſſentially Uncreatedneſs and Eternity belongs to him, inſomuch as the Son is his Begotten, and the Holy Ghoſt proceeds from him;) ſuppoſing, I ſay, the Father uncreated and eternal, it ſeems hence unavoidably to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, the Son and the Holy Ghoſt are created and not eternal: for there are not three Uncreated, nor three Eternals. The ſame may be ſaid in like manner as to the other Attributes of Incomprehenſible and Almighty. And if any ſhould profeſs the Son and Holy Ghoſt created, or not eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, would not all cry out immediately, Hereſy! Blaſphemy! It will not be ſufficient here to ſay, It is confeſſed before that the Son is uncreate, and the Holy Ghoſt uncreate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for that Confeſſion is now contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:51847:23"/> by ſaying there is but one uncreate. What ſhall we then do to extricate our ſelves from the Niceties of this Creed? How few of the People have the Clew? Verily not one in a thouſand of the Laity that<note place="margin">'Hic ponuntur adjectivè iſtae dictiones [viz. coaeterni, &amp;c.] ibi autem ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectivè. Gloſſa ad verbum Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aeterni. De ſumma Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, c. 1. Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miter credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</note> ſay, ſing or receive this Creed, and it may be not one in an hundred of the Clergy. But to ſalve all, behold a wholeſom Diſtinction out of a known Gloſs: When we ſay, the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt are all three uncreate, we take Uncreate as an Adjective; and then the Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is true. When we ſay there are not three uncreate, we take it as a Subſtantive: For if we ſhould ſay there are three uncreated, taking it as a Subſtantive, it were Hereſy. And ſo in the caſe of Eternal; when we ſay the Father is eternal, the Son eternal, the Holy Ghoſt eternal, and all three eternal, we take Eternal as an Adjective: But if we ſhould take Eternal as a Subſtantive, then we muſt deny that there are three Eternals: (ſurely then by the way muſt we alſo deny that there are three infinite Minds, and that even according to <hi>Athanaſius</hi> himſelf: But to come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to the Gloſs) Can now any Man living give me a Reaſon why Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>create or Eternal ſhould be leſs an Adjective when underſtood of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete Subſtance or Eſſence, than it is when underſtood of an uncreate Perſon? And yet taking it either ſubſtantively or adjectively, if I ſhould ſo uſe it, as to deny there are three uncreated Perſons, I am as much a Heretick as if I ſhould ſay there are three uncreated Eſſences. There is therefore very happily a further Remedy in the ſaid Gloſs, namely, that<note place="margin">Hic deſignat Perſonas, ibi Eſſentiam. <hi>Gl. ubi ſupra.</hi>
               </note> when we profeſs all three are uncreate and coeternal, we muſt underſtand or ſupply the word <hi>Perſon:</hi> When we ſay there is but one Uncreate and one Eternal, we muſt underſtand <hi>Eſſence</hi> or <hi>Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In fine then, if we have not Metaphyſicks enough, and Grammar enough, to find out when a Word is to denote the Eſſence, and when the Perſon, or perhaps when it is to be taken adjectively, when ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, we ſhall be led by the very Letter of this Creed, to profeſs Hereſy and Blaſphemy inſtead of the true Faith. Were it not now better that this Creed were either made plainer, or totally laid aſide, than urged and uſed as it is? But indeed neither of the two Councils mentioned made any ſuch Creed as this; nor, as I really believe, did <hi>Athanaſius</hi> himſelf: He and others of the Fathers perhaps did diſpute or opine to this or the like Effect; but ſurely they never deſigned to impoſe ſuch a Form of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief under ſuch damning Clauſes as are contained herein. This may the rather be concluded, for that <hi>Gregory Nyſſen</hi> penn'd the Conſtantinopoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan<note place="margin">
                  <hi>So</hi> Baronius.</note> Creed in that Council, ten Years at leaſt after <hi>Athanaſius</hi> his Death: And amongſt other Fathers of that Council, <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> and <hi>Jerome</hi> (cited here to little Purpoſe by Mr. Dean) approved it as it is, without the pretended Athanaſian Criticiſms and Severities; nay with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:51847:23"/> the very <hi>Filioque.</hi> I had Reaſon therefore, as to the Doctrine of the Trinity, not to go beyond the Deciſions of theſe Councils, but to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſce in their Authorities. What further Authority, beyond that of the Church, interpoſed in the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> I have no mind to ſpeak. I will alſo paſs by here, as ſmall Faults, ſome Blunders of Mr. Dean's which he is guilty of in his huddle of Fathers, making St. <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> St. <hi>Hilary,</hi> and St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> to <hi>write largely againſt theſe Hereſies, which former Councils had condemned:</hi> whereas they all three died when there had but yet one Council ſat; and therein, as far as with Certainty appears, but one Hereſy, namely that of <hi>Arim,</hi> condemned; (for I cannot allow the <hi>Quarto Decimani</hi> to have been Hereticks:) they could not therefore write againſt Hereſies condemned by Councils. But waving theſe and other Exceptions which I might juſtly make touching all theſe Fathers Writings on this Subject, as being impertinently cited againſt me; I ſay after all, if the Worſhip of the Trinity might be left as theſe Fathers, and particularly as St. <hi>Hilary</hi> in the End of his twelfth Book of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, left it, (whoſe Words I produce not, for a Reaſon any one may gueſs who pleaſes to conſult them) the Differences in this Controverſy amongſt Proteſtants would be nearer a Compromiſe. And thus as to my Adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the Authority of theſe Councils.</p>
            <p>My next Charge is, what I confeſs was great News to me, that I am<note place="margin">§. 16. <hi>Pag. 14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>well vers'd in Mr.</hi> Hobbs's <hi>Divinity.</hi> Truly though I neither have, nor ever had any Eſteem for Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi>'s Divinity, yet I could wiſh my ſelf better skilled in it, for then I ſhould better know it when I meet with it in other Mens Writings diſguiſed, (now 'tis ſaid, a certain great Perſon, no Stranger to the Temple, has lately eſpouſed it under a very ſlighty Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe) and I ſhould be able more perfectly to wipe off the Imputation of being a Diſciple to it at preſent, without any Conſciouſneſs to my ſelf caſt upon me. I could here tell Mr. Dean a very true Secret; that there were two Books which I was afraid to read when I was young, leſt they ſhould corrupt me, and Mr. <hi>Hobbs's Leviathan</hi> was one: And having neglected it when my Curioſity was ſtrongeſt, I never read it ſince. So that it would be very ſtrange, ſhould I be well vers'd in a Man's Doctrine which I never read: But the beſt of it is, Mr. Dean ſhews here alſo his great Reading, and cites Mr. <hi>Hobbs,</hi> juſt as before he did the Fathers, at random, without giving us any Text out of him. And I neither have by me, nor in caſe I had, have I leiſure to ſearch all Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi>'s Works, to ſee whether he has any ſuch Aſſertion as Mr. Dean alledges. In an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering Arguments from Teſtimony, the Teſtimony it ſelf ought firſt to be examined: And this not appearing, I muſt for that Reaſon wave any more particular Anſwer to this Charge: Only as to what follows in the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:51847:24"/> Apology, I will renew my <hi>Requeſt</hi> to Mr. Dean, <hi>as being a Perſon of Learning, for that ſmall Favour,</hi> that he will hereafter be conſiſtent with, and <hi>not contradict himſelf;</hi> and particularly that he will no more <hi>affirm that Point made plain and eaſy,</hi> which he <hi>confeſſes difficult and incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible.</hi> And to prevail with him for this Boon, I will promiſe publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to beg his Pardon for the Affront of making this my Requeſt to him a ſecond time, if I do not immediately prove that in this Matter of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, which here in his Apology he confeſſes to be <hi>an incomprehenſible My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery,</hi> he does not ſay again and again in his Vindication thereof, that he has made it plain and eaſy, and ſo has contradicted himſelf in the Point objected. Firſt, I ſay he confeſſes here the Divine Nature, the Trinity of Divine Perſons, and the Unity of the Divine Eſſence, to be incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible. Secondly, He ſays in his <hi>Vindication of the Doctrine of the Holy Trinity,</hi> (p. 48.) <hi>that he will not pretend to fathom ſuch a Myſtery as this.</hi> Here he is for the <hi>Incomprehenſibility</hi> of it. Then in his Preface to his Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation he tells us, <hi>the writing that Book coſt him many Thoughts; and thoſe who have a mind throughly to underſtand it, muſt not think much if it coſt them ſome,</hi> notwithſtanding all that he has done to explain the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery. Here's the <hi>Difficulty</hi> of it acknowledged ſtill: Yet a little before, in the very ſelf-ſame Preface, he ſays, <hi>he has given a very eaſy and intelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Notion of a Trinity in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi> And in his <hi>Vindication,</hi> (p. 66.) that <hi>his Account thereof gives a plain and intelligible Solution of all the Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties and ſeeming Contradictions in the Doctrine of the Trinity.</hi> And again, (<hi>p.</hi> 68.) in a kind of an <hi>Epiphonema, This is a very plain and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible Account of this great and venerable Myſtery, as plain and intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible as the Notion of one God, or of one Perſon in the Godhead:</hi> Notions which are very eaſy and intelligible, and whereof all the Difficulties and ſeeming Repugnancies or Contradictions have received a plain and eaſy Solution, are certainly comprehenſible and eaſy: For what hinders them from being ſo? Or what do we mean in our preſent State by compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending any Notion or Doctrine, but a clear underſtanding it without any Difficulty or Perplexity? That which I ſaid therefore of <hi>ſome Writers pretending to make this Controverſy comprehenſible and eaſy,</hi> is verified in him, though I did not name him, and ſo is no <hi>ſpiteful and ſcandalous Imputation of mine</hi> to him, as he, in his good Nature and ſweet Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, is pleaſed to ſtile it, but was juſtly and truly ſpoken with Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and peaceable Deſign: And he muſt one Day anſwer, if he do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, for this his ſecond ſlandering me with <hi>Spite againſt him,</hi> whom<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 11, &amp; 15.</note> (God knows) I both loved and honoured, and at preſent wiſh him as well as my own Soul; nor do I reprehend any thing in him which I would bear in my ſelf.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:51847:24"/>
            <p>But now I may ſet my Heart at Reſt as to this Controverſy, if Mr. Dean will ſtand to the Profeſſion he has made; for he ſays, <hi>all that any Man</hi> (therefore that he) <hi>pretends to in vindicating the Doctrine of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 16.</note> 
               <hi>is to prove that this Faith is taught in Scripture.</hi> This is that which I would be at, and have contended for, that we may have nothing ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truded upon us for Faith in this Point, but what is taught in Scripture; and then I am ſure there will be no fear that any wiſe Man ſhould <hi>reject Scripture for its ſake, or put ſtrained and unnatural Senſes on it, to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile it to Reaſon:</hi> But that three ſuch Perſons as he has defined are by Scripture aſſerted, or can be thence concluded to be in the Deity, I have denied, I do and muſt ever deny, and conceive I have proved contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictious.</p>
            <p>In the next Place, having repeated his old Prevarication touching my<note place="margin">§. 17.</note> ſtiling <hi>the Socinians the learned Writers of Controverſy,</hi> he is diſpleaſed with me for not taking them to task for <hi>denying the Divine Nature to be incomprehenſible.</hi> Truly I never heard or read any of the Socinians guilty of ſuch Preſumption or Blaſphemy. But this I take only to be a Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence drawn by himſelf from a certain Opinion of theirs, and then faſtned upon them: Of which kind of fair dealing I will ſay nothing for the preſent. But I do know there are ſome who deny <hi>God's Preſcience of future Contigents,</hi> touching which I had no Occaſion to ſpeak; no more had he here, but that he would hedg in any thing, pertinent or imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, to inodiate an innocent Perſon; which being he has done, I will take the Occaſion to profeſs before <hi>the Searcher of all Hearts, who knows what is in Man,</hi> that he knows I do believe, and in my Soul adore his Preſcience; that I abhor any Suſpicions of it, as ſeeing ſcarce any of his Perfections more clearly expreſs'd, and by a World of Inſtances verified in Holy Scripture. Nay, I voluntarily profeſs, I cannot conceive infinite Knowledg without Preſcience; and though, I do confeſs, I cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend infinite Knowledg, becauſe I am very finite, yet I bleſs him who <hi>helps my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief,</hi> and has as fully poſſeſs'd my Heart with the Perſwaſion thereof, as with the Perſwaſion of his Exiſtence.</p>
            <p>But I cannot ſo eaſily believe Mr. Dean's Notions for facilitating, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the comprehending the next Divine Attribute, which he lugs-in, namely <hi>Eternity;</hi> which though he truly ſays, (<hi>pag. 16. lin. 28, 29.) to be without Beginning and without Succeſſion,</hi> yet with his uſual Attention he explains (<hi>lin</hi> 32.) to be <hi>a Succeſſion without a Beginning, a Second or a Third without a Firſt.</hi> This Notion I will not accuſe him to have taken from the School-Doctors.</p>
            <p>Only I muſt ask him why he put thoſe Words, <hi>a God Adequate and Commenſurate to our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings, a little finite comprehenſible God,</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:51847:25"/> in the ſame Character in which he ordinarily puts the Words he cites or wire-draws from my Paper. If he did it with a Deſign to poſſeſs the Reader that I had any ſuch Words, or had ſaid any thing from whence ſuch an Inſerence could be made, I have another Kindneſs to thank him for, of a like Nature to his others.</p>
            <p>I now proceed to account for the laſt Reaſon I aſſigned for the preſent<note place="margin">§. 18.</note> Unreaſonableneſs of ſome Mens agitating this Controverſy, which was, <hi>Hereby</hi> (that is, as both the very Title and the Paper it ſelf expreſly aſſert, by ſome learned Mens preſent Writings on this Controverſy) <hi>our Church at preſent, and the common Chriſtianity, it may be feared, will be daily</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 18.</note> 
               <hi>more and more expoſed to atheiſtical Men,—they being not likely to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>look the Advantages thus daily given them.</hi> This Mr. Dean, according to his uſual way, firſt calumniouſly perverts to another Senſe; then for this <hi>bold Stroke,</hi> as he calls it, will ſcarce allow me to be either <hi>a Chriſtian or a Divine:</hi> And laſtly falls on catechiſing me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt;</hi> He calumniouſly perverts my Senſe: for, ſays he, <hi>The Sum of this is, that to vindicate the Doctrine of the Trinity againſt Socinians, will make Men Atheiſts.</hi> Not ſo faſt, good Mr. Dean: This Sum agrees not either with your own reckoning or with mine: Three times at leaſt in your Paper you ſaid, <hi>theſe learned Writers of Controverſies,</hi> by me de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, <hi>were the Socinians:</hi> According to which (your own) Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, your Propoſition (or the Sum) explicitely ſhould have been this, The Socinians preſent writing againſt the Trinity will make Men Atheiſts. Do you then deny that Propoſition? No; you'l ſay, I believe, you thought not of it. But you know very well on the other ſide, that <hi>amongſt the preſent learned Writers of Controverſy your ſelf were more immediately concerned;</hi> (they are your own Words, <hi>pag.</hi> 2.) And now the Sum, if truly ſtated, will be much different, namely this; Such Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dications of the Trinity, as that writ by Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> tend rather to make Men Atheiſts than to convert Socinians. This, Sir, was my mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and this I re-aſſert. For Atheiſts may confute Tritheiſm or Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm, (for my Part I ſee not how either is defenſible;) and having pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſuch Doctrines in Religion to be falſe, they will be ready to conclude all Religion is ſo too: but they can never overthrow the Doctrine of one God the Father of all; and one Saviour, the Son of God, our Lord Chriſt Jeſus; and of one Spirit ſanctifying and uniting the whole Body of Chriſtian People; or of theſe three being one. And this, if you will call it <hi>a bold Stroke,</hi> I ſtick to it, and fear not being expoſed though I double it.</p>
            <p>The Subſtance of two of his Queſtions is anſwered already. Firſt, <hi>Do I believe the Doctrine of the Trinity to be deſenſible or no?</hi> I do, as deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:51847:25"/> in Scripture, but not upon his novel Definitions and Hypotheſes: But <hi>why do I not defend it better?</hi> I have partly anſwered it already; and a further Anſwer to that, and to his ſecond Queſtion, will come in by and by. In the mean time as to his third; <hi>Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> are Atheiſts concerned in the Diſputes of the Trinity?</hi> Very much in ſuch Vindications of it, which give ſuch a Notion of the true God as implicates, or is inconſiſtent with it ſelf, (<hi>viz.</hi>) that the true God, adored by all Chriſtian People, ſhould be three infinite Minds, and yet not three infinite Minds: If it be, as it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible that there ſhould be, more infinite Minds than one, then will A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts ſay, it is impoſſible ſuch a Being ſhould exiſt, as you deſcribe your God to be; that is, there is no God.</p>
            <p>After theſe Queſtions I am to be <hi>told a Secret, which though in great</hi>
               <note place="margin">§. 19. <hi>Pag. 19.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Modeſty I conceal, yet poſſibly I may be privy to,</hi> (viz.) <hi>that Atheiſts and Deiſts, Men who are for no Religion, are of late very zealous Socinians.</hi> I eaſily believe and acknowledg Mr. Dean better acquainted with the Town than I am: but if Atheiſts and Deiſts be zealous Socinians, let him ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver again object to me my Socinian Friends; for I proteſt I have not, to my Knowledg, any familiar Acquaintance, much leſs Friendſhip, with any Atheiſts or Theiſts in the World. I pray, as our Church teaches to pray, <hi>FOR ALL INFIDELS AS WELL AS T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RKS AND JEWS,</hi> that <hi>GOD WO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LD T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RN THEIR HEARTS:</hi> And in my Sphere, as God gives me Opportunity, I deſire to labour in his Church to that purpoſe; but otherwiſe I am ſo far from eſpouſing the Converſation, much leſs Friendſhip of any ſuch, as that I ſay with the great Apoſtle, <hi>If any Man love not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, let him be Anathema Maran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atha.</hi> And as for my own part, I from my Heart receive every Tittle of the revealed Chriſtian Religion; particularly as to thoſe two <hi>Magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> the <hi>Trinity</hi> and <hi>Incarnation.</hi> Touching the former I have once and again declared my Judgment and Faith: and touching the latter, this being the meeteſt Place wherein to profeſs my Faith of it, I do profeſs ſincerely to believe <hi>my Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the only begotten Son of God, the Word who was in the Beginning, and who was with God, and was and is God, bleſſed for ever,</hi> to have been <hi>in fulneſs of Time made of a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> and ſo to have <hi>become Fleſh,</hi> or truly taken upon him Fleſh and Blood; to <hi>have been in the World as we are in the World,</hi> ſubject to all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, <hi>Sin only excepted;</hi> and that as ſuch, <hi>having by himſelf purged our Sins, he is ſat down on the right Hand of the Majeſty on high;</hi> and as he <hi>lives for ever to make Interceſſion for us,</hi> ſo <hi>he ſhall come to judg the World</hi> at the laſt Day. Thus do I from my Heart adore and preach him, and ſhall do, I truſt, to my dying Hour. I know indeed, and have Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with ſome who are not in all theſe Particulars of my Mind; yet neither
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:51847:26"/> are they <hi>licentious Wits, nor do they ridicule and ſcorn this Faith;</hi> nor do I ſee how any ſober Men dare ridicule it: But ſome vertuous Rationaliſts having perhaps faln upon bad Books, and by that Means lying under ſtrong Prepoſſeſſions, they miſinterpret theſe Paſſages of Holy Scripture which I have reported, and others like, and endeavour to evade their Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence when applied to that Senſe, to which we of the Church of <hi>England</hi> alledg them. Now I do not think Stiffneſs and an immoderate <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a winding up the State of each Queſtion ſtill higher and higher, and then diſputing ſcornfully, and defending all in new Methods, or by new Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſes, to be the way to reclaim theſe Men; but what I conceive to be moſt ſerviceable, I ſhall, before I have done, ſpeak out and ſubmit. As to Men that <hi>ridicule and ſcoff</hi> at any thing in <hi>Religion,</hi> yea though it be erroneous, as long as it is conſiſtent with Holineſs and Charity, has a fair Claim to Scripture, and ſeems deducible thence, I think ſuch Scoffers highly prophane; and both theſe and all ſuch, who treat thoſe that are not of their Opinions with Scorn and Haughtineſs, I judg them to be next door to <hi>David</hi>'s Scorners, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1. namely, in the higheſt Claſs of the <hi>Wicked,</hi> and very near being incorrigible: which is all I will ſay, as to this Imputation, of my having entertained a Friendſhip with ſuch Men.</p>
            <p>Mr. Dean goes on and ſays, <hi>I have found out ſuch a Reaſon to prove</hi>
               <note place="margin">§. 20. <hi>Pag. 20.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the preſent Danger of diſputing the Controverſy of the Holy Trinity, as he believes was never dream'd of, and that is, that it is one of the Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals of Chriſtian Religion: Now to litigate touching a Fundamental, is to turn it into Controverſy,</hi> &amp;c. Here I muſt again complain of ſoul deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; my Words were, <q>The Doctrine of the Bleſſed Trinity, in whoſe Names we and all Chriſtians are or ought to have been baptized, is eſteemed, as it is if duly ſtated, one of the Fundamentals of Chriſtian Religion.</q> It is apparent I did affirm the Doctrine of the Trinity a Fundamental with this Reſtriction, if duly ſtated. He charges it upon me, as affirm'd ſimply and at large. I deny it to be <hi>a Fundamental,</hi> or ſo much <hi>a Truth,</hi> as Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> ſtates it in his Vindication of it, (<hi>viz.) that there is a Trinity of infinite Minds,</hi> &amp;c. though, with Reverence, I acknowledg and believe it to be <hi>both a Truth</hi> and <hi>a Fundamental,</hi> as the Scripture ſtates it. Now for Men to take the Name of a fundamental and revered Truth, the Holy Trinity, and affix it to a novel and groſs Pack of Errors, and to go on to diſpute for thoſe Errors under the ſacred Title of a Fundamental of the Catholick and Apoſtolick Faith, which was plainly enough my Senſe, this I ſay and ſtand to it, is of dreadful Danger, and may prove of as miſchievous Conſequence as moſt Practices aſſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. For in caſe the Adverſary diſprove and expoſe that Error, it is not with the Generality of People the <hi>Error that ſuffers,</hi> but that <hi>great Truth,</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:51847:26"/> the ſacred Name whereof was abuſed. And whereas he demands, <hi>Is it dangerous to preſerve and defend Foundations when Hereticks unſettle them?</hi> I anſwer, he has truly <hi>done neither,</hi> (neither ſecured nor defended them) but very ſurely has he done a third thing, he has to his Power <hi>changed them.</hi> Wherefore to all that dreadful aggravative Diſcourſe, which takes up a whole Page and an half, ſpent to render me ridiculous, and my Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 20, &amp; 21.</note> extravagant, as if, according to what I urge, Men might not <hi>argue againſt Atheiſm;</hi> I will give no other Anſwer, than that I pray God to forgive him the making this Parallel, and grant unto him hereafter better to employ his Time and Parts than in ſuch open and unartificial Exagge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</p>
            <p>In the next Page follows a Piece of News which I am truly to thank him for, touching <hi>a Treatiſe in the Preſs from our excellent Primate.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 22.</note> Now though this Intimation was intended againſt the Deſign of my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, as an Argument from Authority, and the Authority too of ſuch a Perſon, whom ſhould I offer to except againſt, I ſhould moſt juſtly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe my Judgment, if no more; yet ſo welcome is the Tidings he tells me, that here alſo I forgive both this his ill Intent, and the ſly Scoff with which he concludes that Paragraph; not doubting but when I ſee that Piece, I ſhall find in it both plain and perſpicuous Scripture-Notions, clear Reaſon and genuine Antiquity. Beſides I muſt tell the Apologiſt, I look upon his Grace, both by his publick Station and perſonal Qualifications, far otherwiſe capacitated to write on this Subject than a private Doctor; ſuch as I ſuppoſe Mr. Dean was, when he writ what he ſtiled <hi>the Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Holy and ever Bleſſed Trinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I now come to what he has to ſay againſt my laſt Argument for a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary<note place="margin">§. 21.</note> Forbearance of theſe Diſputes, which he thus reports; that I ſay, <hi>All Controverſies are now unſeaſonable in ſuch a Juncture, wherein nothing but an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Counſels, and joining Hands and Hearts can preſerve the Reformation, and ſcarce any thing more credit it than an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion in Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals.</hi> This Report of my Argument is according to his wonted Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour and Veracity: But my Argument, by his Favour, ſtood not ſo in my Paper; it was more carefully expreſs'd, had more Parts, and thoſe preſſing cloſer. I deſire it may be conſidered, I was to ſay as much as I could in a little; and however Mr. Dean thinks fit to deal with me, I am not aſhamed of any Part of what I ſaid: My Argument then ſtood thus; <q>As indeed all Controverſies amongſt Proteſtants are moſt unſeaſonable in ſuch a Juncture, wherein, under God, nothing but an Union of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and joining Hands and Hearts can preſerve the Reformation, (and ſcarce any thing more credit and juſtify it than an Union in Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals;) ſo above all other Controverſies none can well be thought of,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:51847:27"/> worſe tim'd than this.</q> Of which ill timing it I gave a very particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Proof, too warm it ſeems for him to touch upon, and therefore he ſlipp'd it away between his Fingers as if it had not been. But how an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers he my Argument? Firſt he <hi>disjoints</hi> it, then <hi>anſwers to what Parts</hi> of it he pleaſes, and to thoſe Parts <hi>in what Order</hi> he pleaſes: And finally, <hi>never conſiders the Parts as connected</hi> and together, adding Strength to the main Concluſion. Indeed ſuch dealing as this, with ſome Scorn in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlaced, is his uſual way of confuting. What he ſays worth notice, I ſhall reflect upon. The firſt Member of my Argument he thinks fit to ampliate, and <hi>will ſay a little more, that they [i. e.</hi> all Controverſies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Proteſtants, which was the Subject of my Propoſition] <hi>are always unſeaſonable; for there is no Juncture ſeaſonable to broach Hereſies and oppoſe Truth.</hi> But may there be no Controverſies, eſpecially amongſt Proteſtants, which broach not Hereſies? The Denial of the Trinity duly ſtated, I allow to be Hereſy. But we, in the firſt Member of the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſpeak of <hi>all Controverſies amongſt Proteſtants.</hi> Now do all Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſions amongſt Proteſtants ariſe to Hereſy on one ſide or other? God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid! Again, in times of publick Peace may there not be (very ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly) amicable Conferences and Arguings between thoſe who diſſent from one another, in order to clearing Difficulties, and ſo to brotherly Accord? Even thoſe Treaties are certainly ſome kind of Controverſies, though ſome Men may be very unfit for them, and therefore have little Kindneſs for them: and thoſe, I ſtand to it, ought to be held in due Seaſon. But at preſent I did not think even theſe kind of Arguings ſeaſonable, but would have them alſo ſuſpended; and was of Opinion, that as things ſtand, all Proteſtants ſuffering each other to worſhip God in his own way, according to the Conſcience of each, ſhould join againſt a common Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. What I ſaid may be Truth and adviſable, and as far as I yet ſee, is ſo. What Mr. Dean adds is not true, and his Proof of it is very inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, to ſay no worſe: For he would prove all Controverſies to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways unſeaſonable, becauſe ſome are ſo. I will not tell him, that even <hi>Hereſies</hi> may be, and daily are in Univerſity-Diſputations, and like Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical Exerciſes, ſtrongly argued for, and Truth oppoſed; not only for exerciſing and ripening Scholars, but that all the Strength Hereſies have may be detected and enervated, and the weaker Side of Truth ſecured: ſo that thus alſo all Controverſies aſſerting Hereſy, and oppoſing Truth, are not always unſeaſonable. So great a Diſputant as Mr. Dean ought not to have advanced ſo univerſal a Propoſition without more Caution. As to his defending Fundamental Truths, I have already ſpoken: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <hi>ſeaſonable the defending</hi> them may always be, I ſay in a word, the <hi>changing of them can be never ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:51847:27"/>
            <p>Next he repeats two other Members of my Argument, and begins with carping at the laſt thus; <hi>Is the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion in Doctrinals ever the greater that Socinians boldly and publickly affront the Faith of the Church, and no body appears to defend it?</hi> I anſwer, that I am not for any Affronts in what Cauſe ſoever, for I ſeldom ſee they do good; but moſt of all am I againſt Affronts to the publick Faith of the Church. The Socinians, I am informed, were ſilent ſome while upon my Paper, till others blew the Coals afreſh. It is utterly againſt my Mind, and grieves my Soul, if they do affront the eſtabliſh'd Church, and 'tis more than I know: God forbid I ſhould excuſe them for it: I would have them, and all Men, to be peaceable, meek and humble. But in caſe of ſuch Affronts, the Church, God be bleſſed, has better Ways to vindicate the Faith and her own Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, than the Fancies and new Notions of private Doctors, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult her not, but run perfectly upon their own Heads, and advance their own Principles, being buſy and intermeddling in every Controverſy that is moved. I boldly aver, leſs would be ſaid againſt the Truth, did not ſuch Perſons, appearing for it, by their pretended Defences of it, and by the haughty Stile and Manner of penning them, give new Matter to the Adverſary. Thoſe daily freſh Provocations, and the Effects of them, are what I did in part, and muſt ſtill inſiſt upon, as one main Reaſon for my <hi>Suit for Forbearance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>will the World think that we are all of one Mind becauſe there is</hi>
               <note place="margin">§. 22.</note> 
               <hi>diſputing but on one ſide? Then they will think us all Socinians,</hi> &amp;c. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, Let us go on in Conformity to our Church-Doctrine, and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in an holy, humble, peaceable, obliging Converſation, and touching our Judgment in Doctrinals, the World will ſooner credit our Practice, and the Articles, (or Confeſſion) the Liturgy, Catechiſm, Homilies, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, and ſuch publick Acts of our Church, than twenty little Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dications of private Doctors. And as for the Pamphlets of ſome obſcure and anonymous Perſons, I ſtill ſay again, 'tis Oppoſition, for the main, that gives them Celebrity and Life. Hereſies have from Age to Age ſtill been tranſmitted to Poſterity, by ſundry Conſutations they have received. Had we had only the Holy Scripture and our Creed, with a few practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and devotional Books delivered down to us, we ſhould have been united in a plain Faith, in Charity and Holineſs built thereupon; and the very Names, as well as the Errors of the antient Hereticks, had been long ſince buried and unknown: Whereas every Age now, by what has been writ againſt Hereſies, know how to refine and new vamp them. What fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are in my poor Opinion the meeteſt Ways to provide againſt <hi>Socinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm</hi> as well as all the other—<hi>iſms</hi> or diſſenting Parties, I ſhall ſpeak per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps anon.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:51847:28"/>
            <p>In the mean time I muſt not let paſs a very ſignal Favour of Mr. Dean's, to render me, if he could, obnoxious to the Government, in making me privy to a <hi>very dangerous Secret, or great Truth fit for all Governments to</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 23.</note> 
               <hi>conſider,</hi> (truly their Majeſties Chaplain in ordinary ought to admoniſh the Government of their Overſights) a Truth, he ſays, which I <hi>have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warily confeſs'd,</hi> (and he is in the right of it, for I thought not of it; nay I neither before knew, nor do I now believe it to be generally a Truth) that <hi>every Schiſm in the Church is a new Party and Faction in the State, which are always troubleſom to Government when it wants their Help.</hi> This may be true of every vaſt or multitudinous Schiſm, when the Number infected come to bear ſome conſiderable Proportion, as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps of a fifth or ſixth Part to the whole Nation; but not of every Party which ſome call a Schiſm, ſurely as to <hi>that little contemptible Party that</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 19.</note> 
               <hi>only think themſelves conſiderable;</hi> as to that <hi>ſo inconſiderable, abhorred Party, when they ſtand by themſelves, that all Parties who own any Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 23.</note> 
               <hi>will join Counſels, and Hands, and Hearts, to renounce them,</hi> (as he had not above nine Lines before drawn the Character of the Socinian:) <hi>The Help of theſe</hi> ſurely can neither be <hi>wanted</hi> by the Government, nor they ever be <hi>troubleſome to it.</hi> If therefore any Words of mine import any ſuch thing, (which I profeſs I cannot ſee they do) I confeſs it was ſaid <hi>very unawares,</hi> nay contrary to my Intention. Beſides, I ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have expected this Inſinuation <hi>from Mr. Dean againſt the Socinians of</hi> all Parties in the World: For he being a Perſon ſo deeply engaged againſt them, cannot be eſteemed ſo little read or vers'd in their Hereſy, as to be ignorant, that amongſt their Errors of Note, this is one, <hi>That it is not lawful for any Chriſtian Man to exerciſe even the Civil Power of the Sword;</hi> that Chriſtians are to leave this Matter to the World, and that there never will be wanting worldly Men enough, <hi>Children of this Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> who will be ambitious enough of Power and Government, and who are fitter for it, and much better Managers of it than are or would be the <hi>Children of the Light:</hi> that therefore they are to be ſubject to <hi>the Power that is,</hi> and not to attempt the poſſeſſing themſelves of Rule. This Party therefore of all other, ought not to fall under the Jealouſy of the Government: Nor ſhould Mr. Dean, of all Men, being he ſo well knows this to be againſt their Principles, have accuſed them of it.</p>
            <p>And now paſſing by ſome poor trifling Reflections which he makes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, (touching my Intimacy with Socinians, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) without regarding whether that which he infers follow from the Premiſſes he takes, and which moſtly make up his <hi>24th</hi> Page, I come to ſpeak more fully my meaning in a Paſſage of more Weight, which he is unwilling to underſtand. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as all Men know, Oppoſition commonly makes thoſe whom we
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:51847:28"/> cannot quiet, only more eager and troubleſom, I had perſwaded a Neglect of the Socinian Papers <hi>till fit Time and Place,</hi> as really believing that if they received no new Matter to provoke them to write, they would ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe. Now Mr. Dean will have the <hi>Time he wrote in to be a fit Time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 23</note> (I ſuppoſe becauſe he had leiſure and a Mind to give the World ſome new Specimen of his Skill in Diſpute, and for other Reaſons that the World talk of) and <hi>what I mean by fit Place he knows not.</hi> But that he may be ſoon let into the whole meaning, as well as Reaſonableneſs of my Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals, I will tell him, that the great St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> would not undertake writing againſt the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> till choſen and deputed thereto by two Councils, in both which he ſat; one of <hi>Carthage,</hi> the other of <hi>Milevis,</hi> both held according to <hi>Baronius,</hi> in the Year CCCCXVI. From conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of which memorable Precedent, I concluded the <hi>fitteſt Time and Place</hi> for the taking notice of, and confuting heretical Doctrines, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in ſuch tender Points as that of the Holy Trinity, to be (what is near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt a Council amongſt us, namely) <hi>a full Houſe of Convocation;</hi> and the fitteſt Perſons to do this, <hi>a Committee choſen by that great and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Aſſembly;</hi> and the <hi>Work</hi> afterwards to be <hi>reviſed and approved by</hi> the ſaid Aſſembly. How far it might be expedient to call or admit the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries to publick Diſputation at ſuch Time and Place, I take not upon me to conſider. But according to this Method, we ſhould be ſure to have no novel Hypotheſes or Definitions put upon us, or ſtarted: On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, all Points would be maturely ſtated with Moderation and Caution, even Expreſſions themſelves weighed, the Truth ſolidly confirmed, Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror confuted and cenſured. So that in fine, all Sons of the Church would and muſt be concluded, and by this Means a due End would be put to theſe Controverſies. This was what I meant by ſaying, <q>At fit Time and Place let that be done which ſhall be judged moſt Chriſtian and moſt wholeſorn.</q> And I believe a little Candour and Conſideration would eaſily have taken my Meaning. But having now thus more fully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared it, I ſhall only add as to this Matter, that I perſiſt ſtill in the ſame Opinion.</p>
            <p>So do I alſo in my Propoſal of what I termed a <hi>Negative Belief,</hi> which he again attempts to expoſe; inſtead of which Term, if any will give me a better and more ſignificant <hi>Succedaneum,</hi> I ſhall readily accept it: but as for the thing it ſelf, I judg it, as I have ſaid, moſt reaſonable and juſt. Nor do I ſee any readier Expedient towards ſuch <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> as in the preſent State of things may be adjudged <hi>poſſible,</hi> than what I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, namely, that <hi>in ſuch myſterious Points which we cannot underſtand or clear our ſelves in, we ſhall be permitted</hi> (what indeed as to the inward Act none can hinder) <hi>to ſuſpend our Judgment, and not be required to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:51847:29"/> any further Aſſent and Conſent to the Churches Determination, than that we will not contradict or teach contrary thereto:</hi> Withal, that in the mean time <hi>no Practice be impoſed upon any contrary to their Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I would have it noted here, that I <hi>neither in my Paper did,</hi> nor do I <hi>now propoſe this Temper,</hi> as a <hi>Mean to qualify</hi> Men for <hi>Church-Preferments,</hi> but <hi>only for Communion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now though Mr. Dean may judg all this unpracticable, and that it is not poſſible to bring hereby <hi>ſome Men to hold their Tongues,</hi> yet perhaps he judges of their Tongues by what he knows, and has declared of his <hi>own Pen,</hi> that he will, in a <hi>certain Controverſy, never lay it down while he can hold it in his Hand.</hi> However I find ſome in Print to be of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Mind in this Point, even touching himſelf; and to believe, that if the Bookſellers would but hold their Hands in giving him ſo much a Sheet for his Copies, he would ſoon ceaſe troubling the World with Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy of any kind.</p>
            <p>But he adds, that <hi>I remembred not, when I made this Propoſal, what I</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 26.</note> 
               <hi>had ſaid of ſome Mens Zeal, and eternal Diſputing.</hi> I did remember, good Sir, what I had ſaid and ſpoke conſiſtently with it, which is more than ſome People always do; but you miſrepreſent what I ſaid according to your uſual Fidelity: My Words were, <q>An Anſwer would only breed a Reply, that a Rejoinder, that a Triplication, and ſo <hi>in infini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</hi>
               </q> But I did not ſay there would be a Reply, if there were no An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; nor a Triplication, if no Rejoinder; nor any eternal Diſputing, if (as I deſired) ſome Writers would deſiſt, neglect their Adverſaries, or forbear inſolently to exaſperate them.</p>
            <p>Now as to the Queſtions he asks me, I will take the Liberty to imitate<note place="margin">§. 24.</note> my Saviour, and anſwer one captious Queſtion with another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> He asks, Whether I will allow them, whom I grant to be in Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the Faith of the Trinity and Incarnation, to keep Poſſeſſion of it, to teach, explain and confirm it to their People? And I will ask him, Whether he never ſaw certain <hi>Royal Injunctions</hi> aſſigning fit Subjects for Sermons? Some in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Time, and others ſince, ordinarily tranſmitted to the Clergy by the Primate of the Kingdom, that <hi>Preachers ſhall in their Sermons purely and ſincerely declare unto their Hearers the Word of God, and in the ſame exhort them to good Works; to Works of Faith, as Mercy and Charity;</hi>—that they ſhall forbear difficult and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſial Points. Now although this of the Trinity be not, that I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, mentioned, yet I am ſure there is the ſame Reaſon of it, as of thoſe that are: And, by his Favour, I will ask him further, whether it be not fit to obey ſuch Injunctions? or whether the <hi>Doctrine of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> be not as difficult and remote from the common Peoples Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:51847:29"/> as is the <hi>Doctrine of Predeſtination and God's Decrees?</hi> Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this, I yield; In the Name of God, let Miniſters at due Seaſon, as on <hi>Trinity-Sunday,</hi> and the <hi>Feaſt of the Nativity of our Lord,</hi> preach to their People, as they judg it moſt edifying, the Doctrines of the <hi>Trinity and Incarnation;</hi> only let them do it <hi>plainly, eaſily, purely and ſincerely,</hi> according to Scripture, and not with Innovations of their own.</p>
            <p>His <hi>2d</hi> Particular I expected would have been a Queſtion alſo, as he promiſed; but he had either forgot his Promiſe, or changed his Mind, and ſo he puts the Caſe categorically thus: <hi>I hope,</hi> ſays Mr. Dean, <hi>he</hi> [that is, the melancholy Stander-by] <hi>does not propoſe this Negative Belief, as he calls it, as a Term of Communion; that though we know them to deny the Trinity and Incarnation, yet if they will agree not publickly to oppoſe and contradict this Faith, we ſhall receive them to our Communion.</hi> Now though he has not propoſed this in form of a Queſtion, yet I will anſwer it with a very ſhort one; <hi>Why not?</hi> At leaſt as far forth as we know (that is, as they profeſs) they can in Conſcience join with us: Nay, has not Mr. Dean done it? or would he not in the Caſe I ſhall now put? namely, Suppoſe him or me to be in the Pulpit, beginning our Prayer before Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, either, as ſome do, with the Collect, <hi>Prevent us, O Lord,</hi> &amp;c. or with ſome Form or Conceptions of our own, (in which notwithſtanding is nothing of Controverſy intermix'd) and to ſubjoin to our own Prayer that of our Lord's. Suppoſe in like manner after Sermon we ſhould uſe either that Collect, <hi>Grant we beſeech thee,</hi> &amp;c. or ſome Prayer of our own, and then give the Bleſſing to the whole Congregation promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly. Admit now, that in the Beginning of our very firſt Prayer we ſhould have ſeen a Perſon whom we know to be a good Liver, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing the common Chriſtianity, (in other Points) but ſo unhappy, as that he cannot be convinced of the Doctrine of three Perſons in the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, as it is ordinarily taught, or of the Incarnation of the ſecond Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, though he does from his Heart believe and confeſs Jeſus Chriſt to be the Son of God, and hold all other the Articles of the Apoſtles Creed; would or ſhould, either Mr. Dean or I, in ſuch caſe ſtop as ſoon as we ſaw that Perſon in the Congregation, and bid him go out, refuſing he ſhould join with us in thoſe Prayers, or receive his Share in that Bleſſing, to both which he heartily ſays <hi>Amen?</hi> that is, Shall I not admit him to Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion as far as I know he does conſent and deſire to communicate with me and other Orthodox Chriſtian People? I know the Story of St. <hi>John</hi> the Evangeliſt and <hi>Cerinthus,</hi> but <hi>Cerinthus</hi> was anotherguiſe Heretick than ſuch Perſon as in the Character ſuppoſed.</p>
            <p>I might animadvert as I paſs, that (in <hi>pag.</hi> 27.) Mr. Dean imputes ſundry Points very iniquitouſly ſtated to the Socinians, which yet they
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:51847:30"/> hold not as he ſtates them. I am not concerned to defend the Socinian Errors; but as I <hi>love Truth and Peace,</hi> I cannot forbear obſerving, that he here wrongs them. Firſt, as to what he ſpeaks of the <hi>Object of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Worſhip;</hi> if he, as ſome in the World, had had perſonal dealing with the Generality of his Pariſhioners, as to Matters of Conſcience, he would ſay, that the <hi>Ignorance of many Church-People,</hi> and ſo the Errors of their Conceptions, both touching God, and touching the three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the Godhead, much <hi>more alter</hi> (as to them) <hi>the Object of the Chriſtian Worſhip,</hi> than do the <hi>Errors</hi> of the <hi>Socinians.</hi> Again, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he ſays, <hi>the Socinians deny that the Son of God offered himſelf a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to expiate our Sins:</hi> I do ſo far depend upon my Memory, as to avow they affirm our Lord Jeſus to have been <hi>Victimam verè expiatoriam,</hi> a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice truly expiatory; they are the Words of the Author of the <hi>ſhort Expoſition of the Apoſtles Creed,</hi> whether <hi>Slicktingius</hi> (as I rather think) or <hi>Crellius,</hi> I cannot now tell, having not ſeen my Book divers Years. Nor do they <hi>deny the Love of God to Mankind in giving his only Son to be our Prophet and Saviour,</hi> and Redeemer too; nor <hi>his Interceſſion as their High Prieſt in virtue of his Blood, ſhed as an Atonement for our Sins.</hi> They differ from us perhaps in explaining the Nature of Expiation and Satisfaction; but both an Expiation and a Satisfaction they allow. Some Men write againſt them without underſtanding them. But I forbear fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther intermeddling in theſe kinds of Injuries, though, to uſe Mr. Dean's Words, <hi>it were eaſy to enlarge on this Argument:</hi> I am not writing a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence<note place="margin">Pag. 28.</note> of the Socinians, only I am vindicating a peaceable Deſign in a Man that is none, but loves Godlineſs, Vertue and good Works, where-ever he meets with them: and who may chance ſooner to perſwade many So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians to be ſilent, by making it apparent he would not wrong them, (however odious others make them by unjuſt Charges) than will thoſe be able who try their Skill, and ſtrain their Veracity in fierce and haughty Diſputes againſt them. Men <hi>may have Wit enough,</hi> if they have Juſtice done them, <hi>to underſtand when it is fit to be quiet,</hi> who will ſcarce ſit down ſilent under publick Calumnies.</p>
            <p>In the next Place Mr. Dean falls upon me for ſaying, <hi>very much is done</hi>
               <note place="margin">§. 25.</note> [namely, for preſent Union] <hi>by the late Act in Favour of Diſſenters,</hi> and taxes me here again according to his wonted Civility, <hi>with pretending to give Account of Acts of Parliament, as I do of other Books, without ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them.</hi> A ſtrange kind of Incredulity touching my Reading has poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs'd this Gentleman: Muſt I not be believed to have read Books, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept I produce Witneſſes that heard or ſaw me read them? I can produce Witneſſes now in <hi>London,</hi> where I bought this Act, and where I bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed his Book of the Trinity, before I wrote touching either. And I
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:51847:30"/> muſt take the Liberty to ſay, that as I read both, ſo it appears not in the leaſt by any thing I have writ, that I was ignorant in either.</p>
            <p>But <hi>no Diſſenters have any Benefit by that Act who do not renounce Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianiſm.</hi> By your good Favour, Sir, this is too roundly and boldly ſaid: Is there no Favour to Diſſenters but that of allowing them publick Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies? What do you think of a <hi>tacit Connivance,</hi> if not at their <hi>ſtay at home,</hi> yet allowing them <hi>quietly to come to our Congregations,</hi> and joining therewith as far as they are able? What of a kind of <hi>vetuit inquiri?</hi> I declare I would not conſent that the Socinians ſhould have the Liberty ſome other N. Cs. have, to teach publickly all their Opinions in ſeparate Congregations; for I would have moſt, or all of the Controverſies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them and us ſilenced; and therefore I ſaid, <hi>very much, if not full enough, was done already in their Favour; and that the Authority which paſſed that Act, could relax more if neceſſary.</hi> And I hope that Authority, namely King and Parliament, will in time relax what more is neceſſary for ſuch an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> as is <hi>poſſible.</hi> In the mean while, neither did I, nor had I the occaſion which is now given me, to ſpeak what (God be bleſſed) was before relaxed by other Acts, perhaps not with any great liking of ſome Men; notwithſtanding I had thoſe Relaxations, even then, in mine Eye; and I can truly ſay, they came into the Conſideration which moved me to ſay what I did on this Point: There was ſuch a thing as a Writ <hi>de Haeretico comburendo,</hi> which I have heard ſome Perſons, learned in the Law, ſay, did <hi>lie even at Common Law;</hi> and I am ſure the <hi>Canoniſts</hi> tell us, prevailed <hi>by Cuſtom throughout Chriſtendom:</hi> And we know one <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael Servetus,</hi> in whoſe Writings <hi>Grotius</hi> could never find what ſome charged upon him, was burnt even at <hi>Geneva</hi> (by no Papiſts) in the prevailing Virtue of that Cuſtom, I will not ſpeak on what Pretences. This Writ is now, as I have heard, taken away (and ſo it may be hoped the Cuſtom here in a fair way to be aboliſhed) by expreſs Statute; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by poſſibly ſome Men may think a <hi>very conſiderable Benefit,</hi> no leſs than <hi>Security of Lives and Eſtates,</hi> may <hi>redound to them,</hi> in caſe ſome ſuch of their Friends as Mr. Dean were in the Place they affect.</p>
            <p>As to thoſe odious Terms with which he hath interlaced his next Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph [<hi>His beloved Socinians—We may ſee what a hearty good Will he has to the Cauſe. This is ſuch a ſcandalous Repreſentation of the Biſhops of</hi> England, <hi>which in due time</hi> (when the Dean of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s comes to be one of them) <hi>they may reſent</hi>] Theſe are more of the Favours, for his Liberality, wherein I may come to be beholden to him in that Day, when the <hi>Reproaches</hi> and Calumnies which Men have ſuſtained <hi>for the ſake of Chriſt,</hi> or (which is much like the ſame) <hi>for Peace amongſt Chriſtian People,</hi> with a Deſign of <hi>Holineſs,</hi> ſhall add to the Weight of their Glory.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:51847:31"/>
            <p>But I muſt after another ſort anſwer to that heavy Charge which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows,<note place="margin">§. 26. <hi>Pag. 29.</hi>
               </note> of <hi>my tempting the Biſhops to diſpute the Bounds of their Authority;</hi> and that <hi>through my Ignorance both of ancient and later Hiſtories or Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice.</hi> The thing I had ſaid was this, <q>That to the authorizing every Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration which ſhould be made in our Liturgy or Canons, I did not judg the Concurrence of ſuch a lower Houſe of Convocation as is now cuſtomary, to be neceſſary: And that if this Courſe had been obſerved in K. <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth's time, we had had no reformed Liturgy, perhaps no Reformation at all. <hi>And for Proof</hi> that the Synods for ſuch Affairs were of old made up of Biſhops and fewer Doctors, I had appealed to the Practice of the Primitive and truly Catholick Church.</q> This is in Mr. Dean's Language, <hi>without any Provocation, a ſetting up the Authority of Biſhops againſt the lower Houſe, a threatning unruly Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and that through my underſtanding no better the Practice of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church, than I do K.</hi> Edward <hi>the VIth's Reformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To draw my Anſwer into as ſhort a Compaſs as I can, (waving to that Purpoſe his uſual Exaggerations as apparently undue; waving alſo the known Diminutions of Epiſcopal Power, the Source and Original there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of due to <hi>Rome</hi> and Sectaries, and the Miſchief which Religion and the Church ſuſtain thereby) I will ſpeak only to what I perceive pinches him moſt, the <hi>Reformation firſt made of our Liturgy and publick Worſhip in King</hi> Edward <hi>the IVth's Days,</hi> which though I did not ſay or ſuppoſe to be made by the Body of the Biſhops in oppoſition to the Presbyters, as he falſly charges upon me, (for as I have no ſuch Word, ſo I better underſtand the Hiſtory) yet I did, and I do ſay it <hi>was made without a lower Houſe of Convocation;</hi> and by whom, I ſhall ſpeak particularly enough before I have done.</p>
            <p>Now the Evidence on which I ground all, I ſay, is ſuch publick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains and Hiſtories of thoſe Days and Affairs as are commonly to be had; ſuch are <hi>King</hi> Edward's <hi>Injunctions, Order of Communion-Service,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Firſt printed</hi> A. D. 1547.</note> [collected, and with other things reprinted, ſoon upon his late Majeſty K. <hi>Charles</hi> II. his happy Reſtoration, with a Preface of Dr. <hi>Sparrow</hi>'s to the Collection; but the Collection not made by Dr. <hi>Sparrow</hi> himſelf, as he himſelf when Biſhop of <hi>Exeter</hi> told me, (for had he had the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruling it, he ſaid he would have put in more Materials) but by ſuch who conſulted their own preſent Profit] ſuch are too, Fox'<hi>s Acts and Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> Part 2. Book 9. <hi>Sir</hi> John Hayward'<hi>s Life and Reign of K.</hi> Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>the Sixth; Dr.</hi> Heylin'<hi>s Hiſtory of the Reformation;</hi> and <hi>Dr.</hi> Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net'<hi>s</hi> (now Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi>) more lately. If Mr. Dean has had any Acceſs to any Archives or more authentick Records than thoſe by which theſe Hiſtorians were guided, he would have done well to have publiſhed
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:51847:31"/> them. In the mean while I, with others, am content in this Matter to admit for Truth what <hi>theſe concurrently</hi> have delivered.</p>
            <p>To our Point then: That bleſſed Prince K. <hi>Edward</hi> VI. began his Reign <hi>January</hi> 28, 1546 / 7; and if we will take together all that was done towards the Reformation of Religion, in the firſt nine Months of his Reign, Sir <hi>John Hayward,</hi> of whoſe Veracity I find no Reaſon to doubt, has thus drawn up the Sum; <q>Soon after the Beginning of the young<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Life and Reign of</hi> Edw. VI. <hi>pag. 45, 46.</hi>
                  </note> King's Reign <hi>certain Injunctions</hi> were ſet forth for <hi>removing Images</hi> out of Churches, which had been highly not only eſteemed but honoured before, and for <hi>aboliſhing</hi> or <hi>altering ſome other antient Obſervations</hi> in the Church. Hereupon <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> were diſpatched into all Parts of the Realm to ſee thoſe <hi>Injunctions to be executed;</hi> with thoſe <hi>divers Preachers</hi> were ſent, furniſhed with <hi>Inſtructions</hi> to perſwade the People <hi>from praying to Saints,</hi> or <hi>for the Dead,</hi> from <hi>adoring Images,</hi> from <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Beads, Aſhes</hi> and <hi>Proceſſions,</hi> from <hi>Maſs, Dirges, praying in unknown Languages,</hi> and from <hi>ſome other like things,</hi> whereunto a long Cuſtom had wrought a Religious Obſervation; and for defect of Preachers, <hi>Homilies were appointed to be publickly read in Churches,</hi> aiming to the very ſame End.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Some other offering to maintain theſe Ceremonies, were either pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed or forced to recant: <hi>Edmond Boner</hi> Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> was <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted Priſoner to the Fleet,</hi> for refuſing to receive theſe Injunctions; <hi>Stephen Gardiner</hi> was likewiſe committed <hi>firſt to the Fleet,</hi> afterwards <hi>to the Tower,</hi> for that he had openly preached that it were well theſe Changes in Religion ſhould be ſtayed, until the King were of Years to govern by himſelf. This the People apprehending worſe than it was either ſpoken or meant, a Queſtion began to be raiſed among them, whether during the King's Minority ſuch Alterations might lawfully be made or no. For the like Cauſes <hi>Tonſtal</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Dureſm,</hi> and <hi>Heath</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> were in like ſort <hi>committed to Priſon.</hi> All theſe being then, and ſtill continuing famous for Learning and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, were diſpoſſeſſed of their Biſhopricks, but no Man was touched in Life.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Hereupon a Parliament was held in the firſt Year of the King. Thus far Sir <hi>John,</hi> a learned and religious Knight, Doctor of Law, and a wiſe and wary Hiſtorian.</q> This Parliament was ſummoned to meet <hi>Nov.</hi> 4. 1547. when now had paſſed but nine Months and ſome odd Days of this King's Reign. And all this while could there be <hi>no Convocation,</hi> becauſe <hi>no Parliament.</hi> Therefore all this, which was a conſiderable Advance to the Reformation, was done without the Conſent of a lower Houſe of Convocation; for there was none either higher or lower called.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:51847:32"/>
            <p>But it may be ſaid, Sir <hi>John</hi> writes liker a Civil than Eccleſiaſtical Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian, putting things of the ſame Nature together, but not punctually concerning himſelf as to their reſpective Date. We will take therefore next the eldeſt of the Eccleſiaſtic Hiſtorians, which report the Tranſactions of this Reign, namely <hi>Fox;</hi> and from him we have theſe Steps of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding in the Reformation.</p>
            <p>Firſt, ſaith he, <q>By the ſingle Authority of King and Council was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed <hi>a general Viſitation</hi> by certain learned, diſcreet and worſhipful Perſonages, his Commiſſioners in that Behalf, divided into ſeveral Companies, aſſigned to the ſeveral Dioceſſes, appointing to every Company one or two learned Preachers, which at every Seſſion ſhould in their Preaching inſtruct the People in the true Doctrine of Chriſt. The Order for this Viſitation iſſued <hi>Sept.</hi> 1. 1547.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Secondly, That theſe Commiſſioners might be more orderly in their Buſineſs, there were delivered to them by the ſame Authority <hi>certain Injunctions</hi> and Eccleſiaſtical Orders <hi>drawn out by the King's learned Council,</hi> which they ſhould both enquire of, and alſo in his Majeſty's Behalf command to be obſerved by every Perſon to whom they did ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally appertain within their Circuits.</q> This ſaith Dr. <hi>Heylin,</hi> the King might do by his own Authority, as his Father had done, <hi>&amp;c. An.</hi> 1536.</p>
            <q>
               <p>In thoſe Injunctions, to omit Matters of leſs Moment, it is required that every Eccleſiaſtical Perſon having Cure of Souls, ſhould <hi>take down and deſtroy all ſuch Images</hi> as had heretofore been <hi>abuſed</hi> by Pilgrimage or Offerings; that they ſhould not <hi>ſuffer any Lights</hi> or other <hi>idolatrous Oblations</hi> to be made before any Image; that on every Holy-day, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no Sermon in their Church, they ſhould immediately after the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel <hi>read diſtinctly in the Pulpit the Lord's Prayer, the Belief, and the Ten Commandments, in the Engliſh Tongue.</hi> And although the Maſs was then ſtill by Law retained, yet was it enjoined, that at every High Maſs, the Sayer or Singer thereof ſhould openly and diſtinctly <hi>read the Goſpel and the Epiſtle in Engliſh</hi>—and on every Holy-day and Sunday at Mattins <hi>one Chapter of the New Teſtament in Engliſh alſo</hi>—That for avoiding Contention, Proceſſions ſhould be laid down, and the Prieſts and Clerks ſhould <hi>kneel in the midſt of the Church, and there diſtinctly ſing or read the Letany in Engliſh,</hi> ſet forth <hi>by the Authority of King</hi> Henry <hi>the VIIIth.</hi> And further, that they ſhould ſee provided and ſet up in ſome moſt convenient and open Place of every their ſeveral Churches, <hi>one great Bible in Engliſh,</hi> and <hi>one Book of the Paraphraſe of</hi> Eraſmus <hi>upon the Goſpels in Engliſh:</hi> Alſo that the People might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verently, without any Argument or Contention, read and hear the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:51847:32"/> ſame at ſuch times as they liſted. And, to mention no more of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions, <hi>Homilies ſet forth by the King's Authority</hi> were enjoined the Curates to be <hi>read every Sunday;</hi> and when the Homily was read, <hi>the Prince and Hours to be omitted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, Beſides theſe general Injunctions for the whole Eſtate of the Realm, there were alſo <hi>certain others particularly appointed for the Biſhops,</hi> only by the Commiſſioners in their Viſitations to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the ſaid Biſhops, with Charge to be inviolably kept and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved upon Pain of the King's Majeſty's Diſpleaſure. And <hi>this Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was held,</hi> and the <hi>Injunctions executed</hi> according to Order.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, During the Time, ſays <hi>Fox,</hi> that the Commiſſioners were occupied abroad in their Circuits about the ſpeedy and diligent Execution of theſe godly and zealous Orders and Decrees of the King and his Council, his Majeſty cauſed a Parliament to be ſummoned, <hi>Nov.</hi> 4. in the ſame firſt Year of his Reign, wherein all the bloody Laws in point of Religion were repealed.</p>
            </q>
            <p>And here, according to Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> comes in a <hi>Convocation,</hi> which<note place="margin">Hiſt. of Refor. <hi>Par. 2. p.</hi> 27, &amp;c</note> neither Mr. <hi>Fox,</hi> nor Sir <hi>John Hayward,</hi> nor Sir <hi>Richard Baker,</hi> nor any other Hiſtorian that I have ſeen, mentioneth: but I moſt readily admit for Truth what the reverend Perſon reports. Let us ſee then, according to this exacter Hiſtorian, what the Convocation did as to the Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or otherwiſe.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt;</hi> The lower Houſe of Convocation preſented four Petitions to the Biſhops; That according to the Statute made in the Reign of the late King, there might be Perſons impowered for reforming the <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Laws.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly;</hi> That according to the antient Cuſtom of the Nation, and the Tenor of the Biſhops Writ to the Parliament, the <hi>inferiour Clergy might be admitted again to ſit in the Houſe of Commons;</hi> or that <hi>no Acts concerning Matters of Religion might paſs without the Sight and Aſſent of the Clergy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly;</hi> That ſince <hi>divers Prelates and other Divines</hi> had been in the <hi>late King's time appointed to alter the Service of the Church,</hi> and had made ſome Progreſs in it, that this might be brought to its full Perfection.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Fourthly;</hi> That ſome <hi>Conſideration</hi> might be had <hi>for the maintenance of the Clergy</hi> the firſt Year they came into their Livings, in which they were charged with the firſt Fruits; to which they added a Deſire to know whether they <hi>might ſafely ſpeak their Minds about Religion,</hi> without the Danger of any Law.</q> Thus Dr. <hi>Burnet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the firſt of theſe Petitions, all I find done, was, that at ſome Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:51847:33"/> of time ſeveral Attempts and Proceedings paſs'd in order to it, and<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Extracted out of Dr.</hi> Burnet.</note> at length the Work was finiſh'd by divers Committees ſucceſſively, but thoſe neither of the Convocation, nor named by the Convocation: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>Cranmer</hi> was the principal Perſon; and who elſe were imployed therein, may be ſeen in Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>'s <hi>2d</hi> Part, <hi>p.</hi> 196, 197. But before it received the Royal Confirmation, the King died, and the Work fell with him, ſays my Author, As to the ſecond I do not obſerve any Notice was taken of it, either by the Biſhops then in Power, or by the Parliament. And I conjecture the Reaſon to be, for that it was known full well to the Reformers, that the <hi>Generality of the Clergy were at that time Papiſts in</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Dr.</hi> Burnet, <hi>Part 2. p. 96.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>their Hearts (which hindred the Church of many Powers and Privileges that otherwiſe might have been granted to her:</hi>) And however many of them for that time complied, yet in Q. <hi>Mary</hi>'s Days, when Popery came to be reſettled by Parliament, <hi>all of them ſave</hi> 177, if we may believe<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See his</hi> Journal, <hi>pag. 23. Part 2. p. 50.</hi>
               </note> Sir <hi>Simon D' Ewes, turned about again, or became I apiſts.</hi> As to the third, It was reſolved, ſaith Dr. <hi>Burnet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> that many Biſhops and Divines ſhould be ſent [the ſame who afterwards compiled the Liturgy, ſaith Dr. <hi>Heylin,</hi> were ſent] to <hi>Windſor,</hi> to <hi>labour in the Matter of the Communion-Service;</hi> but that required ſo much Conſideration, that they would not enter into it during a Seſſion of Parliament: However it was finiſh'd and publiſh'd with the King's Proclamation, <hi>March</hi> 8, 1547 / 8, as Dr. <hi>Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi> tells us. And for the fourth, what Anſwer was given to it doth not appear: Thus the Reverend Doctor. However moſt certain it is, that <hi>neither were theſe Biſhops and Divines named by the lower Houſe of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation,</hi> but by <hi>the King and Council,</hi> as will by and by appear; nor the <hi>Alterations by them made, ever brought before that Houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What further Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> records done by this Convocation, upon the Biſhops ſending down to the lower Houſe a <hi>Declaration concerning the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament</hi> to be received in both kinds, and <hi>the Marriage of the Clergy,</hi> (to the former of which all conſented, and to the latter moſt) I need not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port. What I have faithfully thus repreſented from him, is the Sum of that Account, which he ſays <hi>is all he could recover of that Convocation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 50.</note> And what ſhall the Man do that comes after him? Deſpairing therefore of more touching this Convocation, we will go on with <hi>Fox</hi> and others <hi>in the Proceedings of the Reformation made without them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not only the <hi>Communion was enjoyned by Act of Parliament to be mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in both kinds,</hi> to which it may be ſaid the Convocation conſented, but by the ſame Parliament <hi>ſolitary Communion of the Prieſt or private Maſſes were put down,</hi> (of which that we find the Convocation had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been conſulted, and to which that lower Houſe, for many Reaſons, would never have conſented) and the Curates required at leaſt one Day
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:51847:33"/> before the Communion to <hi>exhort all Perſons</hi> that ſhould be preſent <hi>to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare themſelves</hi> for receiving.</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Fifthly; After this moſt godly Conſent of the Parliament,</hi>
               </q> continues my Author, making no mention of a Convocation, (for that now was broke up with the Parliament) <q>
                  <hi>The King</hi> being no leſs deſirous to have<note place="margin">Fox, <hi>p. 1183.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>the Form of the Adminiſtration of the Sacrament truly reduced</hi> to the right Rule of the Scripture, and firſt Uſe of the Primitive Church, than he was to eſtabliſh the ſame by his own Regal Laws, <hi>appointed certain of the moſt grave and learned Biſhops and others of his Realm,</hi> to aſſemble together at his Caſtle at <hi>Windſor,</hi> and there to argue and intreat upon this Matter, and conclude upon, and ſet forth one perfect and uniform Order, according to the Rule and Uſe aforeſaid.</q> Here was made the (then new Engliſh) <hi>uniform Order of the Communion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Sixthly;</hi> In the mean while that theſe learned Perſons were thus oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied about their Conferences, <hi>the Lord Protector and the reſt of the King's Council</hi> farther remembring that the time of the Year approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, wherein were practiſed many ſuperſtitious Abuſes and blaſphemous Ceremonies againſt the Glory of God and Truth of his Word, and determining the utter aboliſhing thereof, <hi>directed their Letters unto the Godly and Reverend Father</hi> Thomas Cranmer, Archbiſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> requiring him, that upon the Receipt thereof he ſhould will eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Biſhop within his Province forthwith to give in Charge to all the Curates of their Dioceſſes, that <hi>neither Candles</hi> ſhould be any more born upon <hi>Candlemas</hi>-day; neither yet <hi>Aſhes uſed in Lent,</hi> nor <hi>Palms upon Palm-Sunday;</hi> which was done accordingly.</q> And one of the Letters may be ſeen in my Author, expreſly ſaying, All this was done by my Lord Protector's Grace, with the Advice of other the King's Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's moſt honourable Council, dated <hi>Jan.</hi> 28, 1547 / 8; at which time the King had reigned one Year compleat.</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Seventhly;</hi> Contention and Strife ariſing amongſt the common Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in divers Places of the Realm about Images, what of theſe had been idolatrouſly abuſed, and what not; and conſequently what ſhould be pulled down and deſtroyed, what left; <hi>the Lords of the Council by one Advice</hi> thinking it beſt (of good Experience) for the avoiding all Diſcord and Tumult, that <hi>all manner of Images ſhould be clean taken out of Churches,</hi> and none ſuffered to remain, did thereupon again <hi>write their Letters unto the Archbiſhop of</hi> Canterbury to that Effect.</q> The Copy of the Letters bearing Date <hi>Feb.</hi> 11, 1547 / 8, with <hi>Boner</hi>'s Letters in Obedience to the Archbiſhop's Mandate thereupon, may be ſeen at large in <hi>Fox.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:51847:34"/>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Eighthly;</hi> By this time the uniform Order for the Communion in Engliſh being finiſhed, <hi>Letters miſſive from the Council</hi> are iſſued forth to the Biſhops of the Realm concerning the Communion to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred according to the Tenour of the ſaid Book. Which Letters alſo may be read in the ſame Author, <hi>p.</hi> 1184. bearing Date at <hi>Weſtminſter, March</hi> 13, 1548.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Ninthly;</hi> Notwithſtanding all theſe Orders (to proceed) through the perverſe Obſtinacy and diſſembling Frowardneſs of many of the Prieſts, [who therefore never conſented hereto in Convocation] there ariſing a marvellous Schiſm and Variety of Faſhions in celebrating the Common Service and Adminiſtration of the Sacraments, and other Rites and Ceremonies of the Church: <hi>the King's Council</hi> having good Intelligence hereof, did <hi>by their prudent Advices again appoint the Archbiſhop of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>with certain of the beſt learned and diſcreet Biſhops, and other learned Men,</hi> to draw and make one convenient and meet Order, Rite and Faſhion of Common-Prayer and Adminiſtration of the Sacrament, to be had and uſed within the Realm; which was accordingly done, and the Book (which was the firſt of the two in his Reign) was by the King exhibited to the Lords and Commons aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in Parliament about <hi>Nov.</hi> 4, 1548. in the ſecond Year of his Reign, in which Parliament it paſs'd with the Aſſent of the ſaid Lords and Commons.</q> But that it ever came before the Convocation, cannot be proved. When even eight Biſhops in the Houſe of Lords proteſted againſt it, no one can believe that it would then have paſs'd a Convocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and therefore no doubt it was never brought before them.</p>
            <p>And thus proceeded the two firſt Years of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth his Reformation, as far as I can collect from my afore-mentioned Authors; which two Years broke the Ice, and made way for perfecter Work: For by theſe Proceedings the Eyes of the Clergy, no leſs than of the People, (who had both need enough) began to be opened; many of both ſorts got a Taſte of the Truth, and took a Reliſh of the Reformation, which by the Vigilance of the Government, and indefatigable Diligence of the Reformers, but chiefly by the prevailing and victorious Power of the Truth, and the Influence of God's Spirit, daily grew and advanced; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that a happy Forwardneſs towards a Settlement preſented it ſelf in the ſucceeding Part of this Reign. But I may truly ſay, Had not the Reformers taken Time by the Forelock, and they not begun with the Dawn of the Day: Had the King, Council, and the immortal Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop ſtaid for ſuch a Convocation which would have approved their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, in all likelihood we had had little, or, as I affirmed, no Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation at all in King <hi>Edward</hi>'s, and God only knows whether in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:51847:34"/> following Reign. For how the next of all might have ſtrengthned Popery, (as Bones broke, and once well knit again, are, they ſay, the ſtronger in that Part) we are not able to gueſs. Sure it is, could the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Clergy in the Beginning have cruſhed the Deſigns of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, they would have done it, and by many ſad Inſtances ſhewed their good Will. Wherefore as to the later Years of King <hi>Edward,</hi> and the Corrections and Additions made to the Liturgy near towards the End of his Reign, I am not concern'd to ſpeak: Only (<hi>ex abundanti</hi>) I will<note place="margin">Part 2. p. 169.</note> add, it appears by Dr. <hi>Burnet, the making theſe was the Work of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers, not of the Convocation.</hi> And <q>it is ſuppoſed, ſaith Dr. <hi>Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hiſt. Reform. Anno 1552. <hi>pag. 126.</hi>
                  </note> the Convocation durſt not canvaſs or alter what was before ſettled by the King's Authority and Act of Parliament.</q> Indeed all Men know, that ever ſince the Submiſſion of the Clergy in <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>VIIIth</hi>'s Time, the Convocation hath been cut off from meddling with the State of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, except as they are authorized by the King. And had there been any ſuch Authority given, no doubt we ſhould have found the Footſteps thereof. I do not think it needful to ſpeak more largely on this Point: What I have ſaid will ſufficiently evince I did not ſpeak without Book in what I hinted: If any one elſe uſe to do ſo, let him look to it.</p>
            <p>After this Endeavour to expoſe my Ignorance, Mr. Dean intimates his<note place="margin">§. 27.</note> Regret, that I had not made <hi>my compaſſionate Suit</hi> in a ſeverer Age than this the Reign of our merciful and gracious Princes: for which Kindneſs of his I only return my Prayers, that he may never feel the Severity of ſuch Hands into which he could be content others ſhould have faln. And then he proceeds to tell the World, I conclude <hi>with a heavy Charge upon himſelf and Dr.</hi> Wallis, (a greater Perſon would have ſaid, <hi>Dr.</hi> Wallis <hi>and himſelf</hi>) that <hi>they have receded from the Doctrine taught even in our own Church about the Holy Trinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The whole of this is not true: I never charged Dr. <hi>Wallis</hi> with reced<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Doctrine taught in our Church, but rather expreſly alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Words, <hi>We mean by Perſons</hi> [in divinis] <hi>no more but ſomewhat analogous to Perſons;</hi> I ſaid, <hi>this has been ever held by all learned Trinita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians.</hi> All I mentioned which troubled me, as to the Doctor's explaining of the Trinity, was an indecent Expreſſion, of which I have no mind to ſpeak more.</p>
            <p>But as to Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> I did produce <hi>not broken Paſſages,</hi> as Mr. Dean ſtiles them, but his intire Definition or Deſcription of a Perſon <hi>in divinis,</hi> which he gives in his <hi>Vindication of the Trinity;</hi> and as I have ſaid, the Sum of his Hypotheſis in his very own Words, which I read in and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed from his Book: And I do now expreſly avow, though I did not then do it ſo directly, that he <hi>has receded herein from the Doctrine for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:51847:35"/> taught, not only in our Church, but in the whole Chriſtian World in this Point.</hi> And I think I have already made it out, as far as is conſiſtent with the Brevity I here deſign. But whereas he ſays, <hi>that that very Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 30.</note> 
               <hi>which I give of the Trinity out of Mr.</hi> Hooker'<hi>s Book, is owned and particularly explained by his Hypotheſis:</hi> I muſt acknowledg he has indeed owned it in his Book, but in the ſame contradicted it, both in expreſs Terms, and by his Hypotheſis. And I add, 'tis impoſſible by his Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis to explain it. He contradicts it in expreſs Terms. <hi>One Subſtance and three Properties</hi> was Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi>'s Language (and whence taken I have ſhewn.) <hi>Three real ſubſtantial Beings,</hi> (which if it ſignifies not<note place="margin">Vind. <hi>pag. 47. Pag. 83.</hi>
               </note> three Subſtances, I cannot tell what it ſignifies) and three proper diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Characters (had it not been for Affectation of Novelty he might as well have ſaid three Properties) are Mr. Dean's Terms. And theſe I take to be Contradictions. For one Subſtance and three Subſtances, that is three Subſtances and not three, (becauſe only one Subſtance with three Properties) is a Contradiction, if any in the World.</p>
            <p>His Hypotheſis contradicts, that is, deſtroys it: For his Definition or Account what we are to mean by a Perſon in the Holy Trinity, is part of his Hypotheſis: But that makes the three Perſons <hi>three real ſubſtantial Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vind. <hi>p.</hi> 47, 48, 49, 50, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>three diſtinct infinite Minds, three uncreated Spirits,</hi> (that is, imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial Subſtances) <hi>three intelligent Beings, having each <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, Will, and Power of Action.</hi> Now this, as before made out, is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictious to the Doctrine brought by Mr. <hi>Hooker.</hi> And becauſe his Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis in the very firſt fundamental Point of it, namely, the Definition he gives of a Perſon, contradicts the former Explication of the Trinity, therefore 'tis impoſſible to explain that by his.</p>
            <p>However, we will take the other Part of his Hypotheſis, and try whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we can find therewith any more Conſiſtency. As he ſuppoſes theſe three uncreated Spirits to be <hi>diſtinct by Self-conſciouſneſs,</hi> ſo to <hi>be one (numerically one) Eſſence, or one God by mutual Conſciouſneſs.</hi> But by the former Part of his Hypotheſis, <hi>each Perſon had</hi> (and to uſe his Words, <hi>knew and felt himſelf to have) an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, Will, and Power of Action of his own.</hi> Now though the Suppoſal of <hi>mutual Conſciouſneſs</hi> may in ſome meaſure <hi>explain</hi> how each thereby may have or be <hi>poſſeſs'd of one anothers Knowledg or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding;</hi> yet that any can have or be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs'd of another's <hi>Will,</hi> by being conſcious to him what his Will is, much leſs ſhould have the Power of another, becauſe he knows as well as he what he can do, is in my Apprehenſion impoſſible: For it makes Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, Will and Power, to be the ſame thing. And it is plain, <hi>mutual Conſciouſneſs,</hi> in Propriety of Speech, <hi>implies only mutual Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg.</hi> I may know another's Will, yet not be able to bring mine to it:
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:51847:35"/> I may know what another is able to do, yet not arrive at his Power. Much more might be ſaid to ſhew the Inſufficiency of mutual Conſciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for ſalving the Unity of three ſuch Perſons as he has ſuppoſed in one Nature, any otherwiſe than as three Individuals are united in one ſpecial Nature, which will not ſerve his turn; but I had rather make an end.</p>
            <p>Before he concludes he muſt clothe me, as he has been uſed to do others,<note place="margin">§. 28.</note> and as the Heathen did the Primitive Chriſtians, that Beaſts might ſooner ſeize them; or as the Inquiſitors do Hereticks before their Execution, in ſome monſtrous Shape; that the World, at leaſt the Church, may abhor me. Accordingly in an inſulting Mood, as thinking himſelf to have run me down, he puts the Queſtion, <hi>And can any Man tell what Opinion this</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 30.</note> melancholy Stander-by <hi>has of the Doctrine of the Trinity and Incarnation?</hi> And he anſwers it himſelf, that <hi>I dare not ſpeak out, but I give very broad Signs what I would be at.</hi> But can any Man tell how the <hi>Doctrine of the Incarnation</hi> comes in here? My Paper had not ſo much as named it. On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we muſt know the Doctor had writ on it, and he could not give me Load enough, except he poſſeſs the World, that I diſſent from him in a Doctrine wherein perhaps he is more Orthodox, as well as in that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he is Heterodox. I ſaid, <hi>perhaps</hi> he is more Orthodox in the Doctrine of the Incarnation: but admitting the neceſſary and immediate Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of one Branch of his Hypotheſis, he is not ſo: For if <hi>Self-conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs alone diſtinguiſh one Mind,</hi> whether finite or infinite, from another, then inaſmuch as all muſt allow there is no more eſſential Property of the rational Soul, than to be conſcious to it ſelf, it will follow, that <hi>there are two Perſons in Chriſt, (viz.</hi>) the ſecond Perſon of the Godhead, and the Man Chriſt Jeſus; which I think is <hi>Neſtorianiſm:</hi> Elſe he muſt deny the Son of God did take a rational Soul, or became truly Man; <hi>utrum ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum?</hi> But foraſmuch as this is only a Conſectary of his Doctrine, and not expreſly delivered by him, I affix it not to him. However I muſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, he has done me wrong here, fliely and beyond the preſent Cue, to put the World upon a Jealouſy of my Orthodoxy in Point of the Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and for a Farewell, having by corrupting, diſmembring and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placing my Words, faſtned upon me divers extravagant things, as ſaid by me, which I never ſaid, (as will appear by inſpecting my Paper) to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe me as the <hi>greateſt Applauder of the Socinians,</hi> to <hi>take off my Sheeps Clothing,</hi> as he calls it, and <hi>put me on the Wolves:</hi> In Concluſion, devout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly praying God <hi>to preſerve his Church from ſuch as me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if I may have Liberty to anſwer his Queſtion, I will <hi>ſatisfy the World</hi> what <hi>Opinion I have</hi> both of <hi>all the Controverſies</hi> on Foot amongſt Engliſh <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> (for others I meddle not with) and particularly of thoſe of the <hi>Trinity and Incarnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:51847:36"/>
            <p>Firſt; <hi>As to all Controverſies amongſt Engliſh Proteſtants,</hi> I had in my Paper expreſs'd my Opinion, (and Affection too, <hi>p.</hi> 12.) perhaps with ſo much Moderation and Juſtice, that Mr. Dean thought not fit to take any notice of that Part. A happy Page of mine that; which alone, as far as I can perceive, eſcaped his good-natured Pen. Now the Sum of what I there ſaid, and ſuggeſted in other Places of my Paper, is this; that being we are all agreed in the common Chriſtianity, (thereby I mean the Apoſtles Creed and the Evangelical Law, which is the Sum of Holy Scripture) therefore both all private Doctors, except in the Schools, and all other private Perſons of what Party ſoever, ſhould let Controverſy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and keep their Minds to themſelves; refrain from expoſing one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and treaſuring up to one another Wrath againſt an evil Day; and ſhould bend all their Studies to reform their own and others Lives, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping God ſincerely according to their Conſciences, and bleſſing him for their preſent Liberty, and ſtudying to be quiet and to do their own Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs. This is my Senſe for the preſent, as to all Controverſies amongſt us Proteſtants in general.</p>
            <p>Then as to the two particular Doctrines by him mentioned, I have ſufficiently declared my Judgment already in this Paper. And I will add thereto only thus much, that my Opinion, as to the Controverſy betwixt Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> and me, as more fully I have ſet it forth in this Paper, is not by me newly taken up: For above one and thirty Years ago, being then a Preacher in <hi>Oxford,</hi> I publickly averr'd what I ſtill judg to be Truth, and what was not then taxed as Heretical, <hi>That he that ſhall affirm there are three Perſons in the Godhead, taking the word</hi> Perſon <hi>properly or ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as we do in ordinary Caſes, is guilty of a more grievous Error than he who altogether denies three Perſons:</hi> That both then I had, and ſince have ſubſcribed ſeveral times to the Church-Articles, which are plain enough in theſe Points: That otherwiſe, according to Law, as required, I have given Aſſurance of my Orthodoxy and Conformity; nor have I done or writ any thing by which I have retracted ſuch Subſcription or Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: and therefore I fear no Man's good Will as to <hi>reforming me out of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in Sum, I think it no Point of Nonconformity to deſire, and in my Sphere endeavour, promote or perſwade the reforming of ſuch things in our Church as keep many good Men out of it: And therefore, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding my Engagements to the Church, and Adherence thereto, I declare it as my Judgment, that the Church is bound upon her Faith, that is, upon her Promiſe often and on ſeveral Occaſions given, (eſpecially upon the Profeſſion ſhe has made in time of her Adverſity) to <hi>reform her Liturgy</hi> in divers Points, and to <hi>relax the Conditions of her Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:51847:36"/> as ſoon as <hi>a convenient State of Affairs</hi> offers it ſelf; of which I do not pretend to be a competent Judg, but am of opinion, <hi>much Delay will be dangerous:</hi> And in caſe, when a fit Seaſon offers it ſelf, the Church ſhould <hi>not reform or relax</hi> as aboveſaid, I fear ſhe will <hi>forfeit much of her Credit,</hi> and ſcarce be believed again in a Day of Tribulation, if it ſhould happen to her, which God forbid.</p>
            <p>Mr. Dean concludes with a Promiſe, that <hi>having vindicated the antient</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 32.</note> 
               <hi>Rights and Liberties of the Church, to defend the truly Catholick and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick Faith from the Aſſaults of Hereticks, he ſhall apply himſelf, as his leiſure ſerves, to the Defence of his Vindication,</hi> &amp;c. Alas good Man! Who ever went about any-wiſe to infringe thoſe Liberties? Is intreating Men a while to forbear dangerous Diſputes, and thoſe too ſo managed, as to expoſe both themſelves, the Truth and the Church, an Invaſion of their Liberties, nay and of the Rights of the Church too? Verily, if the <hi>Doctrine of three infinite Minds, their Self-conſciouſneſs and mutual Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciouſneſs,</hi> be not either <hi>cenſured by our Church,</hi> or <hi>generally diſowned by the Divines of it,</hi> it will ſoon be thought the Churches Doctrine. And this being about a Fundamental, perhaps ſome ſhortly will put the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, not, <hi>where was your Church and Faith before</hi> Luther, but where before Dr. <hi>Sherlock?</hi> till he wrote, you were not clear in Fundamentals. For my Part I have admired to ſee, firſt ſuch an Explication of the Trinity, and then ſuch a Reaſſertion of it, reviling and menacing an humble Man for Moderation, and diſſenting from Novelties and Heterodoxies, come forth with <hi>publick Licence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to return to the <hi>Need there was of the Dean's vindicating the anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Rights and Liberties of the Church.</hi> The Caſe is juſt the ſame, as if a Stranger in a time of War, accidentally finding a Friend of his engaged in a private hazardous Rencounter againſt experienced Dueliſts, and truſting to ſome new little Slights he had got, ſhould cry out to them all to hold their Hands; and by all means that he could uſe, ſhould perſwade them to deſiſt, telling them they had more need to be at their Prayers for Publick Peace, and to reſerve themſelves, Strength and Skill againſt the Common Enemy. Now it would be a pleaſant thing in ſuch a Juncture, to hear this Stranger's Friend exclaim againſt the kind Stranger, for at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting or infringing therein his and the publick Rights and Liberties of Mankind, (given forſooth to all by the Law of Nature) to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Even juſt ſo much Occaſion and Reaſon had Mr. Dean to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take a Vindication of the antient Rights and Liberties of the Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me. He <hi>will now apply himſelf,</hi> he ſays, <hi>as his leiſure ſerves, to the Defence of his Vindication of the Doctrine of the Holy Trinity and Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi> Now I muſt beg his Pardon, to ſay, I can conceive but <hi>two ways</hi>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:51847:37"/> in the World he has to vindicate it; the <hi>one,</hi> and that the moſt honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, is, to write ſuch a Piece as the Great St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> did in his latter Years, and which is commonly put in the Beginning of his firſt Tome, called his <hi>Retractations.</hi> The <hi>other,</hi> ſuch a ſhift as ſome Men now and then have been put to, to <hi>buy up or get into his Hands,</hi> if it were poſſible, <hi>all the Copies of his Book,</hi> and deſtroy them, that ſo his beloved Hypotheſis may die away. By either of theſe Means he may effectually vindicate his Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication: But if he be above this honeſt Advice, I cannot help it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Invitum qui ſervat, idem facit occidenti:</hi> I'ſhall not, God willing, trouble either the World or him any more with animadverting upon his Writings.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:51847:37"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51847:38"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:51847:39"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:51847:39"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:51847:40"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51847:40"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:51847:41"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:51847:41"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:51847:42"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:51847:42"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:51847:43"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:51847:43"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:51847:44"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:51847:44"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:51847:45"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:51847:45"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:51847:46"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:51847:46"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:51847:47"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:51847:47"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:51847:48"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:51847:48"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:51847:49"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:51847:49"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:51847:50"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:51847:50"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:51847:51"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:51847:51"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:51847:52"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:51847:52"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:51847:53"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:51847:53"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:51847:54"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:51847:54"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:51847:55"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:51847:55"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:51847:56"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:51847:56"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:51847:57"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:51847:57"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:51847:58"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:51847:58"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:51847:59"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:51847:59"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
